<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="230802">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/tz19PfklMdAdjxV9WArraA__thumb/img/debo694HgBaIBeNGyxu1ELUbQGA=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic3718275.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/tz19PfklMdAdjxV9WArraA__original/img/eFRt3o7W6YltnrkqpiSOKr2rKCw=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic3718275.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Azul" />
			
						                               				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="アズール" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="花磚物語" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="아줄" />
				<rulebook>Rulebook

A GAME BY MICHAEL KIESLING

Introduced by the Moors, azulejos (originally white and blue ceramic tiles)
were fully embraced by the Portuguese, when their king Manuel I, on a
visit to the Alhambra palace in Southern Spain, was mesmerized by the
stunning beauty of the Moorish decorative tiles. The king, awestruck by
the interior beauty of the Alhambra, immediately ordered that his own
palace in Portugal be decorated with similar wall tiles. Azul brings you,
a tile laying artist, to embellish the walls of the Royal Palace of Evora.

Game Setup
1. Give each player a player board (A). Flip your board to the side
with the colored wall. (See Variant Play to play with the gray
side of the player board). Each player must use the same side.

C

2. Take 1 scoring marker (B) and place it on space “0” of your
score track.
3. Place the Factory displays (C) in a circle around the
center of the table:
• In a 2-player game, place 5 Factory displays.
• In a 3-player game, place 7 Factory displays.

Center of
the table

• In a 4-player game, place 9 Factory displays.

4. Fill the bag (D) with the 100 tiles (20 of each color) (E).

5. The player who most recently visited Portugal takes the
starting player marker (F) and then fills each Factory
display with exactly 4 tiles randomly drawn from the bag.

Return any unused player boards, scoring markers and Factory
displays to the box.

B

A

F

Score track

E
D

Pattern lines
Wall
Floor line

2

Then, add the tiles you picked to one of the 5 pattern lines on
your player board (the first line has 1 space to hold 1 tile, the fifth
line has 5).

Object of the game
To be the player with the most points at the end of the game.
The game ends after the round in which at least one player has
completed a horizontal line of 5 consecutive tiles on her wall.

• Place the tiles, one by one, from right
to left in your chosen pattern line.
• If the pattern line already
holds tiles, you may only
add tiles of the same color to it.

Place tiles from right to left.
• Once all spaces of a pattern line are
filled, that line is considered complete. If you have picked up
more tiles than you can place in your chosen pattern line, you
must place the excess tiles in the floor line (see Floor line).

Your goal in this phase is to complete as many of your pattern
lines as you can, because during the following Wall-tiling phase,
you will only be able to move tiles from complete pattern lines to
their corresponding lines on your wall to score points.

Gameplay
The game is played over multiple rounds, each of which is
composed of three phases:
A. Factory offer

First turns example

1. On his turn, Peter picks
the 2 black tiles from a
Factory display and places
the remaining tiles in the
center of the table.

B. Wall-tiling

C. Preparing the next round

A. Factory offer

The starting player places the starting player marker in the
center of the table and then takes the first turn. Play then
continues clockwise.

2. Martin picks the yellow
tile from a Factory display
and places the remaining
3 red tiles in the center
of the table.

On your turn, you must pick tiles in one of the following ways:
EITHER

a) Pick all tiles of the same color from any one Factory display
and then move the remaining tiles from this Factory display
to the center of the table.

3. Then, Andrea picks these 3 red
tiles from the center of the table. As
she is the first one to pick from the
center, she also takes the starting
player marker and places it on the
leftmost space of her floor line.

OR

b) Pick all tiles of the same color from the center of the table.
If you are the first player in this round to pick tiles from the
center of the table, also take the starting player marker and
place it onto the leftmost free space of your floor line.

3

B. Wall-tiling

• In all later rounds, you must also comply with the following
rule: You are not allowed to place tiles of a certain color in
a pattern line whose corresponding line of your wall already
holds a tile of that color.

This phase can be carried out by all players simultaneously,
as they move tiles from their complete pattern lines over to
their walls.

Floor line

A) Go through your pattern
Complete
lines from top to bottom.
Incomplete
Move the rightmost tile of
each complete line to the
Complete
space of the same color in
Incomplete
the corresponding line of
your wall. Each time you
move a tile, score points immediately (see Scoring).

Any tiles you have picked that you cannot or do not want to place
according to the rules, you must place in your floor line, filling
its spaces from left to right. These tiles are considered as having
fallen on the floor and give minus points in the Wall-tiling phase.
If all spaces of your floor line are occupied, return any further
fallen tiles to the lid of the game box to store them for now.
This phase ends when the center of the table AND all Factory
displays contain no more tiles.

B) Then, remove all tiles from any pattern lines that now
have no tile in the rightmost space. Place them into the
lid of the game box to store them for now.

Then, continue with the Wall-tiling phase.

Once that is done, any remaining tiles on the pattern lines
stay on your player board for the next round.

A

B

C
Andrea picks 2 yellow tiles from a Factory display.
She is not allowed to place them in her second or third pattern line, as
their corresponding wall lines each have a yellow tile.

A) Peter's second pattern line is complete with 2 red tiles. So he
moves the rightmost tile of this pattern line over to the red space
on the wall (and immediately scores 1 point, see Scoring).

She may not place them in the fourth pattern line either, as there is
already 1 blue tile and she may not add tiles of a different color to it.

As the third pattern line is not complete, he ignores it.

She may, however, place 1 of them in the first pattern line and the excess
tile in the floor line (A).

From his complete fourth pattern line, he moves the rightmost
blue tile over to the blue space on the wall (and scores 1 point
immediately).

Or she may place both tiles in the fifth pattern line (B).

He ignores the fifth pattern line, as it is not complete.

She may even choose to place both tiles in the floor line (C).

B) Afterwards, he removes the remaining tiles from the second and
fourth pattern lines and places them in the lid of the game box.
The tiles in his third and fifth pattern lines stay on his board.

4

Scoring
Finally, at the end of the Wall-tiling phase, check if you have any
tiles in your floor line. For each tile in your floor line, you lose
the number of points indicated directly above it. Adjust your
scoring marker on your score track accordingly (however, you
can never drop below 0 points).

Each tile you move over to your wall is always placed on the
space matching its color and immediately scores as follows:
• If there are no tiles directly
adjacent (vertically or
horizontally) to the newly
placed tile, gain 1 point
on the score track.

Placing the
red tile gives
you 1 point.

• If there are any tiles adjacent, however, do the following:

First check if there are 1 or more tiles horizontally linked
to the newly placed tile. If so, count all these linked tiles
(including the newly placed one) and gain that many points.

Afterwards, remove all tiles in your floor line and place them
into the lid of the game box. Note: If you have the starting player
marker in your floor line, it counts as a normal tile there. But
instead of placing it in the lid, place it in front of you.

In this example, placing the
yellow tile gives you 3 points
for the 3 horizontally
linked tiles (including
the newly placed
yellow tile).

Then check if there are 1 or more tiles vertically linked to the
newly placed tile. If so, count all these linked tiles (including
the newly placed tile) and gain that many points.

Peter loses a total of 8 points as he has 4 tiles and the starting player
marker in his floor line.

C. Preparing the next round

In this example, placing the blue
tile gives you 3 points for the
vertically linked tiles.

If nobody has completed a horizontal line of 5 consecutive tiles
on her wall yet (see End of the game), prepare the next round.
The player with the starting player marker refills each of the
Factory displays with 4 tiles from the bag as in the setup. If the
bag is empty, refill it with all the tiles that you have placed in
the lid of the game box and then continue filling the remaining
Factory displays. Then, start the new round.

In this example, placing the
yellow tile gives you not only
4 points for the horizontally
linked tiles but also 3 points
for the vertical ones.

In the rare case that you run out of tiles again while there are
none left in the lid, start the new round as usual even though
not all Factory displays are properly filled.

5

End of the game
The game ends right after the Wall-tiling phase in which at least
one player has completed at least one horizontal line of
5 consecutive tiles on her wall.

CREDITS

Once the game has ended, score additional points if you have
achieved the following goals:
• Gain 2 points for each complete horizontal line of
5 consecutive tiles on
your wall.

Game Design: Michael Kiesling
Producer: Sophie Gravel

Development: Viktor Kobilke &
Philippe Schmit

• Gain 7 points for each
complete vertical line of
5 consecutive tiles on
your wall.

Art Direction: Philippe Guérin
Illustrations: Chris Quilliams

Graphic Design: Philippe Guérin,
Karla Ron &
Marie-Eve Joly

• Gain 10 points for each
color of which you have
placed all 5 tiles on your wall.

Coordination: Geneviève Blouin

The player with the most points on her score track wins the
game. In the case of a tie, the tied player with more complete
horizontal lines wins the game. If that does not break the tie, the
victory is shared.

Foreign Affairs: Andrea Ahlers &
Katja Wienicke
Editing: Sophie Gravel,
Viktor Kobilke

Marketing: Martin Bouchard
Development by:

Variant play

PLAN

For a slightly different game, use
the gray side of the player boards.
Rules are exactly the same as in the
normal game, except that when you
move a tile from a pattern line to
the wall, you may place it on any
space of its corresponding wall line.
However, as the game progresses, in
each of the 5 vertical lines of your
wall, no color may appear more
than once.

GAMES

© 2017 Plan B Games Inc.
No part of this product may
be reproduced without specific permission.

19 rue de la Coopérative, Rigaud, QC. J0P 1P0, Canada.
www.planbgames.com

Retain this information for your records.

6

Made in China.

</rulebook>
			
						               													<description>Introduced by the Moors, azulejos (originally white and blue ceramic tiles) were fully embraced by the Portuguese when their king Manuel I, on a visit to the Alhambra palace in Southern Spain, was mesmerized by the stunning beauty of the Moorish decorative tiles. The king, awestruck by the interior beauty of the Alhambra, immediately ordered that his own palace in Portugal be decorated with similar wall tiles. As a tile-laying artist, you have been challenged to embellish the walls of the Royal Palace of Evora.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;In the game Azul, players take turns drafting colored tiles from suppliers to their player board. Later in the round, players score points based on how they've placed their tiles to decorate the palace. Extra points are scored for specific patterns and completing sets; wasted supplies harm the player's score. The player with the most points at the end of the game wins.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2017" />
						               				<minplayers value="2" />
						               				<maxplayers value="4" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="1156">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="7" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="23" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="730" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="632" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="409" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="36" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="448" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="543" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="23" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="274" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="627" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="97" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="12" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="613" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="45" />
						               				<minplaytime value="30" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="45" />
						               				<minage value="8" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="279">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="14" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="73" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="137" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="43" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="7" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="73">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="73" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1009" value="Abstract Strategy" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1028" value="Puzzle" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1070" value="Renaissance" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2875" value="End Game Bonuses" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2041" value="Open Drafting" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2048" value="Pattern Building" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2002" value="Tile Placement" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2829" value="Turn Order: Claim Action" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="5614" value="Country: Portugal" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="70360" value="Digital Implementations: Board Game Arena" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="57039" value="Game: Azul" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="6485" value="Misc: Mensa Select" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="56419" value="Theme: Art" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="294345" value="Azul: Crystal Mosaic" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="235739" value="Azul: Joker Tiles" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="264017" value="Azul: Special Factories Promo" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="257590" value="Deutscher Spielepreis 2018 Goodie Box" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="293240" value="Super Power" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameimplementation" id="363247" value="Azul: Master Chocolatier" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameimplementation" id="346965" value="Azul: Queen's Garden" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameimplementation" id="256226" value="Azul: Stained Glass of Sintra" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameimplementation" id="287954" value="Azul: Summer Pavilion" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="42" value="Michael Kiesling" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="74074" value="Philippe Guérin" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="14057" value="Chris Quilliams" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="38363" value="Next Move Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="34188" value="Plan B Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="157" value="Asmodee" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="9068" value="Broadway Toys LTD" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="40415" value="Divercentro" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="15605" value="Galápagos Jogos" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="8820" value="Gém Klub Kft." />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="4785" value="Ghenos Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="1391" value="Hobby Japan" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="9634" value="KADABRA" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="6214" value="Kaissa Chess &amp; Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="8291" value="Korea Boardgames Co., Ltd." />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="5812" value="Lacerta" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="7992" value="MINDOK" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="40462" value="Orangutan Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="39" value="Pegasus Spiele" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="48279" value="SuperHeated Neurons" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="39774" value="Tower Tactic Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="9215" value="TWOPLUS Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="1466" value="Zvezda" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="50230" value="Бельвіль" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="67674" />
			<average value="7.78924" />
			<bayesaverage value="7.6761" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="62" bayesaverage="7.6761" />
																				<rank type="family" id="4666" name="abstracts" friendlyname="Abstract Game Rank" value="2" bayesaverage="7.67172" />
											<rank type="family" id="5499" name="familygames" friendlyname="Family Game Rank" value="9" bayesaverage="7.68641" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.14781" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="103017" />
			<trading value="528" />
			<wanting value="1055" />
			<wishing value="11464" />
			<numcomments value="8508" />
			<numweights value="1753" />
			<averageweight value="1.765" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>