<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="8730">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/8rt3Z_0ls2gwhCvaLuRaLg__thumb/img/oxXqlkaC_PXvWxWxe6S4Fzjn4zU=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic804598.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/8rt3Z_0ls2gwhCvaLuRaLg__original/img/7eeLwbiEIVZwFWTjZ6GA57iLLwM=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic804598.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Flying Colors" />
				<rulebook>Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

by
Mike Nagel

RULE BOOK
Version 3.1 2014

TAB LE O F C O N T E N T S
Glossary........................................................................	 2
1. 	 Introduction............................................................	 3
2. 	 Components........................................................... 	 3
3. 	 Core Rules............................................................. 	 5
	
3.1 Sequence of Play..............................................	 5
	
3.2 Wind Adjustment Segment.............................. 	 5
	
3.3 Command Determination.................................	 5
	
3.4 Determine Initiative.........................................	 6
	
3.5 Command Activation.......................................	 6
	
3.6 Movement........................................................ 	 7
	
3.7 Fire Combat.....................................................	11
	
3.8 Victory Determination.....................................	15

4.0	 Optional Rules.......................................................	17
	
4.1 End of the World..............................................	17
	
4.2 Anchoring........................................................	17
	
4.3 Grounding........................................................	17
	
4.4 Towing.............................................................	17
	
4.5 Defensive Fire.................................................. 	18
	
4.6 Shore Batteries.................................................	18
	
4.7 Awash Ships.....................................................	18
	
4.8 Initiative Cards................................................. 	18
5.0	 Ship Duels..............................................................	 21
6.0	 Scenario Alternatives.............................................	 22
Index............................................................................. 	 23

GMT Games, LLC • P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308
www.GMTGames.com
© 2014 GMT Games, LLC





Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

Glossary
Actual Rate: The historical rating for a ship

Gunboat: A small ship with a ‘T’ Relative Rate.

Audacity: A relative measure of the historical aggressiveness
displayed by both sides in a particular scenario. Higher numbers
positively modify many battle-related die rolls.

In Irons: A ship that is pointing directly into the wind and making no headway

Admiral: See Commanders

Backing Sails: A maneuver that allows a ship to expend movement points while remaining in its current hex
Beating: Sailing into a wind that is ahead of and off to one side
of your ship

Carronades: Introduced in 1779, their large caliber and lower
muzzle velocity increased a ship’s destructive power at close
range. In game terms, they positively modify a ship’s Firepower
number.
Chase Guns: Small guns, usually no larger than 18 pounders, used
to target an enemy’s rigging and force it to accept battle

Command Range: The value used to determine how far out a
commander’s influence extends from his location
Command Quality: The measure of a commander’s effectiveness in battle.
Commanders: Counters with portraits on them, used to command groups of ships

Damage Capacity: The number of hull hits that will cause a
ship to flip to its Damaged side, or to lose its firing capability if
already Damaged.
Damaged: A ship that has been flipped over to its back side. This
side has a stripe along the top of the counter.

Drifting: Ships that have no movement points owing to being
grappled, fouled, struck, dismasted. They will move one hex with
the wind during the Drifting segment.

Duel: Scenarios with only one or two ships on both sides that
use the Ship Duel map
Firepower: The number used to determine which column a ship
rolls on when using the Hit Results Table
Flagship: The ship that carries the fleet admiral

Fleet Admiral: The commander in overall charge of a fleet. His
death or capture will negatively modify a fleet’s break check.
Floating Battery: An anchored ship without masts. Cannot move
and ignores rigging hits, but otherwise treated as a ship.

Formation Command: A group of ships that are all facing the
same direction and are all within four hexes of at least one other
ship in the command

Fouled: Two or more ships tangled by collision. Neither can move
(except by drifting) until unfouled.
Full Broadside: Fire from a broadside that has a clear line of sight
from both the bow and stern of the firing ship’s counter
Galley: An oar powered ship

Group command: A group of ships activated by using a commander’s Command Range

Gun-Brig: A small ship with a ‘G’ Relative Rate.

Large Ships: Ship counters that take up two hexes on the map

Marine Value: The measure of a ship’s ability to send and repel
boarders
Markers: Informational pieces used to track the status of individual ships
Melee: Hand-to-hand combat that occurs after the Activation
Cycle between ships that are grappled together

Oared Vessels: Ships with a gray circle printed underneath their
Relative Rate
Out of Command: A ship that does not qualify to be included in
either a group or formation command

Partial broadside: Fire from a broadside that has a blocked line
of sight from either the bow or stern of the firing ship’s counter
Port: The left-hand side of a ship as one faces forward

Rake: Fire from an enemy ship that occupies a hex in the target’s
Rake Line

Rake Line: The line of hexes originating at the bow and stern of
a ship and extending outward fore and aft, respectively

Rank: The value used to determine seniority for commanders. 3
= highest, 1 = lowest.

Reaching: Sailing with the wind behind and off to one side of
your ship
Relative Rate: The value used to determine a ship’s Firepower
number. 1 = highest, T = lowest.
Running: Sailing with the wind directly behind your ship

Shore Battery: A fixed gun position on shore. Hull hits can
destroy it.
Side Slipping: A maneuver that allows a ship to alter its course
without turning

Small Ships: Ship counters that occupy only one hex on the
map
Starboard: The right-hand side of a ship as one faces forward

Sternway: A maneuver that must be performed by a stationary,
non-Drifting ship before it can resume forward motion

Struck: A ship that has surrendered, is no longer an enemy target
and cannot sink

Swivel/Pivot Guns: Guns that are mounted so as to be able to
fire outside the normal broadside arc
Tack: A turn that involves moving the bow of the ship through
the wind
Taken Aback: Another term for ‘In Irons’

Wear: In game terms, any turn a ship makes that is not a tack

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC



Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

rection as the compass number indicates (e.g. Direction 1 faces
toward the ‘xx01’ edge of a Fleet map).
A Fleet map is configured in a manner specified in the scenario
setup. Generally speaking, the long edges of the map sections
are mated together so that the lighter areas (indicating shallows,
shoals or solid ground in some scenarios) match properly. It’s a
general rule that Map A mates with Map B, B with C, C with D
and so on. Each map does, however, incorporate a blank edge,
allowing players to freely create their own configurations for
custom scenarios.

1.0 Introduction

2.1.2 The Duel Map: The Duel map is only used for the smallest
of engagements. The map is defined by a large hexagon. Darker
“entry areas” are printed adjacent to each side of the hexagon
and numbered for setup purposes. The use of these entry areas
is defined in the rules section on Duels (5.0). At the center of the
map is a directional compass. Like the Fleet maps, this compass
is used during setup to indicate starting wind direction. NOTE:
The Duel Map is available with Serpents of the Seas (Flying
Colors, Vol. II).

This version of the Flying Colors rules (version 2.00) represents
a split of the game rules from accompanying scenarios, allowing
the rules manual to be updated and corrected without an impact
upon the scenarios included in each series game. These rules
should be used with all games in the Flying Colors series and
replace all previous versions. Changes in the game mechanics
from the previous versions are indicated in the section heading by
using a star (H) symbol. Players familiar with previous rules versions are still encouraged to read through the entire rulebook.

2.2 Playing Pieces

Flying Colors is a simulation of naval warfare in the period dating
roughly from 1750 to 1825. Unlike most other games depicting
this topic, this game simulates large fleet actions as well as individual ship duels, without the minutiae of shipboard operations.
This allows players to compare the qualities of the forces and
their commanders. The game is intended to play quickly, with
minimal rules referencing.

There are three types of playing pieces used during a Flying
Colors scenario: Ships (of which there are both large and small
types), Commanders and Markers. Any number of Commanders
and Markers may be stacked on a single Ship. The specifications
of each are provided below.
Front
Relative Rate

2.0 Components

Each game in the Flying Colors series contains a set number of
components. The actual quantities and identification of these
components may vary from game to game and expansion to
expansion. For an exact component list, please refer to the
Play Book provided with each (or the rules manual in the
original Flying Colors for the content of that volume). The
types of components that may be included in each game or expansion are as follows:

Back
(Damaged Side)

Ship’s Name
Marines

Damage
Capacity
Gunnery and
Actual Rate

VP value

2.1 Game Maps

2.2.1 Ships: These units represent the vessels involved in a battle
or duel. Ships are categorized according to the number of guns
carried, with a ‘1st Rate’ ship being the largest and carrying 100
guns or more. 1st through 4th Rate ships are considered ‘Ships of
the Line’ and are represented with 1 x 1/2-inch pieces. Smaller
ships (5th, 6th, Gun Brigs and Gun Boats) are represented by 1/2
x 1/2-inch pieces. Ships are two-sided, with the reverse used to
depict a ‘damaged’ ship (a color bar is printed on the back for
easy reference during play). Each ship is printed with its name
and the following measures used during play:

2.1.1 The Fleet Map: One or more of these maps are used to depict the body of water upon which a naval engagement is fought.
Each of these maps includes a letter identifier in the upper-right
corner, along with a directional compass.

2.2.1.1 Relative Rate: this is an indication of the weight of a
ship’s broadside (its firepower or how much iron it throws out).
Possible values are 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, Gun-Brig (G) and Gun-Boat
(T). This value is further modified during the Fire Resolution
Process (3.7.7) if the ship has a symbol printed underneath its
Relative Rate. A yellow symbol indicates that the ship is an overgunned 1st Rate (120 guns or more). A white symbol indicates
that a ship is relatively heavily armed for its Rate. A black symbol indicates that it is relatively lightly armed for its Rate. A red

There are two types of maps used with Flying Colors. The first is
a “Fleet” map used for fleet actions. The second is a “Duel” map
used when playing with only one or two ships on a side. This latter
map depicts a much smaller playing area, thus allowing the game
tables to be conveniently placed upon the same sheet. Each map
is printed with a hexagonal grid used to regulate movement.

The compass is used to orient ships during set up and to indicate
initial wind direction. A ship or the wind faces in the same di-

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC



Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

symbol indicates that a ship is primarily armed with carronades
only and is therefore limited to firing inside carronade range (5
hexes). A hexagonal symbol indicates that a ship carries a substantial carronade battery in addition to its long gun armament. A
square symbol indicates that this supplemental carronade battery
is exceptionally heavy (such as the U.S.S. Constitution and her
equivalents). These colors and symbols are used in conjunction,
so a ship with a relative Rate value bounded by a white hexagon
would have a heavier broadside than is usual for its rate together
with a substantial battery of carronades.
NOTE: Some lighter vessels do not have a Relative Rate value
on their damaged (flipped) side. Once damaged, these ships
cannot attack in any way.
2.2.1.2 Damage Capacity: This value is an indication of how
many hits the ship’s hull can sustain, and still be an effective
firing platform. When the number of hits a ship has taken equals
or exceeds this value, it is flipped over to its “damaged” side,
carrying over any excess and applying it to the Damage Capacity printed on a ship’s reverse. Some ships have their Damage
Capacity bounded by a grey circle. These ships are oared vessels (galleys, xebecs, etc) and do not rely on the wind to move
(see 3.6.3).
2.2.1.3 Marines: This value indicates a ship’s ability to send
and repel boarding parties. A ship whose Marine value has been
reduced to one may only attempt to board an enemy vessel whose
original or reduced Marine value is also one (unless specified
otherwise through Special Rule).
2.2.1.4 Victory Points: This value indicates the worth of the
vessel when determining the victor after a battle as well as when
creating custom battles. Note that many of the smallest ships
do not carry a Victory Point value. They are pests that are often
easily swept aside, but dangerous if ignored.
2.2.1.5 Gunnery and Actual Rate: These values indicate the
actual number of guns carried by a ship and its real, defined Rate.
These values do not affect play and are provided as information
only.
2.2.1.6 Ship Color: The color of a ship piece indicates its
nationality. On the larger ships, the nation’s naval jack is also
included. Check the Play Book included in the game for a list
of nationalities included in that game.
Rank

Name

Front

Command
Range
Command
Quality

Back

VP value

2.2.2 Commanders: These half-inch pieces represent the fleet
commanders available during each Fleet action. The commanders
are the heart of the game’s command and control system, as they
allow a fleet to act in unison. Commanders are not used in Duels.
The reverse of a Commander unit indicates his ‘wounded’ status
(with decreased values). Like Ship units, Commander units are

colored to indicate nationality and marked with several measures
used during play:
2.2.2.1 Rank: The small number in the piece’s upper left corner
indicates a Commander’s Rank. The higher this number is, the
greater the Commander’s Rank. Generally speaking, a ‘3’ is a
fleet admiral, a ‘2’ a divisional admiral and a ‘1’ is a commodore. If a fleet includes two or more admirals tied for the highest
rank, the scenario setup indicates which is the fleet admiral (an
important distinction for victory determination).
2.2.2.2 Command Range: The upper number to the right of the
Commander portrait represents the distance at which he can issue
orders. All ships falling within this radius may be considered
‘in command’ (per the Command rules under 3.3.3). The higher
this number, the more effective a Commander is in keeping his
fleet under control.
2.2.2.3 Command Quality: This value represents the experience and effectiveness of a Commander. This value is used to
modify actions of the ship he occupies, but is primarily used in
determining a fleet’s initiative.
2.2.2.4 Victory Points: On the reverse of a Commander unit is
an indication of how many Victory Points he is worth if captured
or killed during the action.
2.2.2.5 Audacity Rating: In addition to the statistics noted on the
individual units, each nationality in a scenario is given an ‘Audacity’ rating. This value is a reflection of how the side behaved
historically in battle, and is an indication of the overall quality
and flexibility of the fleet and the tenacity of its commanders.
2.2.3 Markers: A large number of markers are included in the
game to track the status of each ship. The use of each type of

Hull
Hit

Rigging
Hit

Dismasted!

In Irons!

Battery

Captured!

Anchored

Full
Sails

On Fire

Aground

Adrift

Fouled

Struck!

Fired
Starboard

Fired
Port

Fired
Both

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Out of
Vulnerable Command
Command
Split

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
marker is covered within the rules that require their use. The
number of markers provided is not a game limit. If additional
markers are required, players may create their own, or use similar
markers from other games.

2.3 Status Sheets

If players want to avoid using a lot of markers to indicate ship
status, status may be tracked on paper using status sheets available for download on www.gmtgames.com. Write each ship down
prior to play and cross off each extraneous damage box above
the initial values tracked. As the ships take damage, cross off
damage boxes as necessary. The status sheets can also be used
to track fired and moved status. Ship status sheets are open to
examination by all players.

2.4 Turn Track

Only the Duel map includes a track to mark the current Turn
number. For Fleet actions, use a hex column along an edge of
the map out of the way of the action. Use hex xx01 to mark the
first turn, xx02 to mark the second and so on.

2.5 Game Dice

One 10-sided die is used. Treat a roll of ‘0’ as a zero (not a
ten).

2.6 Game Scale

The hexes on the map are roughly 100 meters across and each
game turn represents five to ten minutes of time.

	
	
	
	

B.	
C.	
D.	
E.	



Activate Ship(s)
Move (and Fire) Ship(s)
Disengage Ship(s)
Select another Command or a single Out-of-Command
Ship (players alternate activating commands or Out-ofCommand ships until all have been activated)

V.	 Melee Combat

VI.	 Ship Status Check
	 A.	 Ship Fires
	 B.	 Drifting
	 C.	 Striking
	 D.	 Sinking
	 E.	 Remove Broadside markers
VII.	Victory Determination

General Overview of Play: After checking for any wind change
each player determines which ships are in/out of command and
who commands each formation. A roll of the die determines
which player determines who will be the first active player. The
active player chooses a formation or single out-of-command ship
and moves/fires each ship individually. After all the activated
ships have completed their actions, play shifts to the other side
to activate a formation or single out-of-command ship. Players
alternate activations until all ships have been activated. After all
ships have moved, any melees are resolved. Lastly, each ship’s
status is checked, victory conditions are checked and markers
removed as necessary.

3.2 Wind Adjustment Segment

3.0 Core Rules

Flying Colors is, for all intents, two games in one. The ‘Fleet’
game allows the recreation of major naval actions with dozens
of ships on a side. Owing to the number of ships involved, much
of the minutiae of shipboard activities are swept away in favor of
quick play. The ‘Duel’ game only involves one or two ships per
side, and so the focus is returned to tactical ship handling decisions (otherwise, Duels would be little more than an exercise).
The Core Rules covers all of the basic mechanics of movement
and combat used for the Fleet game. Further rules sections on
Initiative Card use (4.8) and the Duel Rules (5.0) supersede the
rules in this section. Any mechanics not referenced in these additional sections use the Core Rules as written.

3.1 Sequence of Play

The sequence of play is the order in which you perform the game
functions the rules provide. The sequence of play is repeated for
a number of turns noted in each scenario.
I.	 Wind Adjustment Segment (not on turn 1)
II.	 Command Determination
III.	 Initiative Determination
IV.	 Activation Cycle
	 A.	 Select Command or a single Out-of-Command Ship

Beginning on turn 2, roll a die during the Wind Adjustment
Segment. If the roll is a 0, roll another die and check the Wind
Adjustment Table.
PLAY NOTE: The Wind Change table is designed for northern
hemisphere scenarios. For those players creating their own
scenarios, invert the terms ‘clockwise’ and ‘counter clockwise’
as necessary when fighting south of the equator.

3.3 Command Determination

Victory or defeat at sea during this period was often dependent
upon the fleet commander’s flexibility, and his ability to provide
clear and concise commands. During the Command Determination phase, players indicate which ships are under or out of
command.
3.3.1 Commanders: Each fleet is usually assigned one fleet
admiral and one or more subordinate commanders, depending on
the scenario. Commander units represent these individuals, and
are placed with ship units. Commander units are marked with
a Rank value next to their names. The higher this number, the
greater the rank. More than one commander can be stacked on
a single ship (although for the fleet’s sake, you probably don’t
want to do this).

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC



Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

3.3.2 Flagships: The ship that holds a fleet admiral at the beginning of the scenario is considered the flagship. Conversely, a ship
designated as the flagship at the beginning of a scenario holds
the fleet admiral (for those instances where more than one leader
share the same highest rank). An admiral may not leave a ship
unless it is on its damaged side, dismasted, or on fire.
3.3.3 Commands: Groups of ships are called commands. All
ships that are part of a single command are activated together
and must all move before any enemy ships are allowed to move.
Commands are formed by either of two methods:
1) Group Commands: All ships that are within the Command
Range of a Commander may be part of that individual’s command. Command Range is calculated by counting the number of
hexes between either the bow or stern hex of the commander’s
ship to either the bow or stern hex of a ship in question. When
counting the hexes in this range, do not include the commander’s
ship. Hexes containing enemy vessels may not be counted, but
players may count around them. If a ship is within range of more
than one commander the owning player chooses which formation
the ship will activate with.
DESIGN NOTE: The Command Range concept is not merely the
ability to broadcast commands to ships via signal flags. Rather,
it takes into account the ability of a fleet commander to issue
pre-engagement plans and orders in such a manner as to allow
a fleet to maintain its cohesion once the fleets engage.
2) Formation Commands: Ships may be set up on the map in
such a way that they are in a formation. To be in a formation:

•	 Each ship in the formation must be within 4 hexes of at least
one other ship in the same formation. No enemy vessel may
occupy one of these hexes, but the hexes may be counted
around an enemy vessel.
•	 All the ships in the formation must be facing in the same
direction, and
•	 One of the ships within the formation must include a
commander.
There is no limit to the number of ships that may be included in a
Formation Command. When activating a Formation Command,
each ship may be activated in any order.

3) Out of Command: Ships not conforming to either of these
conditions are considered ‘Out Of Command’ (see 3.5.1). Commands are determined at the beginning of each turn, so a ship may
fall out of command during a turn, but is still considered part of
a command until the end of the turn. All ships are considered “in
command” during the first turn of any scenario and are part of
the nearest Formation command. Exception: Ships of a side that
begins a scenario without commanders are all Out Of Command
for the duration of the scenario (unless specified otherwise by
the scenario’s rules).
3.3.4 Determining Commands: Players must determine which
ships are in which commands, and if any ships are out of command. Starting with the player who lost the initiative in the previous turn (or the fleet with the lowest Audacity for the first turn),

indicate a number of ships that make up a specific command, per
the command definition rules noted above. The other player then
indicates the ships in a specific command. The players continue
to define commands using this back and forth process until all
commands have been defined. After one player has indicated
his final command, the other player may divide his remaining
ships into more than one command if desired and possible. If
necessary, use the Command Split markers to indicate where
one command ends and another begins. These markers serve no
other purpose than to help players keep track of commands. Any
ships that cannot be included in a command are marked with an
‘Out Of Command marker.’ A ship holding a commander unit
is always in command.

3.4 Determine Initiative

After commands have been determined, each player rolls a die
to determine initiative. Players add the current command quality
of their fleet admiral to the die roll (or the fleet’s Audacity if the
fleet admiral is dead or captured). The player with the higher
modified die roll wins the initiative for that turn. In the case of a
tie, the winner is that side with the higher Audacity rating.

3.5 Command Activation

The player who won the initiative for the turn then either selects
a command or a single out of command ship to be activated, or
passes the initial activation to his opponent. The players then
alternate activating commands or single out of command ships
until all ships have been activated. If one player still has ships
to activate after his opponent has activated all of his own ships,
he must make several activations in a row until all ships have
been activated. Each command and out of command ship may
be activated once per turn.
3.5.1 Out of Command Ships: Ships that are out of command
may be limited in what they can do when activated. When each
out of command ship is selected, a die is rolled and compared
to the fleet’s Audacity rating (deducting the fleet admiral’s
Command Quality if he is not dead or captured). If the result is
less than or equal to the Audacity, the ship may function as if
it were in command. If the command check fails, the ship may
not end its move adjacent to an enemy ship (if possible) or fire
when activated unless it starts (is activated when) adjacent to
an enemy ship.
3.5.2 Out of Command Activation Exception: Generally a
player must always activate something when it is their turn. The
only exception to this is a player may “pass” on activation if his
opponent just activated an Out of Command ship. A player may
continue to pass after each Out of Command activation, but must
activate one of his own commands or Out of Command ships as
soon as his opponent has either activated a full command or has
run out of activations.

3.6 Movement

When a ship is activated as part of a command activation or when
a single out of command ship is chosen, the ship is moved through
the map grid from one hexagon, through one or more adjacent

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
hexagons, depending on the ship’s Movement Rate. Hexes may
not be skipped over while moving.
3.6.1 Facing: When placed on the
map, a ship occupies one or two
hexes, depending upon its size. The
front of a ship unit must always face
a hex side, not a vertex. If facing
comes into question, the opposing
player selects the appropriate facing.
Surrounding the ship unit are several
hex sides. The front most hex side
is the ship’s bow hex side. The rear
hex side is its stern hex side. For a
small ship, both hex sides to its left
and right are its port and starboard
hex sides, respectively. For a large
ship, the hex sides bordering the
middle hex on both sides are its port and starboard hex sides,
respectively. The accompanying diagram identifies port and
starboard hexes for game purposes.
3.6.2 Movement Rates: Depending upon its relationship to Wind
Direction, a ship will have a number of Movement Points (MPs)
that it must expend in that turn (Exception: collisions, anchoring,
grappling and running aground). MPs may not be saved for later
turns. A ship’s position relative to the wind direction is described
by the following nautical terms:
•	 Running: the ship is pointing in the same direction as the wind
(4 MPs).

•	 Reaching: the ship is pointing 60 degrees to the left or right
of the wind direction (5 MPs).

•	 Beating: the ship is pointing 120 degrees to the left or right of
the wind direction (2 MPs).
•	 Taken Aback: the ship is pointing directly into the wind
direction (0 MPs). Also called ‘In Irons!’



•	 Small Ship Speed Enhancement: Ships with an Actual Rate
of 5 or 6 (not G or T) on their undamaged side may optionally
add one MP to their allotment upon activation, provided that
they are not dismasted. Once declared, this enhancement may
not be retracted. This enhancement is not considered a bonus
and is applied prior to reducing the movement rate owing to
rigging damage. Ships that are in irons or that have 0 MPs may
not use the small ship speed enhancement
•	 Full Sails: A ship may drop or raise Full Sails at the end of its
movement if desired. A ship may also begin a scenario at Full
Sails if desired. Ships operating at Full Sails can move further
during a turn, but are more susceptible to rigging damage in
combat. A ship that has suffered six rigging hits or is damaged
may not raise Full Sails and loses them if currently raised.
When a ship is attacked while under full sails, add two (2) to
the result die roll when rigging is targeted. When using Full
Sails, increase the movement values of a ship by the following
amounts, depending upon their position relative to the wind:
Beating +1; Running +2; Reaching +3.
•	 Weather Effects: Some scenarios may include a Weather
Condition option, either ‘Breezy’ or ‘Calm.’ When Breezy,
increase a ship’s MPs by one (provided it already has at least
1 MP) and add one to the Weather Change die roll. When
Calm, decrease a ship’s MPs by one and deduct one from the
Weather Change die roll. In addition, Drifting movement (see
3.6.8) occurs only on even numbered turns when Calm.

•	 Oared Ships: A gray circle bounding a Damage rating
indicates a ship equipped with oars (galleys, xebecs, etc).
These ships may always expend up to 2 MP regardless of their
position relative to the wind or the status of their rigging. They
never receive a Small Ship Bonus for movement and may
never raise Full Sails. When activated, they may opt to take
their full movement allowance and act as a normally rigged
vessel, or they may opt to take only two movement points
and act as an oared vessel. Ships acting as oared vessels may
rotate one hex-side freely prior to movement and/or per hex
entered. Moving into a bow hex costs 1 MP. Moving into a
stern hex costs 2 MP. An oared vessel may also rotate to face
any direction in its starting hex at a cost of 2 MP.
DESIGN NOTE: Some players may wonder why all ships share
the same speed ratings, and why the MPs are static. The answer
is: that level of detail is beyond the scope of this game design.
Ultimately, this design is about fleet action, not individual ship
design and capability.
3.6.4 Moving a Ship: A ship is
moved by advancing it directly
across its bow hex side, into the
hex in front of its bow. Doing so
expends one of its MPs.

3.6.3 Movement Rate Modifiers: There are several ways in
which a ship’s basic movement rates may be modified:

3.6.5 Wearing: Wearing is the
process of turning a ship without moving its bow through the
wind. It is a relatively easy maneuver, but one that can be time

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC



Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
Tacking during the same turn. Place an ‘In Irons!’ marker on any
ship that does not complete a tack. Ships that are ‘In Irons’ are
considered adrift for Grappling (3.6.16) purposes.
3.6.7 Side Slipping: Ships that find themselves in a Reaching
position at any point during their move may execute a Side Slip
at a cost of 2 MP. A ship that Side Slips moves one hex to leeward (with the wind) and forward, without turning (it maintains
a Reaching position). A ship may continue to Side Slip so long
at it has sufficient MP to do so. A Side Slipping ship may never
enter a hex occupied by another ship (exception to 3.6.11).

consuming when trying to move a ship up-wind. After expending
a MP, a ship may rotate its stern left or right into an adjacent
hex. A ship may only rotate its stern one direction in each hex it
moves into (it cannot wear twice in the same hex during the same
activation). Unless ‘Tacking’ (see below), a ship may never turn
its bow directly into the wind while turning. Turning may or may
not consume MPs, depending upon the direction turned relative
to the wind (double these costs if at Full Sail, 3.6.3):
•	 Reaching to Running:	1 MP
•	 Reaching to Beating:	

2 MP

Any other changes in direction do not cost MPs. A ship with only
1 MP (due to rigging damage) may wear in place from Reaching
to Running. It may not wear from Reaching to Beating.

3.6.8 Drifting: Ships that are Grappled (3.6.16), fouled (3.6.15),
dismasted (3.7.11), or struck (3.7.11) have no MPs (exception:
oared vessels may still move when dismasted, 3.6.3). In these
cases, move those ships one hex with the wind during the Drift
segment of the Ship Status Check phase. If the wind state is
‘Calm,’ Drifting movement occurs only on even numbered turns.
Place an ‘Adrift’ marker on ships with zero MPs when activated
to indicate this status. A drifting ship may never cause a collision.
If a drifting ship will move a ship into a hex already occupied
by another ship, the drifting ship is left in place.
3.6.9 Sternway: When attempting to move a non-Drifting ship
that has no movement points owing to being ‘In Irons’ or having
sufficient rigging hits as to lower its MPs temporarily to zero, roll
a die (deducting the Command Quality of a commander stacked
with the ship). If the result is greater than four (4), the ship must
move with the wind one hex and then at the player’s option may
be rotated on its bow hex 60 degrees to the left or right. If the
result is less than or equal to four, the player has the option to

PLAY NOTE: Moving into a quicker position relative to the wind
will not gain any movement points until the next game turn. Moving into a slower position relative to the wind will not lose any
movement points until the next game turn.
3.6.6 Tacking: Tacking is the process of turning a ship by moving
its bow through the wind. This is a more efficient way of moving
up-wind, but it is also a risky maneuver, particularly in combat.
Failure to Tack successfully may leave a ship ‘In Irons’ and unable to move! Only ships that begin their move while Beating
may perform a Tack (i.e. it cannot be done mid-turn). To Tack a
ship, follow this procedure:
1) Declare a Tacking maneuver for a Beating ship by rotating the
ship on its stern to face directly into the wind. Note that this is
the opposite of Wearing! Small ships rotate in place.
2) Roll a die and check the modified result on the Tacking Table.
The table indicates if the ship ends up ‘In Irons’ or is able to
continue the Tacking maneuver.
3) If the result from the Tacking Table is anything other than
‘In Irons,’ continue to rotate the ship through the wind so that it
is now Beating on the opposite side of the wind. If the Tacking
table indicates the receipt of any MP, the ship must continue to
maneuver normally until all are expended. Since a ship can only
Tack at the beginning of its turn, it cannot perform any additional

TACKING EXAMPLE: The example above shows how a
ship might move two hexes into the wind using Tacking. The
process takes two turns to complete (unlike Wearing, which
takes several turns to achieve the same result). To initiate its
first Tack, the ship rotates its bow into the wind. A die is then
rolled and the result checked on the Tacking table. In this
example, two MPs result. The first action (requiring no MPs)
is to rotate the ship’s bow away from the wind. The two MPs
are then used to advance straight ahead. In its second turn,
the ship attempts another tack, but in the opposite direction.
The resulting maneuver places the ship two hexes closer to
the wind.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
rotate the ship to the left or right without moving it backwards or
may still allow the ship to drift one hex before it is rotated. Moving backward as part of Sternway does not cause collisions (treat
it as Drifting, 3.6.8). Dismasted ships may not use Sternway. A
ship making Sternway may never turn into Irons.
3.6.10 Backing Sails: A ship may ‘reduce’ its movement rate by
‘backing sails.’ When doing so, a ship expends 1 MP in a hex
without moving forward. Only 1 MP may be expended in a hex
to back sails. Expending a MP to back sails counts towards the
turning requirement (i.e. a ship may Wear in place). A ship may
not back sails prior to Tacking, but may do so after a successful
Tacking result. The maximum number of MPs a ship may use
to back sails is one half of their initial movement rate, rounded
down (i.e. a ship with 1 MP cannot back sails).



ship may change facing while its bow hex overlaps one of the
hexes of the enemy counter, but where this will result in the active ship turning on to the inactive ship’s Rake Line (3.7.7.6),
this constitutes a Pass-Along (3.6.14) and certain restrictions
apply. Where the active ship enters the enemy ship’s hex from
the bow or stern hex in the Facing diagram, this also constitutes
a Pass-Along.
3.6.13 Small Ship Pass-Through: The process of passing through
a small ship works the same as a large ship (above), with the
following enhancement: When entering a small ship’s hex from
either side, the active player declares which end (bow or stern) of
the inactive ship is being crossed. The inactive player may oppose
this movement by rolling on the Evasion table. If successful, the
inactive player decides which end the active ship crosses.

EXAMPLE: A ship begins its turn reaching, and (for whatever
reason) has a movement rate of six (6). The ship may expend up
to three (3) MPs to back sails. It expends its first MP to back sails
and turns into a beating position (at a cost of 2 MP). It expends
its fourth MP to advance one hex. It expends its fifth MP to back
sails. It expends its sixth and final MP to advance one hex. The
ship has spent six MPs but only advanced two hexes.
3.6.11 Stacking Ships: Ships may pass through hexes occupied
by other ships, provided that they do not end their move occupying the same hex as another ship. If it is impossible to end an
activation without having one ship stacked upon another, then the
active ship is moved back to the last position it occupied before
entering an occupied hex and it must check for Collision (3.6.15).
Players must make every effort to avoid Collision by turning,
backing sails etc. If doing so results in the active ship being forced
into a less than optimal position, then that is unfortunate.
3.6.12 Large Ship Pass-Through: If an active ship has enough
MPs to clear a large enemy ship, it may pass directly through
that ship counter from either side. Once the bow hex of the active
ship moves clear of the enemy ship, then the active ship may
turn (where it has sufficient MPs) without restriction. An active

EXAMPLE: The Fortitude can pass right through the small ship’s
hex, passing across the bow or stern of the ship.
H 3.6.14 Pass-Along: When a ship enters a hex occupied by
another ship from the bow or stern hex, the active player declares
which side of the inactive vessel the active ship wishes to pass
along. If the inactive ship is an enemy and is not Dismasted,
Grappled, Fouled, Anchored, or Grounded, the inactive player
may oppose this movement by rolling on the Evasion table. If
successful, the inactive player decides which side the active ship
actually passes along. Where the active ship wishes to turn onto
the inactive ship’s Rake Line having entered from either side,
the active player first resolves any Fire Combat (3.7) before
declaring which side the active ship wishes to pass along. If the
active ship conducted an attack from the Rake Line, then it must
pass along the inactive ship’s far side i.e. with the active ship’s
fired broadside facing the inactive ship. DESIGN NOTE: This
avoids a ship “doubling back” unrealistically to be able to fire
both broadsides in a single pass.
If the active ship did not conduct an attack from the Rake Line,
then the inactive player may oppose the active player’s choice
by rolling on the Evasion table unless either of the following
exceptions applies:

EXAMPLE: The Fortitude can pass through the Superbe. Once
its bow reaches hex B it can turn to port or starboard without
restrictions. The Fortitude can also turn to starboard when its
bow reaches hex A. If it turns to port in hex A, then this consitutes a Pass-Along and certain restrictions apply (3.6.14).

a) If the active ship decides to pass along the near side of the
inactive ship without conducting an attack from the Rake Line,
the inactive player cannot oppose this. DESIGN NOTE: Where
an active ship approaching from the port or starboard beam
decides to hold its distance, the inactive ship would not be able
to force the active ship onto the opposite beam.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

10

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

b) If the active ship turned onto the Rake Line having entered
from the middle hex of the port or starboard side of the inactive
ship (i.e. the hex containing the word ‘port’ or ‘starboard’ in the
Facing diagram (3.6.1), then it must pass along the near side of
the inactive ship. DESIGN NOTE: This avoids the active ship
in effect cutting the other ship in half. A moving ship is either
making a turn around an inactive ship’s bow or stern.

3.6.15 Collisions: If it is impossible to avoid ending one ship’s
move in a hex occupied by another ship, the ships may collide
and become fouled together. A drifting ship may never cause a
collision. Whether or not a collision occurs, the moving ship ends
its turn in the position prior to overlap. Ships may not collide on
purpose! If any movement is possible through the creative use
of wearing and/or backing sails that would allow the avoidance
of a collision, that move must be taken. In addition, if it seems a
collision check is unavoidable, the moving ship must back sails
as often as possible in order to burn the maximum number of MPs
prior to impact. To check for a collision, roll a die and reference
the result on the Collision table. Deduct the Command Qualities
of any commanders available on the moving and ‘target’ ships.
Increase the die roll for the moving and target ship’s Relative
Rate (+1, +2 or +3 each), if the moving or target ship is damaged
(+1 each) and the number of MPs the moving ship was unable to
expend. If the modified result is greater than 9, the moving ship
becomes fouled with the first ship it could not move through.
Place a ‘Fouled’ marker across both ships to indicate this status.
Fouled ships are ‘adrift.’
H 3.6.16 Grappling: In order to board an enemy ship to capture
it, the enemy ship must be grappled. An active ship may attempt
to grapple if it is on a parallel course (facing the same or opposite
direction) with an enemy ship that is Adrift, In Irons, Dismasted,
Anchored, or Fouled, and it either a) occupies one of the enemy
ship’s port or starboard hexes (see diagram in 3.6.1), OR b) is
conducting a pass-along of the enemy ship (see 3.6.14). Ships
that are fouled may attempt to grapple the ship(s) with which
they are fouled.

In “A” the Hercules enters the opposing ship’s hex directly
astern. The active player declares which side he will try to
pass along and then the opposing player tries to oppose this
by rolling on the Evasion Table.
In “B” the Fortitude turns in hex B onto the opposing ship’s
rake line. If the Fortitude fires her starboard broadside before
turning then the Fortitude must pass along the Superbe’s port
side (B-1). If the Fortitude does not fire it may pass along either
side but the opposing player can only oppose the movement
if the Fortitude chooses the far side (i.e. passing along the
port side of Superbe). It can not oppose the pass along on the
near side (B-2).
At “C” the Fortitude moves onto an enemy rake line from
abeam and turns to starboard in hex C. Once the Fortitude
reaches hex C, she must pass aong the near side of the Superbe.
The Fortitude will only be able to fire its port broadside during
the pass-along.

In either case, the moving ship may attempt to Grapple once
during its activation. If the enemy ship is not already Grappled,
Fouled, Anchored, or Grounded, it may attempt to evade by
rolling on the Evasion table and applying appropriate modifiers.
If the target ship successfully evades, the moving ship must
continue its movement. Otherwise, the moving ship may attempt
to grapple by rolling on the Grappling table. If successful, the
Grappling ship ends its movement at that point. If the moving
ship is conducting a pass-along, place it in one of the port or
starboard hexes of the immobile ship instead (whichever side
it is passing along). If that hex is already occupied by another
ship, the Grapple attempt automatically fails and the active ship
must continue moving.
If a Grapple attempt succeeds, place a Grappled marker astride
each ship. Firing is allowed defensively against grappling attempts. Only the defending ship may fire. The moving vessel
may fire (assuming it hasn’t already) simultaneously with the
grappling attempt. This and defensive fire are considered simultaneous, as if the ships were already grappled together. This fire
is considered Point-Blank (3.7.9)..
H 3.6.17 Fouled/Grappled Effects: Ships that are Fouled and/
or Grappled may not move when activated. Instead, they may
attempt to disengage when activated. Ships that remain Fouled
and/or Grappled at the end of the turn will drift during the Drifting
segment of the Ship Status Check phase. Fouled/Grappled ships
may not target each other’s rigging, and they gain no benefit from

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
wind direction when firing at the hull.
3.6.18 Disengaging: When activated, a Grappled and/or Fouled
ship may attempt to cut free from any one enemy ship. Ships desiring to disengage must roll a die and refer to the Disengagement
table. If successful, remove all Fouled and/or Grappled markers
from the disengaging ship and the ship to which it was attached.
3.6.19 Anchoring: Anchoring is allowed only by scenario special
rules. In such cases, a ship may start a scenario at anchor, or may
drop anchor during the course of play. Anchoring is the only way
to purposely halt movement. An anchored ship that fires applies
a +2 die roll modifier on the Hit Results Table.
Dropping Anchor: A ship that wishes to anchor must declare
this action at the start of its activation. Only ships that are not at
full sails may anchor. The ship rolls on the Sternway table instead
of undertaking normal movement. Normal modifiers apply, but
anchoring ships do not rotate after making this roll. On a modified
roll of 4 or less, the ship may either anchor in place or choose to
drift 1 hex before doing so. On a roll of 5 or more, the ship must
drift 1 hex before dropping anchor. Place the anchor marker on
either the bow or stern hex for large ships, and directly on the
ship counter for small ships. A ship may fire as normal during
this process, but the +2 bonus does not take effect until after the
anchor marker is placed.
Rotating at Anchor: Anchored ships may rotate one hexside per
turn beginning on the turn after they drop anchor. (Exception –
Oared ships may rotate any number of hexsides.) When activated, a
large ship may rotate around either its bow or stern hex (whichever
is anchored). Small ships rotate in place. Any ship that fires and
rotates during the same activation resolves its fire with a Relative
Rate one greater than that listed on the firing ship’s unit.
Slipping Anchor: A ship that wishes to slip anchor must declare
this action at the start of its activation. The anchored marker is
removed and the +2 bonus is immediately lost (i.e. before any
firing). The ship receives Movement Points equal to half those
shown on the Movement Table (round fractions down to a
minimum of 1MP) and may not use Full Sails or Anchor during
this activation. On the turn following the ship may maneuver
normally. Ships that are In Irons when slipping anchor must roll
for Sternway (3.6.9) and apply the results as their only movement
for the turn. On the next turn they receive half Movement Points
with the restrictions described above. On the turn following they
may maneuver normally.

11

3)	When firing either offensively or defensively, the firer determines the amount of firepower available that can be hurled at
the target.

4)	The firer then selects the shot target (Rigging or Hull). If there is
the possibility of a Rake, the firer determines if the shot is a Rake.
5) The firer rolls a die to determine the result of the shot.

6)	Any damage resulting from the shot is applied against the target
ship and the firing vessel marked with the appropriate Broadside
Fired marker.

7)	The active vessel, after applying any damage from defensive
fire may then return fire against the originally selected target, 	
or may withhold the declared attack.
8)	The active vessel then continues its move (and may possibly 	
fire again at another target).
3.7.1 Fire Limitations: A ship may fire twice per turn, once from
each side of the ship. Ships may only fire EITHER after they
have expended at least one MP (unless the ship has remained immobile owing to it being Grappled, Fouled, at Anchor, or Adrift)
OR at any point after declaring a Tacking or Sternway maneuver.
Note that Backing Sails expends a MP, therefore fulfilling the
MP expenditure requirement. A ship may fire its guns before or
after it has completed a free turn (wearing into a better position
relative to the wind) after expending a MP. A ship may fire both
broadsides simultaneously, or at different times during its move.
Each broadside is resolved separately.
Masked Broadsides: Ships that sail close to other friendly ships
may lose their ability to fire due to obscured lines of sight. If
at any point during the Activation Cycle, a ship has a friendly
vessel in one of its port or starboard hexes, or in its own hex
during a Pass-Along, that ship must mark as fired the broadside
facing the friendly ship. This occurs for both active and inactive
ships. In the case of a Pass-Along, the broadsides to be marked
as fired will depend on which side the active ship passes along
the inactive one.

3.7 Fire Combat

The goal of Fire Combat is to damage an enemy vessel in such
a manner as to either slow it down (through Rigging damage)
or to sink it or cause it to ‘strike its colors’ (e.g. surrender). The
Fire Combat mechanics follow this process:

1)	An active (moving) ship selects a target that is within both range
and line of sight (e.g. there’s at least a chance of hitting it).
2)	The enemy may conduct Defensive Fire against the active ship,
either by the target vessel or another friendly vessel within range
and line of sight of the moving ship.

LINE OF SIGHT EXAMPLE: The darkened ships are Line
of Sight obstacles (enemy or friendly ships). Ships A through
D are enemy ships. The St. Albans has a clear Line of Sight
to A, a partial LOS to B and D, and no LOS to C. Note that
the LOS follows a hexspine in the case of D.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

12

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

3.7.2 Mixed Fleets: Generally, smaller ships (5th Rate and smaller)
were not part of ‘the Line’ and therefore did not partake directly in
the larger naval actions. Instead, they were used as scouts, flankers,
and message ships. It was not considered prudent (or gentlemanly)
for a ship of the line to fire upon smaller ships. These smaller ships
were, however, known to engage larger ships if there was a reasonable chance of survival and the acquisition of a grand prize. When
smaller (half-inch) ships are in play with full-sized ships, the latter
may not fire upon the former (even defensively) until the smaller
ship has fired upon and inflicted damage to a ship of the line (4th
Rate or larger). Small ships may engage each other freely.

3.7.5.1 Swivel/Pivot Guns: Gunboats (having an undamaged
Relative Rate of ‘T’), oared vessels (gray circle bounding the Hull
rating) and vessels noted as being pivot armed in the Scenario
instructions may fire at any target outside of their broadside arc
and not on the Rake Line with a –1 modifier to the Hit Results
Die Roll. Firing at a target wholly or partially on the Rake Line
incurs a –3 modifier. Such fire expends the broadside attack
of the side of the firing ship nearest to the target. Swivel/Pivot
armed ships never suffer from Partial Broadsides due to firing
arc reasons. Where the target lies on the Rake Line, the firing
player may choose which broadside is expended.

3.7.3 Line of Sight: In order to fire at an enemy ship, a clear line
of sight must be available between the attacking and target ships.
The hexes occupied by friendly and enemy ships (not just the unit
counters or ship outlines) block line of sight. To determine if line
of sight is available, draw imaginary lines between the centers of
both of the attacking ship’s bow and stern hexes or from the center
of a small ship unit’s hex to both of the bow and stern hexes of
the target ship or the center of a small ship’s hex. If any of these
lines cross over a hex occupied by a different ship, line of sight
is blocked along that direction. Note that line of sight may be
drawn between two hexes (along the hex spine) so long as one
of the two hexes is unoccupied. If it is not possible to draw lines
of sight between all of the attacking and defending ship hexes,
but at least one clear line of sight is available, an attack is still
possible. These instances are treated as ‘partial broadsides’ (see
3.7.7.4). A firing ship always has a full line of sight to a ship that
it is stacked on or under (fully or partially).

3.7.5.2 Chase Guns (optional): Vessels with undamaged Relative Rates of ‘G’ or higher may only fire outside of their broadside
arc at targets that lie on the Rake Line (bow and stern chasers).
Fire Chasers by rolling a single die and comparing the result to
the range between the two vessels. If the result is greater than or
equal to the range, then one Rigging hit is scored. The die roll is
modified by Audacity of the firing ship and any Firing modifiers
due to Initiative cards (4.8) currently in play. No other modifiers
apply to chase guns. If the range is five hexes or less and an
unmodified ‘9’ is rolled, then another Rigging hit is scored. Firing chase guns does not expend a broadside, but bow and stern
chasers may only be fired during a ship’s activation, they may
not be used for defensive fire.

3.7.4 Arc of Fire: A ship may only fire at targets that lie fully or
partially within the firing (or, ‘broadside’) arc of their cannon
(exception: Chase Guns, 3.7.5.2). A ship’s arc of fire starts from
the center of its bow and stern hexes (or the center of its sole
hex, in the case of small ships) and extends outward through all
hex sides to either side of the ship. All of the hexes that lie fully
or partially within this arc are subject to attack. The Broadside
diagram below indicates a ship’s firing arcs.

DESIGN NOTE: The armament of Gunboats was often mounted
on pivots or swivels which, when combined with the maneuverability of such vessels under oars, meant that most of their firepower could be brought to bear in almost any direction. Larger
vessels (Gun-brigs and above) generally mounted a few cannon at
the bow and stern in order to target the Rigging of enemy vessels
being chased or to escape a pursuer. The rule for Swivel/Pivot
Guns is mandatory when vessels of the relevant type are involved
in a scenario, the rule for Chase Guns may be used optionally
for any scenario if both players agree.
H 3.7.6 Wind Effects: Wind affects both a ship’s movement rate
as well as its ability to fire. With respect to the latter, a ship is
firing ‘with the wind’ (‘leeward’) if: a) it is reaching or beating,
and b) the firing broadside is on the opposite side of the ship
from which the wind is blowing. A ship is firing ‘into the wind’
(‘windward’) if: a) it is reaching or beating, and b) the firing
broadside is on the same side of the ship from which the wind
is blowing. Similarly, ships that are grappled or fouled gain no
benefit from wind direction, regardless of their actual position
relative to it.
EXAMPLE: A ship is sailing in Direction 1. The wind is blowing
in Direction 2, so the ship is Reaching. Its starboard broadside
will be firing with the wind and its port broadside will be firing
into the wind. The same would be true if the wind was blowing
in Direction 3, in which case the ship would be Beating.

3.7.5 Targets Outside Arc of Fire: Ships may only fire at targets
outside their broadside arc of fire as described below. Firing in
accordance with this section can trigger defensive fire or be used
as defensive fire in response to an incoming attack as normal.

3.7.7 Fire Resolution Process: As indicated, Fire resolution
is a multi-step process. All fire combat should follow the steps
outlined below.
1) Target Selection: After expending at least one MP (unless
otherwise immobile, 3.7.1), the active ship selects a Target vessel.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
The Target vessel must be within Range and (at least partially)
within Line of Sight. If a ship is grappled or fouled with a ship
within one of its broadside arcs (even partially) it may only target
that vessel when firing through that specific broadside arc.
2) Defensive Fire Interruption: As soon as an activated ship has
selected a target, but before its firepower is determined, any one
opposing ship within Range and Line of Sight of the activated
ship may fire defensively at it. The opposing ship may be in or
out of command (Exception: Grappled Fire, 3.7.9). Defensive fire
may only come from a ship that has not fired from its appropriate
broadside. The fire procedure for Defensive Fire follows the same
steps as normal fire (Exception: Rakes, 3.7.7.6). After Defensive
Fire has been resolved, the activated ship may opt to hold its fire.
If the activated ship holds its fire, and attacks later in its turn, it
is subject to additional Defensive Fire interruptions.
3) Range Determination: The maximum distance at which an
enemy ship can be attacked is ten hexes (exception: ships with
a Relative Rate value bound by a red symbol have a maximum
range of 5 hexes). This limit includes the target hex but does
not include either the bow or stern hexes of the firing ship. It is
possible that the range between the attacking and the target ship
will be different, depending on whether you are tracing range
from (or to) a ship’s bow or stern hex. When this situation arises,
use the shortest of the possible range values.
4) Attack Type Determination: A ship may make one of two
types of attacks, depending on its position relative to the target.
The Attack Type must be determined before firing:

•	 Partial Broadside: If only one of a larger (two-hex) target
ship’s hexes lay within the firing ship’s arc of fire, that attacking
ship fires with a Relative Rate one greater than that listed on
the firing ship’s unit. Partial Lines of Sight may also cause
partial broadsides.

•	 Full Broadside: If all the target’s hexes lie within the attacking
ship’s line of sight and arc of fire, the attack is conducted
without modifying the attacker’s Relative Rate.
5) Target Type Selection: Prior to firing, the attacking player
must determine if he is firing at the target ship’s hull or rigging.
This selection indicates which target table should be used during
the fire resolution process. Inflicting damage on a ship’s hull will
reduce its capacity to fire as well as cause it to eventually sink.
Inflicting damage on a ship’s rigging reduces its movement and
is more likely to start fires. A ship that is grappled or fouled may
only target an enemy’s hull.
6) Rake: The row of hexes that extends along the length of a
ship is called its “Rake Line.” The rake line is further defined as
bow- and stern-Rake Lines that end at both the bow and stern
hexes of the ship in question. Whenever any hex of an active
ship occupies this line (even when crossing through an enemy
ship), it may attempt to acquire an additional Rake benefit when
firing at the target. The likelihood of a Rake occurring depends
upon the distance to the target, the part of the Rake Line crossed
(bow or stern), and the quality of the ship firing.

13

Rake Roll: A Rake roll, if possible, is made immediately after
selecting a Target Type. A Rake results from a modified die roll
of four (4) or less. Modifications to the die roll are as follows:
–?:	 Fleet Audacity
–?:	 Available Commander Quality
+?:	 Range in hexes to the target ship
–2:	 If the firing ship is crossing the stern rake line
Rake Effects: All Hull damage resulting from a rake is increased.
Stern rakes double Hull damage. Bow rakes increase Hull damage
by 50% (dropping fractions).
Partial Rakes: If, owing to blocking ships, a line of sight cannot
be drawn from both hexes of the firing ship to the closest hex of
the target ship, the Rake is considered “partial” and firepower is
determined as if the firing ship’s Relative Rate were one value
higher (i.e., a relative rate of ‘3’ uses the ‘4’ row on the Firepower
Determination table).
Defensive Fire vs. Rakes: Only a moving vessel may perform
a rake. A vessel defending from a rake may fire a full broadside
if both hexes of an attacking vessel fall within the defender’s
broadside arc. Otherwise, a partial broadside is fired. An active
ship crossing over another ship is assumed to be on the “approach” side of the inactive vessel (the first side of the inactive
ship crossed) for the purpose of firing defensively.
Rake Limits: If a ship successfully performs a rake, it must
completely exit the target’s rake line and then re-enter it in
order to rake the same target again during the same activation.
Exiting is defined as moving both the bow and stern off of the
enemy’s rake line.
7) Firepower Determination: The ability of a ship to project
force is referred to as its Firepower. A ship’s Firepower is determined by cross-referencing its Relative Rate with the range to
the target on the Firepower Determination Table. Follow these
steps to determine a ship’s Firepower:
a) Determine Rate Row: Use the (1) row if the active ship’s
Relative Rate is bound by a yellow symbol, otherwise use the
row corresponding to the ship’s current Relative Rate (1-6, G
or T). Once the correct row is found, shift up one or more rows,
depending upon the following modifiers:
•	 shift up by one if the attack is a Partial Broadside or Partial
Rake.
•	 shift up by one for each six points of Hull Damage on the firing
ship.
•	 shift up by one when firing during a Tack.
•	 shift up by one when firing with Full Sails.
•	 shift up by one when firing while Dismasted.
•	 shift up by one when firing while On Fire.

EXAMPLE: A ship with a Relative Rate of 3 with 14 Hull Hits
(two shifts) making a partial Broadside (one shift) would have
a modified Relative Rate of 6.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

14

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

NOTE: If the cumulative shifts result in a Relative Rate falling
off the table (i.e. more than ‘T’), the attack has no effect and the
ship’s broadside is marked as fired.
b) Determine Base Firepower: Cross-reference the Rate row value with the range to the target to find the base firepower value.
c) Determine Actual Firepower: Modify the base firepower
value by the following cumulative factors:

+1	 If the firing ship’s Relative Rate value is bound by a white 	
symbol and the unmodified firepower rating on the Firepower Determination table is shaded
–1	 If the firing ship’s Relative Rate value is bound by a black 	
circle (on the counter) and the unmodified firepower rating
on the Firepower Determination table is shaded
+?	 Firing ship’s fleet Audacity rating
+2	 Point-Blank fire (3.7.9)

+2	 (Optional) if broadside is being fired for the first time. (This
rule requires some extra record-keeping.)
+#	 Cumulative carronade bonus

	 –1	 if firing outside broadside arc and not down own Rake
Line.
	 –3	 if firing down own Rake Line.

Cross-reference the modified die roll with the previously determined firepower value. Use the appropriate target type columnrigging or hull. The result indicates what type of damage is done
to the target ship (if any). An ‘H’ result indicates a Hull hit. An
‘R’ result indicates a Rigging hit. A number to the left of a letter code indicates a number of hits of that type (example: 2HR
translates as two Hull hits, and one Rigging hit). An asterisk (*)
noted as part of the damage results indicates the chance of a fire
breaking out on the target ship (3.7.11). Use the Hull and Rigging
hit markers to keep track of a ship’s damage.
3.7.8 Excess Damage: If the modified die roll is greater than
12, apply the remainder as if it were an additional die roll on the
unselected target type (Ex: If a modified die roll of 14 against
a Hull target would result in the application of a die roll of 2
against Rigging).
3.7.9 Damage Limits and Modifications: Circumstances may
call for a limitation on damage or damage may be enhanced.
•	 Point-Blank Fire: A ship may fire while passing through a
hex occupied by an enemy ship. Fire by both ships involved
receives a +2 firepower modifier against the target. Fire of this
type is a Full Broadside. When moving across an enemy ship
the active player may check for Rake.

EXAMPLE: The two ships (above) are both firing at a target that
is three hexes away. Both ships are firing a full broadside and both
have less than 6 Hull hits-so their Relative Rate is unmodified.
Britannia’s firepower value (at a range of 3 hexes) is 12, which
is decreased by one to 11 because of the black circle. Ajax’s firepower value of 8 is increased to 9 because of its white circle.
d) Determine Hit Results: After determining firepower, consult
the firing ship size-specific (large or small ship) Hit Results Table
and roll a 10-sided die. Modify the die roll for the following
reasons (to a maximum modification of +5):
•	
	
	
	
	
	
•	
	
	
	

If the Target Type is the Rigging:
+1	 if French ship firing
+1	 if firing to windward
–1	 if firing to leeward
+2	 target at Full Sail
–2	 during Calm conditions
If the Target Type is the Hull:
+1	 if British ship firing
+1	 if firing to leeward
–1	 if firing to windward

•	 Other Modifiers
	 +2	 if firing while anchored
	 +2	 battery firing

•	 Grappled/Fouled Fire: If a ship fires upon a vessel to which
it is grappled and/or fouled and the opposing vessel can return
fire, the opposing grappled vessel is the only vessel that may
return fire. In these cases, fire from both ships is considered
simultaneous (apply the results of combat after both ships have
fired) and benefits from the +2 Firepower bonus of point-blank
fire (see above). When firing at a grappled or fouled opponent
only the hull may be targeted. Grappled/fouled ships gain no
benefit from wind direction, regardless of their actual position
relative to it. Note that grappled/fouled ships may only fire if
allowed by their individual arcs of fire. It is possible that the
position in which ships are grappled/fouled may only allow
partial broadsides or rakes. If a ship is fouled or grappled in a
position to rake or be raked, the attempt is automatic.
3.7.10 Carronades: Carronades were shorter, large bore guns
fired at close range, first used by the British in 1779. Depending
on the year in which a scenario takes place, ships may be armed
with a variety of carronades. These provide cumulative Firepower
increases on the Firepower Determination table. Use the table
below to determine these modifiers.
Type of Fire	

British fire, range 3 or less	
British fire, range 1 or less	
American fire, range 3 or less	
American fire, range 1 or less	
French/Dutch fire, range 3 or less	
Spanish fire, range 1 or less	
© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

1779-1786	
+1	
+1	
n/a	
+1	
n/a	
n/a	

1787-1826
+1
+1
+1
+1
+1
+1

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
H Russian/Turkish fire, range 1 or less	
Hexagonal Rate, range of 3 or less	
Square Rate, range 3 or less	

n/a	
+1	
+2	

+1
+1
+2

EXAMPLE: A British ship with a hexagonal Relative Rate value firing at a range of one hex would increase their Firepower by +3.
3.7.11 Damage Effects: As ships sustain Rigging and/or Hull
damage, the effects of the damage mounts and begin to degrade
a ship’s ability to maneuver and fight.

H Rigging Damage: For every three Rigging hits (ignore remainders) reduce a ship’s movement rate by one and apply a -1
modifier toward Tacking rolls. These penalties take effect the next
time the ship is activated, unless the ship has sustained 15 rigging
hits in which case it is Dismasted. A Dismasted ship comes to an
immediate halt (even if in the middle of a move) and may only
drift for the remainder of the game. During the Drift segment
of the Ship Status Check phase, every immobile ship drifts one
hex with the wind, so long as the drift will not cause a collision.
Drifting ships never cause collisions, although they may be collided with. As long as a drifting ship has not had its Hull damage
capacity reduced to zero, it may still be activated to fire.
Hull Damage: Ships have two possible states, damaged and
undamaged. Ship units begin the game displaying their undamaged side (unless special scenario rules dictate otherwise). When
a ship unit has sustained enough hull hits to equal or exceed its
damage capacity, flip over the unit to its damaged side (carrying
over any excess hull damage.). Example: A ship with a damage
capacity of four on its undamaged side sustains six points of hull
damage. Flip the ship over to its damaged side, carrying over
two damage points. Any Rigging damage is carried over in full.
The damaged side indicates reduced attributes (Relative Rate,
Marines, etc.). Every six Hull hits (ignore remainders) increase
a ship’s Relative Rate by one (meaning the number of available
guns is actually decreased). A damaged ship that has only three or
fewer Hull hits remaining is marked with a ‘Vulnerable’ marker
to indicate it may strike its colors.
Striking: A ship is vulnerable to strike under two conditions. If
either condition is met during the Striking segment of the Ship
Status Check phase, the ship must roll on the Strike Table:
•	 It is damaged and has three or fewer hull hits remaining.

•	 It is both dismasted and within five hexes of an enemy ship or
shore battery which is closer to the dismasted ship than any
friendly ship or shore battery. The friendly ship/shore battery
must have at least one hull hit remaining and may not have
struck.

If vulnerable due to hull damage, a ship strikes on a modified
die roll of ‘4’ or more. If vulnerable due to being dismasted, a
ship strikes on a modified roll of ‘6’ or more. If a ship meets both
conditions, it strikes on a modified die roll of ‘2’ or more.
For all striking rolls, reduce the die roll by the fleet’s Audacity rating and the Command Quality of the highest ranking commander
on board. Ships that have struck may not move or fire. They will
drift one hex during the Drift segment of the ships Status Check

15

phase. A struck ship cannot evade a grappling attempt and does
not melee. Struck ships that have been grappled are automatically captured during the Melee Combat phase. Struck ships will
not sink. Struck ships may not be part of a formation, nor may
commanders on them create formations.
Sinking: A ship is vulnerable to sink when it has no hull hits
remaining. A ship sinks upon a die roll equal to or less than its
original rate (or a 7 for G and T ships). Add one to the die roll if
the rate is bounded by a black dot. Deduct one or two from the
die roll if the rate is bounded by a white or yellow dot, respectively. A ship may no longer fire if its Hull damage capacity is
reduced to zero. When a ship sinks, any commanders aboard are
eliminated. Also, any ships currently fouled (but not grappled)
with the sinking ship are dismasted. Note: This rule does not
mean the ship has gone to the bottom; rather it has become so
awash as to be completely unreliable as a vessel.

Fires: During fire combat, any result that includes an asterisk (*)
indicates that a fire may have started on the target ship. Roll a
die. If the result is less than or equal to the number of hull and/or
rigging hits sustained by that attack, the ship has caught fire. A
fire never ignites when a ‘9’ is rolled, regardless of the amount
of damage taken. During the Ship Fires segment of the Ship
Status Check phase, check the status of the fire by rolling on the
Fire table. The fire may be extinguished, cause further damage,
or even spread to fouled and grappled ships nearby. If the result
is a 5-9, regardless of whether the fire is able to spread to other
ships, roll another die. A roll of ‘9’ results in the burning ship
exploding and sinking! Remove the exploded ship and any ships
fouled or grappled to it from the game. Note: this differs from a
ship simply sinking, which does not affect ships grappled to it.
Commander Transfer: When a ship is dismasted, on its damaged side or is on fire, any non-wounded commander on that
ship may attempt to transfer to another ship. If there is more than
one commander on a ship, each must transfer individually. Successfully transferred commanders move to the nearest, friendly,
undamaged ship that is not on fire. If two or more ships are
equidistant, the owning player may choose which one receives
the commander unit. Transfers may be attempted only when a
ship holding a commander is activated (e.g. before the ship is
moved or fired). In order to transfer, roll a die and add the fleet’s
Audacity Rating. If the result is greater than or equal to seven
(7), the commander may leave the ship.

Commander Casualties: Whenever a ship carrying one or more
commanders suffers damage (including Melee losses 3.7.12.d
and fire control, 3.7.11, but excluding Chaser fire, 3.7.5.2), roll a
die for each commander on board. A roll of ‘9’ results in a commander being wounded. Flip the commander to his ‘wounded’
side. A wounded commander has his command Range and his
Quality reduced. When receiving a wound, roll another die. If
this die is less than or equal to that side’s Audacity Rating, the
commander has been killed and is removed from the game. A
commander may be wounded more than once, but there is no
further effect. When this occurs, simply roll again to see if the
commander is killed (in other words, a ‘9’ must be rolled before
there is a chance for death).

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

16

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

Commander Capture: A commander is automatically and irretrievably eliminated if a ship on which he is located is sunk or
captured. A commander on a ship that strikes must be captured
before the leader is eliminated. Until a struck ship is captured, any
commander aboard may attempt to transfer his flag normally.

3.8 Melee Combat

Opposing forces may capture enemy ships by boarding them. A
captured ship is generally worth more victory points than one
that is sunk.
3.8.1 Melee Process: After all ships have been activated, Melee
Combat may take place between ships that are grappled together.
Only ships that are grappled to enemy ships (or friendly captured
ships) may engage in melee combat. The player who won the
initiative at the beginning of the turn selects the order in which
melee combats are resolved. After selecting a group of two or more
grappled ships, the initiative player indicates whether he will attack and how Marine points will be allocated (if necessary). If the
initiative player declines to attack, the non-initiative player has the
option to attack and allocate Marine points. If the non-initiative
player declines to attack, no melee combat takes place.

attacker cannot muster at least as many Melee Combat points as
the defender, no attack may take place. Regardless of the number
of Melee Combat points the attacker can muster, no more than
four dice may be rolled (a maximum ratio of 4:1).
MELEE COMBAT VALUE EXAMPLE: The attacker has a total
Melee Combat value of 11 to the defender’s value of 4. Assuming that the attacker is storming a ship that has a better Relative
Rate, the ratio would be 2 to 1. If the attacker had better Relative
Rate, the ratio would be 3 to 1.
H d) Melee Combat Resolution: To resolve Melee Combat, each
player rolls a number of dice equal to his ratio value. The values
of each side’s dice should be summed together and compared.
One of the following will occur:
•	 Defender’s roll is equal to or higher than Attacker’s: The
defender has repulsed the attacker’s assault. There are no
effects to any ships involved in the Melee, though they do
remain grappled.
•	 Attacker’s roll is higher: The attacker’s assault has succeeded
and the defender’s ship has been captured. Place a Captured
marker on the defender’s ship.

a) Melee Rate Limitation: Regardless of the background color
of an attacking or defending ship in melee, the current relative
rate of a defending ship may not be more than two points larger
than the current relative rate of the attacking ship (i.e. a 4th Rate
ship may not attack a ship greater than a 2nd Rate; a 1st Rate may
only be captured by a 2nd or 3rd Rate; etc.). Gunbrigs (G) and
Gunboats (T) are considered rates 8 and 9, respectively.

3.8.2 Nelson’s Patent Bridge: If a captured ship is fouled with
another enemy ship, the capturing side may immediately try to
grapple the second ship and attempt to capture it with any remaining Marines through the Melee Combat process. Continual
attacks may be attempted against additional fouled enemy ships,
so long as each melee attack is successful and the attacker has
sufficient Marines to initiate an assault.

b) Determining Melee Combat Value: Prior to engaging in
melee combat, the melee combat value of each ship needs to be
determined. To find this value, check the Marine value of a ship
and add the command quality of all commanders on board. If the
attacker has a ship grappled to one or more enemy ships, he may
divide the ship’s Melee Combat value as desired between each
enemy ship (example: If a ship whose Melee Combat value is 5
is grappled to two ships, it may use three points against one of
the ships and two against the other). At least one point must be
assigned to each attack or the enemy automatically captures the
attacking ship. If two or more attacking ships are grappled to a
single defending ship, all of the attacking ships’ Melee Combat
values are totaled into a single value. If two or more attacking
ships are grappled to two or more defending ships (two on two,
three on four, etc.), the attacker indicates how he will allocate
his Marine points. Marine points on defending ships are not allocated-they remain with the ship to repulse any attack.

HISTORICAL NOTE: This was how Nelson gained fame at
the Battle of Cape St. Vincent. The San Nicolas had collided
and fouled with the San Jose. Nelson boarded and captured
the former and before the crew of the San Jose could rally, he
captured her as well!

c) Melee Combat Ratio: Once the Melee Combat values of
both the attacking and defending ships have been determined,
compare the attacking value to the defending value in terms of
a ratio, rounding to the nearest whole value in favor of the side
with the lower Relative Rate (increased by one for each six hull
hits sustained) or the defender if tied. This ratio indicates the
number of dice rolled by each side in determining the victor in
Melee Combat. The defender always has one Melee Combat die,
regardless of the number of Melee Combat points available. If the

H 3.8.3 Captured Ships: Captured ships may not fire offensively
or defensively, nor may they initiate Melee Combat. They may be
part of a command for the purposes of activation and movement.
Captured ships that are not part of a command must attempt to
move away from the nearest enemy ships if possible. Captured
ships may be recaptured if they are boarded and lose the ensuing
Melee Combat. A captured ship has an inherent Marine value of
one, regardless of what is printed on the ship unit itself. Captured
ships are attacked in the same manner as non-captured ships. If a
ship is recaptured, the Captured marker is removed but the ship
still retains a Marine value of 1 regardless of the printed value on
the counter (players may need to make a note of this). Recaptured
ships share the same attributes as captured ships if enemy forces
attack them again. Recaptured ships may conduct fire attacks
normally (their crews have been released). Captured ships never
check for Sinking if they have no Hull hits remaining.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

3.9 Victory Determination

A game ends when the scenario’s listed number of turns is
completed (at which stage victory points are tallied for ships
captured, sunk, and damaged), or as soon as one of the opposing
fleets breaks (3.8.3).
3.9.1 Victory Points: The values of ships at the end of a game
are tallied thus:
•	 Captured enemy ships: 2x Victory Point Value
•	 Sunk enemy ships: Victory Point Value
•	 Damaged or Dismasted enemy ships: 1/2 x Victory Point Value
(retain fractions)
•	 Killed commander: Victory Point Value

Undamaged ships sailing off a map edge are considered damaged
and score victory points only for the side with the lower audacity.
(DESIGN NOTE: The side with the higher Audacity is the aggressor, who will lose victory points if his ships sail off the map).
Damaged ships sailing off the map edge are scored normally. A
ship is only worth its maximum value (so a damaged, captured
ship is only worth the value of a sunk ship). Surviving undamaged ships that were not captured are not worth any points, nor
are ships that were recaptured during play (although the latter
denies points to an opponent).
3.9.2 Victory Levels: A battle that lasts through the last turn
without one side breaking is a normal victory for the side with
the higher victory point total. If the totals are tied, the side with
the lower Audacity rating gains a marginal victory.
3.9.3 Break Check: On the first turn that a side loses a vessel
(sunk, struck, captured or sailed off the map edge) and each turn
thereafter, make a die roll on the Break-off Table during the
Victory Determination Segment. Do not include T-Rated vessels
unless at least one of the fleets involved in a battle is entirely
composed of T-Rated vessels. If the result is less than or equal
to zero (0) that fleet has decided to cut and run. The non-running
fleet wins a substantial victory. It is possible that both sides may
withdraw simultaneously. In these cases, use the accumulated
victory points to determine a winner of a marginal victory. A
fleet that loses all of its commanders automatically breaks. A roll
should still be made for the opposing fleet if there is a chance of
it breaking as well (thus, possibly giving a normal or marginal
victory to a retreating fleet).
a) Break-off Modifiers: The following modifiers are used to
make a Break-off more or less likely:

•	 Reduce the die roll by one if there are more undamaged ships in
the opposing fleet, or by two if the ratio of undamaged enemy
ships to the rolling side is two-to-one or greater. Do not count
T-Rated vessels unless at least one of the fleets involved in a
battle is entirely composed of T-Rated vessels.
•	 Increase the die roll by the rolling side’s Audacity.
•	 Deduct the command quality of the fleet’s admiral if he is
captured or has been killed in combat.
H Reduce the die roll by two if rolling for the Turks

17

b) Combined Fleet Break-off: In the event that one or both sides
have a multi-national fleet, each nationality within the fleet rolls
separately using its own Audacity rating (but uses the noted fleet
admiral and the combined lost ship ratio regardless of nationality). If either nationality breaks, the entire fleet breaks as well,
unless specified otherwise in the scenario rules.

4.0 Optional Rules

The following rules may be used to add more realism and tension
to a game, but at the expense of longer playtime. When in use,
these rules supersede those provided in the Core Rules (3.0)

4.1 End Of The World

This rule may be used to “extend” the play area beyond the
extents of the map. If a ship cannot help sailing off the edge of
the map, all other ships should be shifted to allow additional
space. If the ships cannot be shifted without pushing other vessels off the map, the moving vessel must exit the play area and
is considered damaged and scores victory points for the fleet
with the lower Audacity rating only. Any vessel that sails off the
map in this fashion is considered lost when rolling for a fleet’s
Break Check.

4.2 Anchoring Limits

Ships may only anchor twice during each scenario. Where a ship
starts a scenario anchored this counts as one of the permitted anchorings. After anchoring, ships may rotate a maximum of three
hexsides in either direction (i.e., a ship cannot rotate more than
180 degrees from its original anchored direction). Players may
wish to keep the anchor marker facing the original direction in
order to keep track of how many hexsides a ship has rotated.

4.3 Grounding

Certain scenarios have parts of the map defined as ‘shoals’ or
‘shallows.’ Ships that move through shallows (either on purpose
or because they have no choice) may run aground. Whenever any
part of a ship unit moves into a shoal hex, roll on the Grounding
table. Modify the die roll by the depth value of the shallows,
the ship’s Relative Rate, and the Command Quality of any commander stacked with the moving ship. Grounded ships may no
longer move for the duration of the game, but may still fire their
guns (if an enemy ship moves close enough). Place an ‘Aground’
marker on grounded ships to indicate this status.

4.4 Towing

Gun-Brigs and Gunboats may begin a scenario towed by larger
ships. Only ships with a Relative Rate of 1-6 may tow. To indicate that a ship is being towed, place its piece atop the unit
towing it (in the stern hex of a large ship), orienting both to face
in the same direction. Ships under tow are automatically part
of the same command (if any) of the towing ship. Ships that
are towing may not raise Full Sails, nor may they fire Chasers
down their stern Rake Line. Ships that are being towed may not
fire Chasers down their bow Rake Line. Ships being towed may

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

18

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

be activated to fire and may be targeted independently of the
ships towing them. Determine the target of a Rake by the type
of Rake (bow or stern). The towing ship receives a bow Rake,
while the towed ship receives a stern Rake. A tow may be broken
during the Ship Status Check at the end of the turn. A ship may
not break a tow and raise Full Sails during the same turn. Tows
may not be established during a scenario (ships may only begin
a scenario being towed).

4.5 Defensive Fire

The non-moving player may choose to fire any one broadside at
the activated ship after it has expended a MP (including MPs expended while turning), or at any point during a Tack or Sternway
maneuver. When using the optional Defensive Fire rules, treat
a ship using defensive fire as if it were moving for the purpose
of determining Rakes. A ship using defensive fire may attempt
a Rake whenever it occupies a moving ship’s Rake Line. Use of
this option does not negate the Core defensive fire mechanics.
Both are used and treated as separate defensive fire mechanics
(i.e. a ship using standard defensive fire may not Rake, but a ship
using the optional mechanic may do so).

4.6.3 Battery Audacity: The scenario indicates the Audacity
rating for the batteries if it is different from their friendly fleet.
All batteries share the same Audacity. The battery Audacity is
only used as a firepower modifier during combat and affects no
die rolls.

4.7 Awash Ships

Rather than remove vessels that have ‘sunk,’ players may leave
them in place to act as movement obstacles. Awash ships, of
course, cannot move, fire or be captured. Awash ships are subject
to drifting (3.6.9) and while they may not cause collisions can
be collided with.

4.8 Initiative Cards

The decks of Initiative Cards are an optional method of determining the order in which commands and out-of-command ships are
activated. NOTE: These cards are available with Serpents of the
Seas (Flying Colors, Vol. II).

Out of Command Exception: When firing upon a moving OOC
ship, the fire is considered offensive and thus, the OOC ship
may return fire defensively (fires and applies damage before the
non-moving player fires). In addition, when using the optional
Defensive Fire mechanics, an OOC ship must make an unmodified Command check to fire at an active ship. A failed roll means
the OOC ship cannot fire defensively at the active ship for the
duration of its activation.

4.6 Shore Batteries

Certain scenarios indicate one or more hexes containing shore
batteries. For game purposes, these are collections of guns that
harass any enemy ships that come into range. Shore batteries
are activated as an individual command (or commands if there
is more than one) and are always in command. Shore batteries
may fire twice per game turn (offensively and/or defensively)
in any direction. Use Fired Port and Fired Starboard markers to
indicate fired status.
H 4.6.1 Battery Characteristics: The scenario rules indicate
the battery’s ‘Rate’ and how much damage it can sustain. When
firing upon a battery, only the Hull column is used. The only
DRMs that are used on the Hit Results Table are for firing while
anchored and firing outside the broadside arc. Any non-hull
damage results are ignored. Batteries are not subject to rakes.
Batteries may fire through friendly ships without effect. Batteries
neither benefit from nor are penalized by wind effects and do not
receive carronade bonuses. All batteries also gain an automatic
+2 die roll modifier on the Hit Results table (the equivalent of
being anchored).
4.6.2 Floating Batteries: Floating batteries (those anchored in
navigable areas) do not move. They may be fouled, but never
boarded. They sink immediately if they absorb their damage
capacity. Any ships fouled with a floating battery that sinks are
dismasted.

4.8.1 Alternate Sequence of Play: Using the Initiative Cards
replaces the Initiative Determination and Command Activation processes and uses a revised sequence of play as indicated
below.
a) Initial (First Turn Only) Command Determination: After setting up the game, players alternate in determining their
commands. The player with the lower Audacity selects the first
command. Regardless of this initial determination, all ships are
considered to be in command. Those ships not part of a group
or formation command are not required to roll for full command
status when activated. After initial commands have been determined, play begins with the dealing of the Initiative cards.
b) Revised Sequence of Play: The following sequence of play
is used each turn; in lieu of the Core sequence (3.1).
I.	 Wind Adjustment Segment (not on turn 1)
II.	 Determine Commands
III.	Deal Initiative Cards
	
	

A.	 Discard unused cards as desired.
B.	 Deal cards up to Hand Size.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1
IV. Activation Phase
	

A.	 Both players select an Initiative Card.

	

B.	 Both players reveal their selected cards.

	
	
	

C.	 The player with the lower value card determines which
player goes first (is active) during the current activation.
D.	 The active player determines command status.

E.	 First player activates a command or out-of-command ship
(roll for command status if able/necessary).

		1. The active ship’s movement points are determined.
		 2. The active ship’s maneuver direction is determined.
		 3. The active ship is moved.
	
	
	

F. 	 Second player determines command status.

G. 	Second player activates a command or out-of-command	
ship (roll for command status if able/necessary), as in
steps E1-3.
H. 	Return to Step A until only one player has inactivated commands and/or out-of-command ships. This player continues to play Initiative Cards to activate commands and
out-of-command ships until all have been activated.

V. Melee Combat

VI.	Ship Status Check
	
	
	
	
	

19

ing. Examples: A fleet with an Audacity of ‘2’, a Fleet Admiral
with a Quality of ‘4’ and two additional subordinate commanders
would have a hand size of 8 cards. A single ship with no commander and an Audacity rating of ‘2’ has a hand size of 5.
b) Initiative Card Use: At the start of each Activation phase,
each player secretly selects an Initiative card. Both are revealed
simultaneously. The player with the lower Initiative value then
selects if he will go first or second during the activation. In case
of ties, the player with higher Audacity wins.
Once all of a player’s ships have been activated for that Activation phase, the Initiative card is discarded.
If one player still holds Initiative Cards and the other player does
not, the player holding cards automatically wins the initiative
when playing a card and retains the initiative throughout the
remainder of the turn.
c) Command Status: The player moving first during the activation determines his command status by:
•	 Selecting a command or single out-of-command ship to use
with the card played.

•	 Selecting a single out-of-command ship and withdraws the
card played back into his hand in exchange for the “out-of
-command” option.

A.	 Ship Fires

After any ships have been activated per the choice made, the
second player makes a similar choice:

C.	 Striking

•	 Selects a command or single out-of-command ship to use with
the card played.

B.	 Drifting

•	 Selects a single out-of-command ship and withdraws the card
back into his hand in exchange for the “out-of-command”
option.

D.	 Sinking

E.	 Remove Broadside Markers

VII. Victory Determination

4.8.2 Initiative Decks: There are two Initiative Decks, one for
each player, each containing 27 cards. In the upper left corner
of each card is a number (its Initiative value) ranging from “1”
to “27.” In addition to each card’s Initiative Value in the upper
left corner, each card also has a list of Initiative Effects and an
Event. Cards are played either as Initiative Cards (to determine
player order and the effects on maneuvering and combat) or as
an Event, never both. A player may only play a single Initiative
card per command or out-of-command Activation, but may play
as many Event cards as he wishes (unless limited by the Event
cards played).
a) Dealing Initiative Cards: After commands have been determined, each player may discard any number of their remaining
Initiative cards. They then deal a number of cards out of their
own Initiative deck until each has a number of cards (including
cards retained from the previous turn) equal to their hand size. A
player’s hand size is equal to his side’s Audacity rating, plus the
Fleet Admiral’s current Quality rating, plus a number of cards
equal to the total number of subordinate commanders in the fleet.
A hand size is never less than three, plus the side’s Audacity rat-

•	 If (and only if) his opponent just selected the “out-ofcommand” option, withdraws the card played back into his
hand and does nothing.
A player who cannot play a card must select the “out-of-command” option, regardless of what his opponent may have
done.

d) Initiative Effects: Once a command or out-of-command ship
has been selected, all of the Initiative Effects noted on the card
are applied to all ships in the chosen command or the single outof-command ship for the duration of that Activation phase. Once
a player has completed movement and combat for all selected
ships during that Activation, the Initiative card no longer has any
affect and may be discarded. Initiative Effects have no effect on
Defensive Fire. Four of five possible modifiers are listed on each
card. The possible Initiative Effects are:
•	 Wear Requirement: The number of movement points that
must be expended before every hex-side turn (not side-slip) a
ship executes.

•	 Tacking Modifier: An additional modifier applied to a Tacking
die roll.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

20

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

•	 Speed Adjustment: A number of movement points that may
be added to or deducted from a ship’s initial speed prior to
moving the ship. When using the Maneuver Option (below),
Speed Adjustments must be determined prior to setting a
maneuver direction.
•	 Firing Modifier: An additional die roll modifier used on the
Fire Results table.

•	 Out of Command: An additional modification to the die roll
used to determine if an out-of-command ship behaves as if it
were in command.
e) Out-of-Command Option: If a player cannot play a card
or opts for the Out of Command option, any ships selected are
subject to the following restrictions:
•	 The ship is considered out of command in all respects and may
not roll to be treated in command.

•	 Other Maneuvers: A ship may attempt to maneuver in a
direction not indicated by the card’s icon by making a die
roll less than or equal to ‘3.’ A successful roll allows a ship to
maneuver to an adjacent direction (port or starboard to forward;
forward to port or starboard) as if that direction was indicated
as part of the maneuver icon. The die roll is modified by any
maneuver modifier indicated on the icon (absence of a modifier
indicates no modification) and further reduced by the ship’s
Audacity rating and the Command Quality of a commander
present on the ship. A ship successfully making this roll must
move in the new direction as if it were the only maneuver
icon indicated on the card. Exception: a ship playing a port- or
starboard-only maneuver card that successfully rolls to move
forward must make an additional maneuver roll in order to
move to starboard or port (respectively). If this roll fails, the
ship must move forward.
EXAMPLE: A ship with an Audacity rating of ‘2’ plays a port-only
maneuver card, but wants to move
to starboard. The maneuver icon
indicates a ‘–1’ modifier. The die
roll is a ‘5,’ reduced to a ‘2,’ which
is successful. The player makes a
second roll of a ‘7,’ reduced to a
‘4,’ which is not successful. The
ship must move forward during its
activation.

•	 The ship incurs a 2-hex Wear requirement.
•	 The ship incurs a +3 Tacking modifier.
•	 The ship incurs a –3 Firing modifier.

•	 If using the Maneuver Option (below), the ship must use a
forward maneuver by default, but may roll to change that order
with a +3 modifier.
An additional “Out-of-Command Option” card is available for
use when this option is selected.

f) Maneuver Option: Each Initiative card includes a maneuver
icon. The use of this icon is optional, but recommended when
playing scenarios with only a few ships per side. The icon indicates the direction a ship (or ships in formation) must move
when activated. These icons indicate one, two or three allowable
directions. When an initiative card is played, a direction indicated
on the card must be selected. A ship may try to alter direction to
one not indicated by the card by making a modified die roll less
than or equal ‘3’ (see ‘Other Maneuvers’ below) Ships that are
making Sternway ignore the maneuver order.
•	 Forward: An arrow pointing upwards toward the top of the
card indicates that a ship may not wear or tack (it may only
move forward, sideslip or back sails).

•	 Port: An arrow pointing to the left (marked with a ‘P’ for
‘Port’) indicates that the ship must wear or tack to the left
before any other turn may be made, and at least one wear or
tack in that direction is required.

•	 Starboard: An arrow pointing to the right (marked with a ‘S’
for ‘Starboard’) indicates that the ship must wear or tack to
the right before any other turn may be made, and at least one
wear or tack in that direction is required.
•	 Multiple Directions: An icon that includes more than one
possible direction indicates that a ship may chose any direction
indicated. The choice must be selected prior to the vessel
beginning its move, and must follow the rules of the selected
maneuver as if it was the only maneuver indicated on the
card.

g) Event Cards: The bottom portion of the Initiative cards describes the card’s Event. During an activation a single ship may
only be affected by one event card per player, whether the event
is played on a single ship or the formation to which it belongs.
h) Load Cards: Roughly a third of the Initiative cards are also
marked with a Load type: Double or Chain Shot. These cards
are played on single ships at any time (including defensive fire)
prior to determining combat results. Both of these cards can be
played on a ship, but a single broadside may only fire one type
of load. The fire effects of these cards are as follows:
•	 Double Shot: No fire is allowed beyond a range of five hexes.
Provided at least one Hull hit is sustained by a target, add
+2H at a range of one hex or less or +1H at a range of two
hexes or greater (prior to determining Rake effects, if any). An
unmodified die roll of ‘0’ results in two Hull hits on the firing
vessel. An unmodified roll of ‘1-2’ results in one Hull hit on
the firing vessel.
•	 Chain Shot: When firing at Rigging, add +1 to the fire results
die roll at a range of 2-3 hexes, +2 at a range of one hex or
+3 at point blank range. Reduce the die roll by –2 if firing at
a ship’s hull.
i) Deck Reshuffling: The Initiative Decks are only reshuffled
when the last card from a deck is drawn or at the beginning of a
turn following the play of the “Blind Eye to Danger” event.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

5.0 Ship Duels

Ship Duels comprise those Flying Colors scenarios where there
are no more than two ships per side and no commanders are
used. These scenarios use a different map and a somewhat different set of rules than a Fleet scenario owing to the removal of
the command system used in larger scenarios. The Core rules
are used for the most part, with any differences indicated within
this section.

5.1 Duel Map

Ship Duels use a special, hexagonal map. On the fringes of
each side of the map are shaded areas labeled A-F or with a Star
symbol. There is also a bounded three hex area labeled “Chase.”
These areas are used for scenario setups and for randomly
generating duels. The entry point with the Star is the setup area
for the scenario ‘Attacker.’ The ‘Defender’ starts in one of the
other areas. Also included around the borders of the map are
ship-tracking charts. Players should use these charts to keep
track of the status of ships in play. Use Hull 1 and 2 Hit markers to identify the ships in play (these would be the only “hit”
markers on the map).

5.2 Duel Types

There are two types of Duel scenarios: Meeting Engagements
and Chases. Meeting Engagements are those where each side
attempts to sink or capture his opponent. Chases are those where
a ship attempts to escape from the other or, failing this, sink or
capture the chaser.
5.2.1 Meeting Engagements: Victory Points determine the
winner of Meeting Engagements. There is no maximum number
of turns, unless specified by scenario rule. If a ship moves out
of the engagement area, it scores points (as if sunk) only to the
defender.
5.2.2 Chases: In a Chase, the winner is determined per a Meeting
Engagement (5.2.1) or the defender wins immediately if he can
exit the play area, per End of the World (4.1).

5.3 Initiative Cards

The Initiative Card decks must be used in Duel scenarios and
all aspects of the cards are in use (including the Maneuver option). Where a player only has a single card in their hand and
an inactive ship in play, the card must be played as an Initiative Card to activate the ship or immediately used as an Event
(and only if applicable). If an Initiative card cannot be played

21

to activate a ship, that ship is considered out-of-command and
suffers the same limitations as defined by 4.8.2.e. A player may
not purposely define a ship as out-of-command when playing an
Initiative Card (i.e., there is no “out-of-command option” when
playing a Duel scenario).

5.4 Duel Sequence of Play

Since there are no commanders in a Duel game, the entire command system used in Fleet scenarios is abandoned. This requires
the use of a special sequence of play for Duel scenarios:
I.	 Deal Initiative Cards
	
	

A.	 Discard unused cards as desired.
B.	 Deal cards up to Hand Size.

II.	 Wind Adjustment Segment (not on turn 1)
III.	Activation Cycle
	

A.	 Both players select an Initiative Card.

	

C.	 The player with the lower value card determines which 		
player activates a ship.

	

	

B.	 Both players reveal their selected cards.

D.	 First player activates a ship.

		1.	The active ship’s movement points are determined.
		
		
	
	

2.	The active ship’s maneuver direction is determined.
3.	The active ship is moved.

E.	 Second player activates a ship per steps D1-3.

F.	 Return to Step A until only one player has inactive ships.
This player continues to play Initiative Cards to activate
ships until all have been activated.

IV. Melee Combat

V.	 Ship Status Check
	

A.	 Ship Fires

	

C.	 Striking

	
	
	

B.	 Drifting
D.	 Sinking

E.	 Remove Broadside markers

VI. Victory Determination

5.5 Fire Combat

The combat mechanics described in the Core rules are used
unchanged with one addition: the Defensive Fire optional rule
(4.5) must be used.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

22

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

6.0 Scenario Alternatives

The scenarios included in the Play Book of each Flying Colors
series game are used to recreate historical actions fought (or
which may have been fought) during the time period and focus
covered by each game. Although many, many scenarios have
been set up, players may want to create their own or modify those
included for the sake of playtime. These options are described
within this section.

6.1 Design Your Own

If you want to try something a little different, or want to design a
scenario for tournament use, you can use the Victory Point values
of the ships to create balanced engagements. First determine the
number of points each player has to spend.
6.1.1 Fleet Actions: When purchasing fleets, ships and commanders are worth their Victory Point values in points. A fleet
must start with at least one commander. Use one map for smaller
scenarios, two for mid-sized and three for large scenarios. Before
building the fleets, the players should determine the length of
the game in turns, if any shoals will be used and if any optional
rules will be in play. After the fleets have been built, each player
rolls a die and adds the number of any unspent build-points to
the roll. The high roller gains one Audacity point. In case of a
tie, roll again and compare unmodified die rolls until a winner is
determined. The winner starts with an Audacity of 1 (Player A)
and the loser an Audacity of 0 (Player B). Player B sets his fleet
up near the center of the board as desired. Side A then selects a
side of the board where his fleet will enter in formation. After
these steps have been completed, roll to determine wind direction.
On a 1-6, position the wind marker to point in that direction. On
a 7-0, roll again until a wind direction has been determined. Play
begins with Player A automatically having the initiative (regardless of card play, if the Initiative Cards are in use).
6.1.2 Ship Duels: When selecting ships for Ship Duels, the
Victory Point values of the opposing sides should be equivalent.
To determine sides, roll a die. The high roller is considered the
Attacker. Before placing ships, determine the initial wind direction by rolling a die. A result of 1-6 indicates the initial wind
direction. On a roll of 7-0, re-roll.
•	 Meeting Engagements: The Attacker places his ship(s)
anywhere within the setup area indicated with the star and
oriented as desired. The defender rolls a die to determine his
setup area. The setup areas lettered A-E are indicated with a die

roll result. Rolling a die selects the defender’s setup area. The
defender sets up his ship(s) in the determined area, oriented as
desired.

•	 Chases: The Defender places his ship(s) anywhere within the
Chase setup area, oriented as desired. The Attacker then places
his ship(s) anywhere within the setup area indicated with the
star, oriented as desired.

6.2 Tournament Play

Players who want to use Flying Colors for tournament play will
find it well suited. Ship Duel Meeting engagements are best suited
for tournament play owing to their relatively short playing time
and head-to-head nature. Chases are doable, as well as Fleet
Actions when slightly modified to shorten play.
6.2.1 Ship Duels: Meeting Engagements are the ideal way to
play Flying Colors competitively, although referees may want to
use a time limit. At the completion of a battle, tally victory points
to determine the winner. In the case of a tie, the player with the
higher Audacity rating loses. Chase scenarios are not suggested
for tournament play unless time limits are not used (as their use
penalizes the defender from the outset). If Ship Duels are used
in a tournament setting, players should bid Victory Points to play
the side with higher Audacity. Bids come in half victory point
increments and are applied to the lower Audacity player’s score
at the conclusion of the battle.
6.2.2 Fleet Actions: The historical scenarios all have an inherent
bias toward one side or the other in the form of the Audacity rating. The side with the higher Audacity is expected to win most of
the time. This is by design, but it makes for boring tournament
play! For those wanting to play fleet actions competitively, these
options are suggested:
•	 The Break Check rolls are triggered as soon as an enemy ship
is damaged (as opposed to sunk, struck or captured). This will
drastically shorten each game.

•	 Players should secretly bid positive die-roll modifiers to the
Break Check roll to play the side with the higher Audacity. For
example, if one player bids two points to play the historically
superior side, the other player may add two (+2) to their Break
Check die rolls. Tied bids should be bid again no more than
three times. If bids are still tied after the third bid, roll a die. The
high roller wins the bid to play the superior fleet. Alternatively,
each player rolls a die with the high roller making the first bid.
Players up their ante until one player declines. This option
favors a lucky roller, but it’ll avoid tied bids.

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

Index

Actual Rate . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.1.5
Anchoring . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.19
Arc of Fire . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.4
Audacity Rating  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.2.5
Awash Ships . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.7
Backing Sails  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.10
Batterys/Shore Batteries  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.6
Beating  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.2
Break Check . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.8.3
Broadside  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.74
Calm . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.3
Captured Ships  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.14
Carronades  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.10
Chases . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5.2.2
Chase Guns . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.5.2
Collisions  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.15
Command Range . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.2.2
Command Quality . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.2.3
Commands  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.3.3
Commander Casualties . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Commander Transfer  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Commanders . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.3.1
Carronades  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.10
Damage Capacity  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.1.2
Damage Limits/Modifications  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.9
Defensive Fire . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.5
Design Your Own . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6.1
Disengaging  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.18
Dismasted . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Drifting . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.8
Duel Map  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5.1
Duel Sequence of Play  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5.4
End of the World . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.1
Excess Damage . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.8
Evasion, Evasion Table . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.16
Facing . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.1
Fire Combat  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7
Fire Resolution Process . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.7
Fires (Ships on fire) . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Firepower  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.7
Flagships . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.3.2
Fleet Actions . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6.2.2
Fleet Admiral (Rank)  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.2.1
Fleet Commanders  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.2
Fouled . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  3.6.16-18
Full Broadside . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.7
Full Sails . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.3
Grappling  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.16
Grounding . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.3
Hit Results Determination . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.7
Hull Damage . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11

In Irons! (Taken Aback)  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.2
Initiative  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.4
Initiative Cards . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.8, 5.3
Initiative Decks . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.8.2
Line of Sight . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.3
Marines . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.1.3
Mixed Fleets . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.2
Meeting Engagements . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5.2.1
Melee Combat . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.8
Movement . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6
Nelson’s Patent Bridge . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.13
Out of Command . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.3.3, 3.5.1
Oared Ship  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.3
Partial Broadside . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.7
Pass-Along  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.14
Pass-Through  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .  3.6.12-13
Point-Blank Fire . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.9
Port Broadside . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.4
Rake  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.7
Range  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.7
Rank  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.2.1
Rate (Ship Size)  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.1
Reaching . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.2
Relative Rate . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.1.1
Rigging Damage . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Running . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.2
Scale . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.5
Sequence of Play . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.1
Ship Duels . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5.0
Shore Batteries  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.6
Side Slipping . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.7
Sinking  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Small Ship Speed Enhancement . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.3
Stacking Ships . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.11
Starboard Hex . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.1
Status Sheets . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.3
Sternway . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.9
Striking . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Subordinate Commanders . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.3.1
Swivel/Pivot Guns  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.5.1
Tacking . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.6
Taken Aback . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.2
Tournament Play . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6.2
Towing  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4.4
Victory Determination  . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.9
Victory Points . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2.2.1.4
Vulnerable (Hull Damage) . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.11
Wearing . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.5
Weather Effects . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.6.3
Wind Effects . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3.7.6

© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

23

24

Flying Colors — ver. 3.1

Strike Table

Collision Table
	 Die Roll	
	 0-9	
	10 or more	

When a damaged ship has 3 or less hull hits remaining:
	 Die Roll	
Result
	 3 or less	
No Effect
	 4-9	
Ship strikes its colors

Result
No Collision
Fouled!

Modifiers
	 –?	 per Commander Quality
	 +1	 per ship Rate 3 or 4
	 +2	 per ship Rate 1 or 2
	 +3	 per ship Rate (1)
	 +1	 per damaged ship
	 +?	 MPs the moving ship cannot expend

Modifiers:
–? Hull hits remaining,
–? Commander Quality

When a ship is both dismasted and within five hexes of an
enemy ship or shore battery which is closer to the dismasted ship than any friendly ship or shore battery:

Note: Apply modifiers for both the moving and non-moving ships.

	 Die Roll	
	 5 or less	
	 6-9	

Evasion Table
	 Die Roll	

	 0-6	
	7 or more	

Result

Evasion Successful
Roll for Grapple

Result
No Effect
Ship strikes its colors

Modifiers: –? Fleet Audacity Rating, –? Commander Quality

Modifiers (Rate modifiers based on ship’s undamaged
Relative Rate)
	 –?	 Evading Commander Quality
	 +1	 Evading ship Rate 3 or 4
	 +2	 Evading ship Rate 1 or 2
	 +3	 Evading ship Rate (1)
	 +1	 Evading ship damaged

When a ship has 3 or fewer hull hits remaining AND is dismasted while within 5 hexes of an enemy ship or shore battery
which is closer to the dismasted ship than any friendly ship or
shore battery:
	 Die Roll	
Result
	1 or less	
No Effect
	 2-9	
Ship strikes its colors
Modifiers: –? Hull hits remaining; –? Fleet Audacity Rating;
–? Commander Quality

Grappling Table
	 Die Roll	
	 0-4	
	5 or more	

–? Fleet Audacity Rating

Result
Grappled	
Failed

Disengagement Table

Modifiers
	+/–	 Marine difference
	 –1	 if target has struck its colors
	 –2	 if Fouled

Break Off Table (15.2)

Die Roll		
Result			
0 or less		
Fleet Breaks!			
1-9		
Remain and Fight!		

Modifiers	
	
	
	
	
	 –1	 Opposing fleet has more undamaged ships
	 –2	 Opposing fleet has double undamaged ships
	 +?	 Audacity Rating				
	 –?	 Fleet Admiral Quality if dead or captured
	 –2	 If rolling for the Turks

Die Roll	
	 0-4	
	5 or more	

Result
Disengaged
Failed

Modifiers
	 –?	 Commander Quality
	 +1	 Fouled
	 +2	 Grappled and Fouled

Command Transfer Table	
	 Die Roll	
	 6 or less	
	 7-9	

Result
No Transfer
Command Transfer

Modifiers
	 +?	 Audacity Rating

GMT Games, LLC • P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308
www.GMTGames.com
© 2014 GMT Games, LLC

</rulebook>
			
						                           
						               													<description>Flying Colors recreates naval actions during the height of the Age of Sail, from small engagements to full battles involving dozens of ships in each fleet. Play is fast, furious, and does not require the pre-plotted movement found in many other naval games. Instead, a simple initiative and command system allows players to activate and maneuver their fleets in a realistic manner, indicating how older commanders adhered to rules of engagement where more forward thinking commanders, like Nelson, could retain control of their fleets after the first broadsides began to be exchanged.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Rather than focusing on the abilities of individual ships, Flying Colors uses broad classes of vessel within each &amp;quot;rate&amp;quot; and concentrates the players minds on maintaining command of their fleets using a simple command system.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;This is not a strategic level game where one piece represents several ships. Flying Colors includes individually named ships rated for size, gunnery, boarding ability, and damage capacity. Also included are nearly four dozen individually named commanders, rated for their ability to control their formations as well as the impact of their presence within the fleet. The game system provides what naval enthusiasts will expect in a tactical Age of Sail game: broadsides, rakes, anchoring, wind effects, weather, shore batteries, and much more. All this is packed into a short, accessible rulebook.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Included within the game are historical scenarios [...]. The battles range in size from small engagements playable on a single map through huge engagements like the Glorious First of June playable on three maps. Players are also free to create their own variants and &amp;quot;what-if&amp;quot; scenarios using point values for each ship. Most scenarios can be played within a few hours and two players can complete even the largest within a day. Several are also well suited to solitaire play.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;TIME SCALE : 5-10 minutes per turn&amp;#10;MAP SCALE: 100 meters per hex&amp;#10;UNIT SCALE: Individual Ships&amp;#10;NUMBER OF PLAYERS: One to Four&amp;#10;&amp;#10;(from GMT website and BGG users)&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2003" />
						               				<minplayers value="1" />
						               				<maxplayers value="4" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="22">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="14" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="4" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="15" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="11" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="5" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="8" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="8" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="240" />
						               				<minplaytime value="240" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="240" />
						               				<minage value="12" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="10">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="6">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="1" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="5" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="2726" value="Age of Reason" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1075" value="American Revolutionary War" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1051" value="Napoleonic" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1008" value="Nautical" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1019" value="Wargame" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2072" value="Dice Rolling" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2676" value="Grid Movement" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2026" value="Hexagon Grid" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2975" value="Line of Sight" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2070" value="Simulation" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="4892" value="Game: Flying Colors (GMT)" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="9793" value="History: Age of Kings" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="57982" value="History: French Revolutionary Wars" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="61118" value="History: Napoleonic Wars" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="58131" value="History: Seven Years War" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="338895" value="Flying Colors: Beat to Quarters!" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="29878" value="Flying Colors: Ship of the Line" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameintegration" id="133518" value="Blue Cross, White Ensign" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameintegration" id="36597" value="Serpents of the Seas" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameintegration" id="202989" value="Under the Southern Cross: The South American Republics in the Age of the Fighting Sail" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="2961" value="Mike Nagel" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="71" value="Rodger B. MacGowan" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="2961" value="Mike Nagel" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="140" value="Mark Simonitch" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="52" value="GMT Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="1991" value="Relative Range" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="802" />
			<average value="7.54348" />
			<bayesaverage value="6.09646" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="2181" bayesaverage="6.09646" />
																				<rank type="family" id="4664" name="wargames" friendlyname="War Game Rank" value="148" bayesaverage="7.03533" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.3856" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="2566" />
			<trading value="76" />
			<wanting value="97" />
			<wishing value="408" />
			<numcomments value="388" />
			<numweights value="108" />
			<averageweight value="3.037" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>