<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="62226">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/KIWvFMnGp63foMwPfwqlCQ__thumb/img/oFfK06nNwrQ8YvqWozdntUSn6O0=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic1651133.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/KIWvFMnGp63foMwPfwqlCQ__original/img/YEFtGjDT-nR6LZU9lKkZCOVSTB4=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic1651133.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Iron and Oak" />
				<rulebook>Living Rules

March 2014

RULE BOOK
This is the “Living Rules” document for the game. It
includes errata and clarifications to the original rules. To
aid readability, errata is indicated in blue text.

GMT Games, LLC • P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308
www.GMTGames.com

2

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

Table of Contents

1.0	 GAME COMPONENTS...........................................3
1.1	Gameboard...................................................................3
1.2	Ship &amp; Fort Counters...................................................3
1.3	Card Decks...................................................................4
1.4	Game Markers..............................................................5
1.5	Play Aids.......................................................................6
1.6	Dice...............................................................................7
2.0	 SETTING UP THE GAME......................................7
2.1	Team Play.....................................................................7
3.0	 SEQUENCE OF PLAY..............................................7
3.1	Status Phase..................................................................7
3.2	Order Phase..................................................................8
3.3	Action Phase.................................................................8
3.4	Replace Card Phase......................................................9
3.5	Victory Phase................................................................9
4.0	ORDERS...................................................................9
4.1	Anchor..........................................................................9
4.2	Weigh Anchor..............................................................9
4.3	Refloat...........................................................................9
4.4	Unfoul.........................................................................10
5.0	MOVEMENT......................................................... 10
5.1	Maneuver Procedure...................................................10
5.2	Drifting.......................................................................11
5.3	Towing........................................................................11
5.4	Hazards.......................................................................12
5.5	 Crossing the ‘T’...........................................................12
5.6	 Ram/Spar Torpedo Attacks........................................13
5.7	Terrain........................................................................14
6.0	 GUNNERY COMBAT............................................. 15
6.1	Combat Range............................................................15
6.2	Combat Procedure......................................................15
6.3	Critical Hits................................................................16
6.3.1	 Armament (May Repair)....................................16
6.3.2	Boiler..................................................................16
6.3.3	Captain...............................................................16
6.3.4	Collateral............................................................16
6.3.5	Crew...................................................................17
6.3.6	 Engine-D (May Repair).....................................17
6.3.7	 Engine-S (May Repair)......................................17
6.3.8	Explosion...........................................................17
6.3.9	Fire.....................................................................17
6.3.10	 Jam (May Repair).............................................17

6.3.11	Magazine.........................................................17
6.3.12	Ram.................................................................17
6.3.13	 Rudder (May Repair).......................................17
6.3.14	 Spar Torpedo....................................................18
6.3.15	Speed...............................................................18
6.3.16	Smokestack......................................................18
6.3.17	 Steering (May Repair).....................................18
7.0	 ACTION CARDS.................................................... 18
7.1	Double Charge [5]—Gunnery Segment.....................18
7.2	Grapeshot [5]—Gunnery Segment............................18
7.3	Incendiary Shells [5]—Gunnery Segment..................19
7.4	Misfire [4]—Gunnery Segment..................................19
7.5	Quick Maneuver [6]—Movement Segment...............19
7.6	Rapid Fire [5]—Gunnery Segment............................19
7.7	Screen [3]—Movement Segment...............................19
7.8	Scuttle [4]—Movement Segment...............................19
7.9	Slipped Anchor [2]—Movement Segment.................19
7.10	 Slow Maneuver [6]—Movement Segment...............19
7.11	 Springs [1]—Movement Segment............................19
7.12	 Strike [4]—Movement Segment..............................19
8.0	 CAMPAIGN GAME............................................... 20
8.1	Campaign Log............................................................20
8.2	Campaign Game Sequence of Play.............................20
8.3	Campaign Setup.........................................................20
8.4	Pre-Battle Actions......................................................20
8.5	Battle...........................................................................21
8.6	Night Battles...............................................................21
8.7	Post-Battle Actions.....................................................21
8.8	Repairing and Refitting Ships.....................................22
8.9	Yard Cards..................................................................22
8.9.1 Crew Grade [4]...................................................22
8.9.2 Fast Repair [2].....................................................22
8.9.3 In Short Supply [2].............................................24
8.9.4 Limited Ammunition [2]....................................24
8.9.5 Out of the Mist [2].............................................24
8.9.6 Replacements [2].................................................24
8.9.7 Yard Fire [2]........................................................24
9.0	 OPTIONAL RULES............................................... 24
9.1	Low Freeboard............................................................24
9.2	Tenders.......................................................................24
9.3	Alternating Movement...............................................24

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

3

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

Turn Track

Player Side

Band

Grid Box

1.0	GAME COMPONENTS

1.1	Gameboard

The Gameboard is used to control all action in a scenario and
is placed between the two sides with the Union sitting on one
side and the Confederate on the opposite side. It includes three
main sections:

•	 The Play Area: A 5 x 5 grid where the various ships maneuver. Each one of the play area’s 25 ‘boxes’ is called a ‘Grid
Box’. A horizontal row or vertical column of 5 contiguous
Grid Boxes is called a ‘Band’. Place markers per the scenario
instructions if the top and/or the bottom are bounded by
river banks/shorelines.
•	 Environment: Place markers per the scenario instructions
to indicate the shoal depth in each Band and the current
and wind conditions.
•	 Turn Track: Used to keep track of the current turn. Place
the Turn Marker on the current turn. The scenarios indicate
the game length in turns.

Ship Cards are arranged along their respective edge of the
Gameboard for easy viewing by both sides.

1.2	 Ship &amp; Fort Counters

Each counter has the name of a ship or fort and its national flag
depicted on the front side and just its national flag depicted on
the back side (note that some scenarios require hidden movement and ships are committed in secrecy to campaign scenarios).
These Counters are what the players use on the Gameboard to
indicate the current position of a ship or fort. Two ship counters
(the Steamer/Barge) represent either a Steamer or a Barge as
required by a scenario.

	

front	back

Each game of Iron &amp; Oak contains the following:
•	 1 22”x34” map
•	 2 counter sheets (1 full and 1 half )
•	 This rule booklet
•	 1 Playbook
•	 78 Ship and Fort cards
•	 50 Action cards
•	 16 Order cards
•	 16 Naval Yard cards
•	 2 (identical) Player Aid cards
•	 10 dice (2 red, 2 white, 2 green, 2 yellow, 2 blue)

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

4

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

1.3	 Card Decks

Iron &amp; Oak includes four types of cards: Ship and Fort Cards
(78 large cards [1.3.1]), the Action Card deck (50 cards [1.3.2]),
Order Cards (16 sets of four cards each [1.3.3]), and the Naval
Yard Card deck (16 cards [8.9]). When specific Action and Yard
card names appear in these rules, they are rendered in Small
Caps text. Naval Yard cards are utilized only during Campaign
Games and should be kept separate from the Action cards at
all times.
B. Ship Name

CSS Atlanta

Sample Ship Card:
CSS Atlanta

C. Victory Points

A. Nationality

H. Specials
	 (none present)
E. Crew Factor

D. Maneuver Chart

F. Draft

I. Ram Rating

J. Spar Torpedo

G. Armored Hit Location
G. Wooden Hit Location

K. Gunnery

L. Ship Image

1.3.1	Ship Cards
A.	 Nationality: Depicts the Civil War era naval ensign of
either the CSA or USA.
B.	 Ship Name: The name of the ship.
C.	 Victory Points: The point value of a ship for comparison
purposes or when it is used in the campaign game.
D.	 Maneuver Chart: Each line shows the Maneuver dice
rolled by the ship when it attempts to move after incurring the number of Hits shown. For example, if Atlanta has
suffered 8 Hits, it would roll a d8 and a d6. When the ship
suffers the Total Hits allowed, it sinks.
E.	 Crew Factor: A numerical value depicting the size of a
ship’s crew. The Crew Factor is depicted as #/ (light casualties)/# (heavy casualties) –# (full crew). As a ship’s crew
suffers casualties it affects the ship’s ability to fire its guns
and maneuver, and it may be forced to retire from a battle.
F.	 Draft: A numerical rating of the amount of water the ship
draws (depth the hull rides in the water) from 1 (slight
draft) to 3 (deep draft). A ship’s draft may increase as it
suffers damage. If a ship’s draft rating is higher than a shoal
rating, it could run aground.

G.	Hit Location: There are 5 possible Hit Locations for
each ship. Each location is classified as either armored or
wooden as depicted by its background image. Each Hit
Location also depicts the dice that are rolled for defensive
purposes when that location is hit during combat action.
H.	Specials: These symbols indicate whether or not a ship
is subject to damage from Grapeshot, is classified as a
monitor-type ship, or may participate in campaign Blockade Battles. The symbols are:
	

Ship’s crew is subject to damage from grapeshot.

	
	

Monitor-type ship
Ship may participate in campaign blockade battles.

I.	 Ram Rating: All ships have the ability to ram another ship.
The Ram Rating depicts the dice that are rolled to resolve
a ram attack.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

5

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual
J.	 Spar Torpedo: If a ship is equipped with a spar torpedo, it
has “Spar” listed. It is able to conduct a single spar torpedo
attack where the spar torpedo explodes. Note the Union
ship, USS Spuyten Duyvil, was able to reload its spar
torpedo and may therefore conduct any number of spar
torpedo attacks.
K.	 Gunnery: The Gunnery section is a graphical depiction of
a ship’s ability to fire its guns at an opposing ship or fort,
including the dice that are rolled when a ship fires its guns.
Gunnery is subject to various die roll modifiers. Two are
shown in this Section: Bow-On Fire and Stern-On Fire.
	
Bow-On Fire
Gunnery Modifier

1.3.3 Order Cards
Each Order card has one or two Orders [4.0] at each end.

During the Order Phase of each turn, players will assign an
Order to each ship by placing an Order Card next to its Ship
Card with the applicable Order closest to the ship. If there are
two Orders at that end, the ship’s situation will make it clear
which applies. For example, a Grounded ship cannot Drift,
while a ship that is not aground cannot Refloat.

Gunnery Dice:
Limited guns have a
yellow circle
Stern-On Fire
Gunnery Modifier

	

If an “X” is shown, the ship may not fire at an opposing
ship that is across its Bow or Stern as appropriate.
L.	 Ship Image: A graphical depiction of the listed ship for
information purposes only.

1.3.2	 Action Cards

Union and Confederate players use the Action Cards to assist
during a battle. Scenario instructions indicate the number of
Action Cards each side is dealt at the beginning of a scenario.
Action Cards are classified as either Movement or Gunnery,
indicating the Segment of an Action Phase when they may be
played. Players are never required to play Action Cards. Keep
un-played Action Cards hidden at all times.

Each set of four Order Cards is numbered to ease sorting. Assign a set to each ship.

1.4	 Game Markers

Various counters are used to mark the status of situations
during a scenario; e.g., Hits, Critical Hits and the position of
Torpedo-Mines on the Gameboard.

Protection Damage (‘Shields’): Includes values from
“–1” to “–4”. They are used to mark protection damage
at each of the five possible Hit Locations on ships or
fort section.
Hits: Includes values from “1” to “10”. Marks total
Hits on a ship or fort section. Use multiple markers
for 10+ Hits.

Card Name

Fouled: Marks a ship that is fouled with another ship,
an obstruction, or a hulk.

Card Text

Grappled: Marks two ships that are grappled together.

Decision Dice

Anchored: Marks a ship that is anchored.

Card Type

Slipped: Marks a ship that may not anchor.

Day/Night
Symbol

Grounded: Marks a ship that is aground.
Opposed: Marks an opposed maneuver.
Light/Heavy Smoke: Marks a ship or fort
section obscured by smoke.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

6

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual
Repair Party: Marks a ship or fort section employing
a Repair Party.

Rudder: Marks a Rudder Critical Hit on a ship.

Elite: Marks a ship/fort section as possessing Elite
Grade.

Armament: Marks Armament
Critical Hits on a ship or fort
section.

Crack: Marks a ship/fort section as possessing Crack
Grade.

Torpedo-Mine: Placed in a Grid Box to indicate the
potential presence of mines.

Green: Marks a ship/fort section as possessing Green
Grade.

Heavy Obstruction: Placed in a Grid Box to indicate
the potential presence of Heavy Obstructions.

Draft +1: Marks Draft increase on ships due to damage.

Obstructions: Placed in a Grid Box to indicate the
potential presence of Obstructions.

Fire: Includes values from “1” to “5”. Marks fires on
a ship or fort section.

Hulk: Placed in a Grid Box where a sunken ship
poses a hazard to navigation.

Crew Loss: Includes values from “1” to “6”. Marks
crew hits on a ship or fort section. Use multiple markers for 7+ hits.

Bank: Placed at the top or bottom of the Play Area
to indicate Banks along those edges.

Engine Damaged: Marks an Engine Damaged
Critical Hit on a ship.

Wind: Placed in the Environment section
to indicate wind strength.

Engine Stopped: Marks an Engine Stopped Critical
Hit on a ship.

Shoal Depth: Includes values from “0”, “1” , “3”, “4”.
Placed along the edge of the Play Area to indicate
shoal depth in those Bands.

Speed –1 and Speed –2: Marks Speed
Critical Hits on a ship.

Current: Indicates the direction and speed of the
Current (if any) on the Play Area.

Steering: Marks a Steering Critical Hit on a ship.

Gunfire: Marks ships and batteries firing this turn at
night.

Jam: Marks a Turret Jammed Critical Hit on a
monitor.
Captain: Marks a Captain Critical Hit on a ship.
Smokestack: Marks a Smokestack Critical Hit on a
ship.
Ram: Marks a Ram Critical Hit on a ship.
Spar: Marks a Spar Critical Hit on a ship.
Boiler: Marks a Boiler Critical Hit on a ship.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Turn: Indicates the current turn (Day or
Night) on the Gameboard.

1.5 Play Aids

The 2-sided Play Aids
include all of the reference tables and charts required for play. They are
explained in the various
sections of these rules.

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

1.6	Dice

The ten dice (two red four/eight-sided—called a “d4”; two
white six-sided—“d6”; two green eight-sided—“d8”; two
yellow eight-sided—d8; and two blue ten-sided—“d10”) are
used to determine results. Note that some versions of d10s are
numbered 0-9. In those cases, treat the “0” as “10.” A set of five
dice is composed of one of each color and is used by a player
to determine movement, combat and other results. When one
die is rolled, the number rolled on it is used as the result. When
two or three dice are rolled, the highest number rolled appearing
on any of the dice is used as the result.
Example: If a red “4” and a green “2” are rolled, the number used
is the “4.”
Exception: See Dice Sum Rolls [1.6.1C].

1.6.1	Rules for Dice Rolls
Movement, Combat, and some Action Cards and other checks
require die rolls to determine the outcome. Some die rolls are
competitive, while others are just one-side rolls. Movement,
combat, and decision resolutions are always an attack or challenge roll by an active player and a defensive or response roll by
an opposing player. The dice to be rolled are found within their
respective sections on the Ship, Action Card or table. Opposing
players roll the indicated dice (listed in the format “dXdY”),
from one to three, and compare the results to determine the
outcome. Only the single highest number rolled from each set
of dice is used for comparison.
A. Movement and Combat Resolution
	 If the highest modified movement/combat number rolled
exceeds the highest modified opposing/defense number
rolled, the movement or combat is successful.

B. Decision Resolution
	 If the highest modified ‘Challenge’ number rolled exceeds
the highest ‘Response’ number rolled, the decision is successful. If the highest modified ‘Challenge’ number rolled
equals or is less than the highest ‘Response’ number rolled,
the decision fails. In either case, apply the result if appropriate.

2.0	SETTING UP THE GAME

Players should choose a scenario from the Play Book and lay
out the gameboard between them. Shuffle the Action Card deck
and deal each side the number of cards indicated in the scenario instructions. Select the appropriate Ship Cards and Ship
Counters for the scenario, place Environment Game Markers
per the scenario instructions, and set the remaining markers off
to the side. Give each ship one set of four Order cards [1.3.3].
Give each side a set of five dice [1.6].

2.1	 Team Play

Many Iron &amp; Oak scenarios are perfect for three or more players.
When teams of two or more play a scenario, divide the ships
among the teammates by any method desired. Play Action
Cards from a single hand—do not divide the cards among the
teammates. Teammates must agree how cards are to be played
each turn—remember, it is a collective effort.

3.0	SEQUENCE OF PLAY

Iron &amp; Oak is played in turns with one side resolving its turn
as the active side, and then the other side resolving its turn.
The two sides alternate play until the scenario is completed.
Each scenario indicates which side plays first during each turn.

First Side’s Turn
1.	Status Phase:
a.	Attempt repairs or remove Repair Party markers (if
desired).
b.	Check the status of all fires affecting your forts and
ships.
c.	Check for removal of each Smoke marker on your forts
and ships.
d.	P lace Repair Party markers.
2.	Order Phase: The first side orders all its ships as desired.
3.	Action Phase: The first side moves and conducts combat
with each of its ships and forts as ordered.

4.	Replace Card Phase: The first side may replace one action
card in its hand if it did not play any.

C. Dice Sum Rolls
	 Some Action Cards and Critical Hits call for the numbers
rolled to be added. When this applies, the dice will be listed
in the format “dX+dY”.
	 Example: If a red “4” and a green “2” are rolled, the result

Second Side’s Turn: Complete the same four phases.

D. Dice Roll Modifiers (DRMs)
	 Except for Shields modifying a defensive roll in gunnery
combat [6.2.1] and target Maneuver rolls during Crossing
the ‘T’ or Ram/Spar Torpedo attacks [5.5, 5.6.1], all DRMs
apply to the attack or challenge roll.

3.1	 Status Phase

used is “6.”

7

5.	Victory Phase: Determine if either side has met the victory conditions for the scenario. If not, advance the Turn
marker by one and start the sequence again. When teams
of two or more play, the players of a side play in any order
desired during their phases just like a single player.

Each ship or fort that has one or more fires burning and/or is
marked with a Heavy or Light Smoke marker must check the
status of each occurrence. Check status in any order, except
must check any Level 5 Fires first. Ships and forts with Repair
Parties may also attempt to repair Critical Hits.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

8

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

3.1.1	Repairs
At the end of a Status Phase, players may place a Repair Party
marker on any ship or fort section with less than full crew casualties that does not already have a Repair Party or Captured
marker. A Repair Party remains in play until the ship or fort
section suffers full crew casualties or until voluntarily removed
at the beginning of a subsequent Status Phase.
A ship or fort section with an existing Repair Party may attempt
to repair any one repairable Critical Hit:

•	 The active player rolls the Challenge d10d4 with a +1 DRM
for an Elite Grade Crew; –1 DRM if Green Crew.
•	 Any opposing player rolls the Response d10.
•	 If the Challenge is successful, remove the Critical Hit
marker (Exception: Flip an Armament 4/2 marker to its
Armament 2/1 side).

A Repair Party also automatically assists in fighting any and all
active Fires per the Fire Status Table. While present, apply a
–2 DRM to all Gunnery attacks by a ship or fort section with
a Repair Party.

3.1.2	Fire Status
A ship or fort section may have one or more fires burning at
the same time. Roll a d10 for each Fire marker and apply the
indicated results from the Fire Status Table, modifying the die
roll by the following:
•	
•	
•	
•	
•	

+2: The ship/fort has a Repair Party marker present
+1: The ship/fort has an Elite crew
–1: The ship/fort has a Green crew
–1: The Crew has heavy casualties (/#)
–2: The Crew has full crew casualties

A fire may either Extinguish, decrease 1 level, remain unchanged, or increase 1 or 2 levels. Level 3, 4 and 5 Fires also
apply a number of Hits per turn. After determining their
status, refer to the Fire Table and immediately apply the listed
number of Hits.

Note that fires affect movement and combat by applying the
listed modifier(s) to the respective die rolls.

If a Level 5 Fire is not reduced during the next turn’s friendly
Status Phase, the player must roll for an Explosion Critical Hit.
Remove the Level 5 marker and apply all indicated damage.
See the Critical Hit section of the rules [6.3.8] for resolution.

3.1.3	Smoke Status
Roll to remove each Heavy or Light Smoke marker in play on
the active side’s forts and ships. The player controlling the
ship or fort with the Smoke marker rolls one d10 and applies
DRMs if any:
•	 If the scenario stipulates ‘Fresh Wind’:	+1
•	 If the scenario stipulates ‘Calm’:	
–1
•	 If a fort or the ship is immobile [4.0]:	 –1

If the result is 7 through 10, remove a Light Smoke marker or
flip Heavy Smoke to Light. If the result is 11, remove any Smoke
marker.
Important Note: A ship also removes any Smoke marker if it moves
into a new Grid Box during the Movement Segment.

3.2	 Order Phase

The active side gives an Order to each of its ships by placing
one Order card next to each Ship card, face down, with the
applicable Order next to the Ship card.

3.3	 Action Phase

The phasing side resolves each ship’s order and fires its guns (or
fires a fort’s guns) one at a time until all have executed their
orders and/or fired. Players may choose their ships/forts in any
order desired, except all ships subject to drifting (voluntary or
un-powered) must move before any others.

3.3.1	Movement Segment (skip for Forts)
A. Order the Ship
	 Identify the ship, turn its Order card face up, and describe
its path and intended destination if Maneuvering. Ships
under power that are to remain in place or that are immobile
do not move, but are still subject to Action card play.
B. Play Movement Cards
	 The player controlling the ship may play any and all desired
Action cards (with “Movement” listed on the bottom edge)
on the moving ship.
C. Play Opposing Movement Cards
	 The opposing player(s) then may play any and all desired
Action cards (with “Movement” listed on the bottom edge)
on the moving ship.
	 Resolve each Action card as soon as it is played except those
applying to the Maneuver procedure. Note that certain
Action cards may be played on ships by either side during
a Movement Segment whether or not the ship attempts
to Maneuver.
	 Example: An opposing player may play a Slipped Anchor
Action card on a ship even though it cannot attempt to move.

D. Move the Ship
	 Resolve the Order and, if it drifts or Maneuvers successfully,
move the ship. If the ship does not drift or the Maneuver
fails, the ship remains in its starting location.
Fort Morgan, Mobile Bay
© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

3.3.2	Gunnery Segment
Ships and forts are not required to fire their guns, but other than
for Night Combat (when they may reveal their position), there is
no reason not to fire as there are no specific ammunition limits.
A. Remove Gunfire Markers
	 (Night Combat only; see 6.2.4)
B. Announce Target
	 Identify the ship or fort that is firing its guns and its target.
C. Play Gunnery Cards
	 The player controlling the ship or fort may play any and all
desired Action cards (with ”Gunnery” listed on the bottom
edge) on it.
D. Play Opposing Gunnery Card
	 The opposing side may play one Misfire card on the firing
ship or fort.
E. Resolve Gunnery
	 Resolve the gunfire and mark any resulting damage. Place
a Gunfire marker on the firing ship if battle is at night
[6.2.4].

3.4	 Replace Card Phase

Players never refill their hands. However, if the phasing side
did not play any Action cards from its hand during the current
turn and has not already replaced a number of cards equal to
half its original hand size, it may set aside one card from its
hand and draw a replacement card from the Action Card deck
(never from the discard pile). If the deck is exhausted, reshuffle
the discard pile to reform the Action Card deck.
•	 Set the card to be replaced facedown off to one side—not
in the discard pile. These cards may not be examined or
reused later; they are out of play.
•	 This serves two purposes. First, it does not reveal the card
to the opposing side. Second, it keeps a ready count of the
number of cards replaced.

3.5	 Victory Phase

If neither side has won, advance the Turn marker and begin a
new turn. Return all Order Cards to their respective sets.

3.5.1	Victory Conditions
Each scenario lists the conditions that must be met for either
side to claim victory. Usually they require the sinking or damaging of enemy ships and/or the exiting of friendly ships from the
play area. A ship is considered to have taken ‘Light Damage’
once it has suffered sufficient Hits to use the middle (second)
line of its Maneuver Chart. It has taken ‘Heavy Damage’ if it
has suffered sufficient Hits to use the bottom (third) line of its
Maneuver Chart.

9

4.0	ORDERS

During the Movement Segment, each ship must execute one
of the following Orders:

•	 Anchor
•	 Weigh Anchor
•	 Refloat
•	 Unfoul
•	 Drift
•	 Maneuver
Ships that are anchored, aground, fouled with a hulk or obstruction, or fouled with such a ship are immobile and may not Drift
or Maneuver. Any ship that is un-powered (i.e., has a Boiler or
Engine-S Critical Hit) or that is fouled with an opposing mobile
ship cannot Maneuver and must check for drift unless immobile.

The procedures for the Drift and Maneuver Orders are described
in the following section [5.0]. If a ship is given an illegal Order,
its Order changes to Drift unless immobile (in which case,
nothing happens). If an Order is rendered impossible by events
which occur after it is given and before it can be executed, is it
is changed to a Maneuver 0 order.

4.1	Anchor

Place an Anchored marker on the ship if in a Grid Box with
a Shoal depth of 4 or less. This prevents all movement by the
anchored ship.

4.2	 Weigh Anchor

Remove the Anchored marker. The ship is free to move in subsequent Movement Segments.

4.3	Refloat

A ship with a Grounded marker may attempt to break free.

4.3.1	Powered Ships
If the ship does not currently have an Engine-Damaged Critical Hit:

•	 The controlling player rolls the Challenge d10d8. Apply a
+2 DRM if one friendly powered ship that does not currently have an Engine-Damaged, Rudder, Speed, Smokestack
or Steering Critical Hit is grappled to the grounded ship
and is not immobile.
•	 Any opposing player rolls a Response d10.

If the Challenge fails, the ship remains aground. If the Challenge succeeds, remove the Grounded marker from the ship,
which may attempt to move normally during subsequent turns.
However, as a result of breaking free, the ship may suffer an
Engine-Damaged Critical Hit:
•	 The controlling player rolls the Challenge d10d8.
•	 Any opposing player rolls the Response d8.

If this Challenge succeeds, nothing happens. If it fails, place
an Engine-Damaged CH marker on the ship. In addition, if
the Response roll is triple or more than the Challenge roll also
apply a “WL” Critical Hit [6.3]. In either case, do not apply
any Hits as a result.
© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

10

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

If the ship currently has an Engine-Damaged Critical Hit:

•	 The controlling player rolls a Challenge d8. Apply a +2
DRM if one friendly powered ship is grappled to the
grounded ship and it does not currently have an EngineDamaged, Rudder, Speed, Smokestack or Steering Critical Hit.
•	 Any opposing player rolls the Response d10d8.

If the Challenge succeeds, remove the Grounded marker from
the ship, which may attempt to move normally during subsequent turns. If the Challenge fails, the ship remains aground
and replaces the Engine-Damaged Critical Hit with an EngineStopped Critical Hit. In addition, if the Response roll is triple
or more than the Challenge roll also apply a “WL” Critical Hit
(but do not apply any Hits as a result).

4.3.2	Un-powered Ships
If the ship currently has a Boiler or Engine-Stopped Critical Hit:
•	 The controlling player rolls a Challenge d6. Apply a +2
DRM if one friendly powered ship that does not currently
have an Engine-Damaged, Rudder, Speed, Smokestack or
Steering Critical Hit is grappled to the grounded ship and
is not immobile.
•	 Any opposing player rolls the Response d10d8.

If the Challenge succeeds, remove the Grounded marker from
the ship. If the Challenge fails, the ship remains aground. In
addition, if the Response roll is triple or more than the Challenge roll also apply a “WL” Critical Hit (but do not apply any
Hits as a result).

4.4	Unfoul

Attempt to unfoul a ship from an obstruction, hulk or ship:

•	 The controlling player rolls the Challenge d10, applying a
–2 DRM if fouled with a Heavy Obstruction.
•	 Any opposing player rolls a Response d10d4.

Note: There is no facing in Iron &amp; Oak. Ships may never move
through a Grid Box containing one or more opposing ships. They
may move into such a Grid Box but not through it on the same
move.

5.1	 Maneuver Procedure

Conduct powered ship movement by rolling the dice competitively, referring to the ship’s Maneuver Chart and the
Maneuver Response Chart to determine the appropriate dice
to roll. The player attempting the move rolls Challenge dice
based on the ship’s current Hits, and any opposing player rolls
Response dice based on the ship’s attempted movement per
the Maneuver Chart.
Example: Undamaged CSS Arkansas attempts to move to an
adjacent Grid Box. The Confederate player rolls a d10, and the
Union player rolls a d8d6.
The ship’s modified dice-roll result must exceed the opposing
(never modified) dice-roll result to complete the Maneuver. If
successful, move the ship to the new Grid Box or off the play
area as ordered, tracing its path if it is moving to a non-adjacent
Grid Box. If unsuccessful, the ship remains in its present position or off the map. When a ship enters the map, it always
ends its move in the Grid Box adjacent to its off-map position.

A number of situations can reduce a ship’s Maneuver dice or
cause positive or negative dice-roll modifiers to be applied.
All of these situations are cumulative, but the net DRM cannot
exceed “+/–5”.

5.1.1	Currents
Apply a positive DRM if the entire Maneuver is directly
downstream, and a negative DRM if any part of a Maneuver
is against a Moderate or Fast Current as shown:

If the Challenge succeeds, remove the Fouled marker from the
ship(s), which may attempt to move normally during succeeding turns.
If the Challenge fails and this is the first of one or more mobile
ships Fouled together to execute an Order this turn, check for
drifting [5.2].

Direction
of Current

5.0	MOVEMENT

During their Movement Segments, the Union and Confederate
players must attempt to move each ship with a Drift or Maneuver order (but see Maneuver 0 [5.1.3]). Ships under power may
attempt Maneuvers from off the play area onto a Grid Box on
the edge of the play area; from a Grid Box on the edge of the
play area to off the play area; within the Grid Box they currently
occupy; to an adjacent Grid Box; or to a non-adjacent Grid
Box that is two Grid Boxes away in distance. Ships may never
move to a Grid Box that is three Grid Boxes away in distance.
Ships may move in any direction vertically, horizontally or
diagonally. There is no extra cost to move diagonally, but ships
may make only one diagonal move in a turn, never two.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Direction
of Current

11

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

5.1.2	Opposing Maneuver
Use this order to hinder Maneuvering by an enemy ship located
in the same Grid Box. The ordered ship must not be:
•	 Anchored;
•	 Fouled;
•	 Grounded;
•	 Towing or under tow; or
•	 Across the bow or stern of any ship.

5.1.7	Maneuver 2
Use this Order when attempting to move to a non-adjacent
Grid Box that is two Grid Boxes away [5.1], including escaping
from a Bow-On or Stern-On position [5.5.3]. When tracing
the ship’s path, either of the two Grid Boxes may be entered
diagonally, but not both [5.0], and the diagonal move may not
pass between two enemy ships. If successful, remove any Smoke
marker on the ship.

If successful, designate one enemy ship that must
apply a –1 DRM if attempting to Maneuver in its
next Movement Segment unless it orders a Ram or
Spar Torpedo attack on the opposing ship or attempts
to Cross its ‘T’. Place an Opposed marker on the designated
ship. Regardless of how many Opposing Maneuvers succeed,
apply only one –1 DRM.
Play Note: In a large battle, players may wish to place the opposing
ship across the bow of its target with the Opposed marker between
them as an aid to recall which is the opposing ship.

5.1.3	Maneuver 0
Use this Order when attempting to escape from a Bow-On
or Stern-On position while remaining in the same Grid Box
[5.5.3], when playing a Screen Action card [7.7], or when
desiring to remain in position (including across an enemy’s bow
or stern). When remaining in position, no Maneuver rolls are
needed, but Hazards must still be negotiated [5.4].
5.1.4 Maneuver 0: Crossing the ‘T’
Use this order when attempting to cross the bow or stern of
an opposing ship.
5.1.5 Maneuver 0: Spar and/or Ram Attack
Use this order when attempting to Ram an opposing ship and/
or attack it with a Spar Torpedo.
5.1.6	Maneuver 1
Use this Order when attempting to enter or leave the map or
to enter an adjacent Grid Box [5.1], including escaping from
a Bow-On or Stern-On position [5.5.3]. If successful, remove
any Smoke marker on the ship.

Maneuver 2
not possible

5.2	Drifting

If a ship is un-powered (i.e., has a Boiler or Engine-Stopped
Critical Hit), fouled with an opposing mobile ship, or is ordered
to Drift, the phasing player rolls one d10 and refers to the
Drifting Table instead of using the Maneuver procedure. The
scenario map indicates the direction and speed (slow, moderate
or fast) of the current, if any.

If two or more ships are fouled or grappled together, check for
drifting only during the first of these ships’ Movement Segments
of each turn. If Drift results, all the fouled ships drift together.
Ships drifting off the gameboard either exit the map (and may
count towards victory conditions if appropriate) or automatically run aground on a marked bank edge of the map (including
diagonally off the corners where applicable). If the latter, mark
the ship counter in the same Grid Box with a Grounded marker.

5.3	Towing

A friendly powered ship that is not immobile may automatically
grapple a single friendly powered or un-powered ship or barge
located in its Grid Box at the start of its move for the purpose
of towing it to a new Grid Box, or more likely to tow it off of
the play area. Butt the two ship counters together and place a
Grappled marker on them. Then use the towing ship’s Maneuver
dice to determine movement for both ships. Grappled ships may
not be given a Maneuver 2 Order, and cannot move if either is
immobile. Apply a DRM per the Towing Chart:

•	 Subtract the towed ship’s original (undamaged) Hits value
from the towing ship’s original Hits value.
•	 Apply that result in the Chart to determine the modifier, if
any, the towing ship must apply to its movement die-roll.

USS Brooklyn after the battle of Mobile Bay.

Example: USS Zouave is towing USS Minnesota. The Maneuver
dice roll modifier is “–4” (3 – 17 = –14).
© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

12

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

The two ships/ship and barge may automatically ungrapple
at the start of their own Order Phase. Remove the ‘Grapple’
marker; the ships may then move normally.

5.3.1	Crossing the ‘T’ Maneuvers
A towed ship cannot have an Across the Bow Maneuver attempted against it. A towing ship cannot have an Across the
Stern Maneuver attempted against it.

5.4	Hazards

If a ship drifts or maneuvers into a new Grid Box or attempts
to maneuver within its starting Grid Box, and that Grid Box’s
Shoal Depth is less than the ship’s Draft or it includes one or
more Hulk, Obstruction, or Torpedo-Mine markers (all collectively known as “Hazards”), the ship must check to see if it
has safely negotiated each hazard. If more than one hazard is
present, an opposing player chooses the order in which they are
resolved. If two or more ships are grappled or fouled together
and the moving ship safely negotiates a hazard, each other ship
in succession must also check against that hazard (the moving
player determines the order if more than one).

5.4.1	Shoals
If the Shoal Depth in the Grid Box is less than the ship’s Draft,
determine if the ship runs aground:
•	 The controlling player rolls a Challenge die
•	 d10 if the ship’s current draft is 1 more than the Shoal
Depth;
•	 d8 if the ship’s current draft is 2 more than the Shoal
Depth; or
•	 d6 if the ship’s current draft is 3 or more greater than
the Shoal Depth.
•	 Any opposing player rolls a Response d10d6.

If the Challenge fails, place a Grounded marker on the ship and
end its movement.

5.4.2	Hulks and Obstructions
If the Grid Box has a Hulk or Obstruction marker:

•	 The controlling player rolls the Challenge d10d4, applying a –2 DRM for a Heavy Obstruction and –1 for each
additional Hulk.
•	 Any opposing player rolls the Response d10.

If the Challenge fails, place a Fouled marker on the ship and
end its movement.

5.4.3	Torpedo-Mines
For each Torpedo-Mine marker in the Grid Box:

•	 The controlling player rolls the Challenge d10d6.
•	 Any opposing player rolls the Response d10.

If the Challenge fails, the mine explodes. Roll a d8 on the ‘Mine’
column of the Torpedo Damage Table and apply the resulting
number of Hits to the ship.
•	 Increase the target’s WL “Shield” damage to –4.
•	 End its movement, and remove the Mine marker.

5.5	 Crossing the ‘T’

When starting the Order Phase in the same Grid Box as one
or more opposing ships, a special kind of Maneuver may be attempted if the moving ship is not already across the bow or stern
of an opponent. Use the Maneuver 0 (Crossing the ‘T’) Order
and, when this ship is selected during the Movement Segment,
designate an opposing ship in the same Grid Box to be the
target and specify whether attempting to cross its bow or stern.
•	 Since the attacking ship is moving within a Grid Box, the
player must first safely negotiate any potential hazards [5.4].
•	 The attacking player and the opposing player may play
Quick Maneuver and/or Slow Maneuver Action Cards
on the attacking and/or target ships if under power and
not anchored, aground, or fouled.
•	 Note any applicable movement dice-roll modifiers for both
the moving and target ships. If the target ship had executed
an Opposing Maneuver against the moving ship [5.1.2],
remove the Opposed marker.
•	 Automatically apply a DRM of “–1” to the moving ship.
	 Note: This is in addition to a potential Opposed maneuvering DRM.

•	 After determining the final modifiers, both ships roll their
current Maneuver dice. A Towed or Towing ship uses
the Towing ship’s Maneuver dice and applies any Towing DRMs [5.3]. Exception: If the target ship is anchored,
aground, or fouled, roll one d10 for its Response instead and
apply a –5 DRM. The moving ship must roll higher than
the target ship to succeed.

If unsuccessful, the moving ship cannot attempt to cross the
‘T’ of the same target ship during the next turn.

5.5.1	Across the Bow
If successful, butt the two ship counters together with the moving ship across the bow of the target.

•	 The target ship is now Bow-On to the ship across its bow
and is subject to a combat modifier if it fires at that ship
(it may fire normally at another ship). If an ‘X’ is listed in
the bow-on portion of its combat section it may not fire
at the ship across its bow at all.
•	 A ship may only be Bow-On to one ship at a time, and
cannot attempt to cross the ‘T’ of any ship.
•	 The target ship adds a +1 DRM to its Maneuver roll if
attempting a Ram or Spar Torpedo Attack on the ship
across its bow. When attempting any other Maneuver, the
ship suffers a –1 DRM to its roll.

5.5.2	Across the Stern
If successful, butt the two ship counters together with the moving ship across the stern of the target.

•	 The target ship is now Stern-On to the ship across its stern
and is subject to a combat modifier if it fires at that ship
(it may fire normally at another ship). If an ‘X’ is listed in
the stern-on portion of its combat section it may not fire
at the ship across its stern at all.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual
•	 A ship may only be Stern-On to one ship at a time, and
cannot attempt to cross the ‘T’ or make a Ram or Spar
Torpedo Attack on the ship across its stern.

5.5.3	Escape
To escape from a Bow-On or Stern-On position, either the
target ship or the ship across its bow/stern must Maneuver into
the same or a new Grid Box. The position also ends if either
ship drifts into a new Grid Box or they are fouled after a Ram
or Spar Torpedo Attack.

5.6	 Ram/Spar Torpedo Attacks

When starting the Order Phase in the same Grid Box as one
or more opposing ships, Ram and/or Spar Torpedo Attack
Maneuvers may be attempted. Use the Maneuver 0 (Spar and/
or Ram Attack) Order and, when this ship is selected during the
Movement Segment, designate an opposing ship in the same
Grid Box to be the target and specify which kind of attack (or
both) is attempted. Resolve Ram and Spar Torpedo Attacks
with a four-step procedure:
i.	 Determine if the attacking ship negotiates any Hazards
in the Grid Box [5.4];
ii.	 Determine if the attacking ship makes contact with the
target ship;
iii.	 If contact is made, resolve the attack(s).
iv.	 If contact was made, check for fouling.
A ship may combine a Spar Torpedo Attack with an immediately following ramming of the same target ship. The attacking
player must declare both attacks prior to determining if the
ship makes contact with the target. If it makes contact, it does
so for both attacks; it does not need to roll again for the ram
portion of the attack. Any damage, to either ship, as a result of
the spar torpedo attack is taken into account for the follow-on
ram attack. If the target or attacking ship sinks as a result of
the spar torpedo attack, the ram attack never occurs.

5.6.1	Making Contact
If the attacking ship successfully negotiates all Hazards in the
Grid Box, determine if contact is made.

•	 The attacking and the opposing players may play Quick
Maneuver and/or Slow Maneuver Action Cards on
the attacking and/or target ships if under power and not
aground, anchored, or fouled.
•	 Note any applicable Maneuver dice-roll modifiers for both
the attacking and target ships, including an automatic ‘–2’
DRM to the attacker’s roll and a ‘+1’ DRM to the attacker’s
roll if the target ship is across its bow. If the target ship
had executed an Opposing Maneuver against the attacking
ship [5.1.2], remove the Opposed marker.
•	 After determining the final modifiers, both ships roll their
current Maneuver dice. A Towed or Towing ship uses
the Towing ship’s Maneuver dice and applies any Towing DRMs [5.3]. Exception: If the target ship is anchored,
aground, or fouled, roll a d10 for its Response and apply a “–5”
DRM. The attacking ship must roll higher than the target
ship to make contact.
•	 If contact is made, resolve the attack(s). Otherwise, discard
any Action card(s) played and go on to the next move.

13

Example: CSS Atlanta is attempting to ram USS Nahant. USS
Weehawken is also present in the same Grid Box and she played
an Opposing Maneuver against CSS Atlanta. The Confederate
player plays a “Quick Maneuver +3” card on Atlanta and she is
bow-on to the monitor, while Nahant has a ‘Captain’ Critical Hit.
The Confederate final modifier is “+1” (– 2 + 1 + 3 – 1) due to the
BOW ON status, the Quick Maneuver card, and the Opposed
Maneuver from Weehawken. The Union final modifier is “–1”
due to the Captain’s injuries. Atlanta rolls a d10 with a result of
“6” which is modified to “7” (6 + 1). Nahant rolls a d10 with a
result of “6” which becomes “5” (6 – 1). The maneuver is successful.

5.6.2	Resolving a Spar Torpedo Attack
First roll to determine if the torpedo explodes:

•	 The attacking player rolls the Challenge d10d8.
•	 The target player rolls the Response d4.

If the Challenge succeeds, refer to the Torpedo Combat Table:
•	 The attacking player rolls a d8 and applies the resulting
number of Hits under the ‘Spar Torp’ column to the target
ship.
•	 Increase the target’s WL “Shield” damage to –4.
•	 The attacking player rolls a d8 a second time and applies
the resulting number of Hits under the ‘Ship Spar’ column
to the attacking ship.
•	 Place or increase the attacking ship’s WL “Shield” damage
based on the number of Hits incurred.
•	 Place a Spar CH marker on the attacking ship, but do not
apply any Hits as a result.

Example: CSS Atlanta is attacking USS Nahant with her Spar
Torpedo. The Confederate player rolls a d8 with a result of “3”; USS
Nahant receives “7” Hits and also applies a Shield –4 on her WL.
The Confederate player rolls the d8 again with a result of “5”; CSS
Atlanta incurs “1” Hit and also applies a Shield –1 on her WL.

5.6.3	Resolving a Ram Attack
Roll the attacking ship’s Ram dice from its ship card. Roll the
target ship’s WL defense dice. Compare the two results by subtracting the target ship’s result from the attacking ship’s result.
•	 If the result is positive, apply the resulting number of Hits
to the target ship.
•	 If the result is negative, apply the resulting number of Hits
to the attacking ship.
•	 If the result is “0”, both ships receive a number of Hits equal
to ½ the attacker’s result (round down) with a minimum
of “1” Hit.
•	 On each ship, apply WL “Shield” damage equal to the
number of Hits (up to 4) applied to that ship.

Example: CSS Atlanta is ramming USS Nahant. The Confederate
player rolls a d10d6 with a result of “8”. Nahant has a Shield –2
marker on her WL and the Union player rolls a d10d6d4 with a
result of “8” which is modified to “6” (8 – 2). Nahant receives “2”
Hits and also replaces the Shield –2 on her WL with a Shield
–4 marker.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

14

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

Example: Using the same ships as above, Atlanta’s result is “5”.
Nahant’s modified result is also “5”. Atlanta incurs “2” Hits (1/2
of “5” rounded down to “2”) and also applies a Shield –2 on her
WL. Nahant also receives “2” Hits and replaces the Shield –2 on
her WL with a Shield –4 marker.
After determining damage, check to see if the attacker’s ram
is damaged:
•	 The attacker rolls d10d8 Challenge dice.
•	 The target rolls a d8 Response die.

If the Challenge fails, place a Ram CH marker on the attacking
ship (but do not apply any Hits as a result).

5.6.4	Check for Fouling
If contact is made (whether or not a spar torpedo explodes) and
neither sinks, check to see if the ships become fouled:
•	 The attacker rolls d10d8 Challenge dice.
•	 The target rolls a d8 (if rammed) or d6 (if spar torpedo
only) Response die.

If the challenge fails, butt the ship counters parallel together
and place a Fouled marker on them. Until one or the other
succeeds in unfouling [4.4], both ships check for drift together
during subsequent Movement Segments unless either or both
are immobile.

5.6.5	Consequences
Whether or not contact is made, certain consequences apply
to the attacking ship:

•	 The attacking ship cannot attempt either a Ram or Spar
Torpedo attack (regardless of which one was originally
attempted) against the same target ship during the next
turn.
•	 If the attacking ship attempts to fire on the target ship
during its next Gunnery Segment, it must use its Bow-On
Combat dice.
•	 If the target ship is given a Maneuver 0 Order and fires
on the attacking ship during its next Gunnery Segment,
it fires at Point Blank Range.

5.7 Terrain

Terrain overlays may be added to Grid Boxes to alter the look
of the mapboard to create many different configurations. They
may be designated to represent any type of terrain from high
coastal areas to flat, low-lying islands or sandbars.
Unless a scenario’s Special Rules indicate otherwise, all mapboard terrain applies the rules for Gunnery and Movement in
section 5.7.1 below.

5.7.1 Gunnery &amp; Movement
Gunnery may be directed into a Grid Box containing terrain
against forts, but may not cross over a Grid Box containing
terrain as measured from the center of one Grid Box to the
center of another Grid Box unless the terrain is designated as
a low-lying island or Sandbar.

Actually crossing over the physical terrain is not necessary,
just the fact that terrain is located in a Grid Box. Firing along
a diagonal is allowed as long as terrain is not located in two
adjacent Grid Boxes split by a diagonal.
Ships may never enter a Grid Box containing terrain unless the
terrain is designated as a Sandbar (see 5.7.2).
Ships may never move between terrain located in two adjacent
Grid Boxes split by a diagonal.
Terrain acts in a similar manner as an opposing ship when attempting a Maneuver 2 order (see 5.1.7).

5.7.2 Sandbars
If a ship drifts or maneuvers into or attempts to maneuver within
its starting Grid Box and that Grid Box contains a Sandbar:

•	 The controlling player rolls the Challenge d10, applying a
-4 DRM and an additional –1 for each amount the ship’s
current draft is greater than 1 (remember, a ship’s draft
increases by 1 when at heavy damage).
•	 Any opposing player rolls the Response d10.

If the Challenge fails, place a Grounded marker on the ship
and end its movement.
Example: An undamaged CSS Virginia enters a Grid Box with
a Sandbar. The Confederate player rolls the Challenge d10 and
applies a -6 DRM (-4 for the Sandbar and an additional -2 for
the Virginia’s current draft, which is 3). Any Union player rolls
the Response d10.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

6.0	GUNNERY COMBAT

During a Gunnery Segment, the active ship or fort may fire
at only one opposing ship or fort section. A ship or fort may
fire at the same target as other ships/sections. Each section in
a fort fires individually.

6.1	 Combat Range

The combat ranges are:

•	 Long: The target is located in a non-adjacent Grid Box
that is two Grid Boxes away in distance.
•	 Medium: The target is located in an (orthogonally or diagonally) adjacent Grid Box to the firing ship or fort.
•	 Short: The target is located in the same Grid Box as the
firing unit.
•	 Point Blank: The target attempted a Ram or Spar Torpedo
attack on the firing ship during its previous Action Phase
or is Fouled with the firing ship.

Ships may never fire at a ship or fort in a Grid Box that is three
Grid Boxes distant. While forts are typically located at the edge
of the play area, each is considered to occupy the adjacent Grid
Box(es) for range determination purposes.

6.2	 Gunnery Combat Procedure

When a ship fires at a fort, it fires at one of the fort’s active
sections, not the entire fort.

When a ship fires its guns, the controlling player rolls the dice
found in the Gunnery Section of the ship’s card plus a yellow
d8 and applies any appropriate die-roll modifiers. The yellow d8
indicates the Hit Location on the target ship (for forts, there
is only one location—the targeted section). Once the Hit Location is identified, the player controlling the target ship then
rolls the defensive dice for that location and applies any ‘Shield’
die-roll modifiers. Either result may increase to any value, but
is never less than“1”.
Apply the modified dice results—Combat Result (CR) vs.
Defense Result (DR)—to determine gunnery damage:

•	 CR less than or equal to DR: No effect
•	 CR greater than but not double DR: Possible Effective Hit
•	 If the Hit Location does not have any Shield markers
present—no effect.
•	 If the Hit Location is Wooden with any ‘Shield’ marker
present—place “1” Hit.
•	 If the Hit Location is Armored with a ‘Shield –2’, ‘–3’
or ‘–4’ marker present—place “1” Hit.
•	 CR double but not triple DR: Effective Hit
•	 If the Hit Location is Wooden with any ‘Shield’ marker
present—place “2” Hits.
•	 If the Hit Location is Armored with a ‘Shield –2’, ‘–3’
or ‘–4’ marker present—place “2” Hits.
•	 In all cases, increase the ‘Shield’ marker by “–1” (placing
a Shield –1 marker if none present).
•	 CR triple or more than DR: Critical Hit.

15

•	 Increase the current ‘Shield’ marker at that location by
“–2” (placing a Shield –2 marker if none present) and
place “2” Hits.
•	 In addition, the attacking player rolls two d6 on the
Critical Hit Table and applies the listed result to the
target ship.
•	 If the Hit Location is WL, add 1 additional Hit.

6.2.1	Gunnery Modifiers
A number of situations cause positive or negative die-roll
modifiers to be applied to the gunnery dice-roll. All of these
situations are cumulative, but the result is never less than “1”.

Only Shield markers cause negative defensive die-roll modifiers
equal to the Shield value. The maximum Shield DRM in any location is –4, and the modified result is never reduced to less than “1.”

6.2.2	Hit Location
When firing at ships (forts are targeted as a specific section),
the Target Hit Location is determined by the yellow d8 on
the Hit Locations Table. The hit locations are also listed on
the ship cards.
If the target ship is Bow-On or Stern-on to the firing ship, treat
‘S’ hits as ‘B’ hits and ‘B’ hits as ‘S’ hits, respectively. Hits on a
monitor’s TF or TR are not subject to change, since a monitor’s
turret is considered to be rotating at all times throughout the
battle (even if it has a ‘Jam’ Critical Hit).
Note that if the target ship is subject to ‘Plunging Fire’ those
Hit Locations marked with an asterisk (‘*’) are treated as D
(deck) hits instead.

6.2.3	Special Considerations
A. Limited Guns
	 Ships with just a single d4 or a d6 as their combat dice are
classified as ‘Limited Guns’.
B. Fouled Ships
	 Fouled ships may fire on one another. They fire at Point
Blank Range, and treat all hits in the ‘WL’ location as ‘A’ or
‘TS’ hits instead. All Fouled ships except Monitors suffer
adverse Gunnery die-roll modifiers when firing.
C. Smoke
	 When firing with neither a Bow-On or Stern-On modifier
nor an Armament CH, place a Light Smoke marker on the
ship or fort section if the unmodified gunnery die roll is 8
or 10. If a ship or fort section with an existing Light Smoke
marker would get another, flip the marker to its Heavy
Smoke side instead. A ship or fort section is never subject to
more than a single Smoke marker. Apply Gunnery DRMs
for both the firing and the target ships/fort.
D. Plunging Fire
	 Forts firing on ships at Long Range may choose to treat ‘*’
location hits as Deck hits instead if they declare this option
before rolling the Gunnery dice.
E. Grounded Ships
	 A ship that is aground, and any non-Monitor fouled with
it or grappled to it, suffers adverse DRMs when firing. A

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

16

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual
ship or fort targeting a grounded ship or any ship fouled
or grappled to it enjoys positive DRMs.

F. Draft
	 A ship’s Draft increases by “1” once it suffers heavy damage
[3.5.1]. It is now riding lower in the water.

G. Crew Casualties
	 A ship with light (#/) or greater crew casualties suffers a
–2 DRM to its Maneuver rolls. Once a ship suffers heavy
(/#) or greater crew casualties, it must immediately retire
from the battle [6.2.3H]. Once a ship suffers full crew (#)
casualties, it may no longer fire.
H. Retirement
	 Any ship required to retire must exit the play area by assigning a Maneuver 1 order to move one Grid Box per
turn towards its friendly map edge (the edge marked by
the national flag in the scenario description) each turn
if possible. It may not play any Action Cards that would
impede its progress.

I. Captured Ships
	 If an opposing ship is captured through the play of a
Strike card, that ship must immediately retire towards
the capturing player’s map edge if able (see above) and
may not fire. For movement purposes, it utilizes the
‘Grade’ of the original crew. The ship may be fired on
as an opposing ship by the original side. If subsequently
sunk in the same battle, award only normal Victory
Points to the capturing side.
J. Sunken Ships
	 Any ship incurring a number of Hits greater than or equal
to its ‘Total Hits’ rating is sunk and removed from the
game. If Fouled or Grappled with another ship, remove
the marker—the other ship automatically breaks free. If
it sinks in a Grid Box with a shoal depth of “2” or less or
while Grounded, place a Hulk marker in its Grid Box.
K. Silenced Forts
	 A fort section that sustains Hits equal to or greater
than its ‘Hits’ rating or suffers full crew (#) casualties is
silenced and may no longer fire. If all a fort’s sections
are silenced, remove it from the game.

6.2.4	Night Combat
Some of the scenarios take place at night when sighting conditions are limited. Place a Gunfire marker and apply the single
largest DRM from the Night Combat Modifiers Table when
firing at a ship or fort and not fouled with the target.
Play Note: You may not fire at night at a target at Long Range
unless it is on fire or it fired its guns during its last Action Phase.
If a ship fires, it may be targeted at Long Range or the reduced
combat modifier at Medium Range applies for the next opposing
Action Phase only.

6.3	 Critical Hits

When a ‘triple’ hit is scored on a target ship or fort, the firing
player rolls two d6s and refers to the Critical Hit Table. Note
that there are five separate columns. On a Waterline (WL) hit,

use the appropriate WL column depending on whether the
target ship is Bow-On, Stern-On or normal to the firing ship.
Use the Ship column when the Hit Location is other than the
WL. If the target is a fort, use that column.
All Critical Hit markers show
one or two yellow “hit” symbols
for ease of recognition.

6.3.1	Armament (May Repair)
For the first Critical Hit, place an Armament –2
marker (Armament –1 for Limited Guns [6.2.3A]);
for the second, place an Armament –4 marker (Armament –2 for Limited Guns). For a third hit, Mark “2”
Hits on the ship or fort section instead.
•	 Apply the DRM to the ship’s gunnery roll.
•	 Successful repair of an Armament –4 CH flips the marker
to its Armament –2 CH side; for an Armament –2 CH,
remove it (for Limited Guns, replace it with an Armament
–1 marker); for Armament –1 CH, remove it.

6.3.2	Boiler
Target ship suffers an explosion and loses all power;
it is now subject to drifting. Place a Boiler marker on
the ship and resolve the explosion by:
•	 Hits: Roll a d10+d8 and apply the resulting total number
of Hits.
•	 Roll a d10 gunnery attack vs. any ships grappled or fouled
with the target ship.

If the target ship sinks, ignore the remaining steps:

•	 Crew Casualties: Apply the resulting number of casualties
to the target:
•	 If the Crew Factor is greater than ‘10’ roll a d8
•	 If the Crew Factor is ‘9’ or ‘10’ roll a d6
•	 If the Crew Factor is ‘8’ or less roll a d4
•	 Fire: Place a Level ‘3’ Fire marker on the target ship

If a ship with a Boiler marker is the target of a crossing the
“T” or Ram or Spar Torpedo attack, apply a –5 DRM to its
Maneuver  roll. For a subsequent Boiler hit, mark “2” Hits on
the ship instead.

6.3.3	Captain
Target ship’s captain is incapacitated. Place a Captain
marker on the ship. For a subsequent hit, mark “2”
Hits on the ship instead.
•	 All Gunnery and Maneuver applies a –1 DRM to the roll.
•	 If it is the target of a crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo attack, apply a –1 DRM to the Maneuver roll.

6.3.4	Collateral
Protection damage extends to an adjacent location. Add “–1”
Shield damage to:
•	 Hit Location “B” or “S”—place on “A”
•	 Hit Location “TF” or TR”—place on “TS”
•	 Hit Location “A”—place on “B” or “S” at targeted player’s
choice

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual
•	 Hit Location “TS”—place on “TF” or “TR” at targeted
player’s choice
•	 Hit Location “WL” or “D”—place on any location of the
targeted player’s choice other than the original location

If all potential target locations are already at ‘Shield –4’, apply
2 Hits to the ship instead.

6.3.5	Crew
Roll one die:

•	 If the Crew Factor is ‘8’, ‘9’ or ‘10’ roll a d6
•	 If the Crew Factor is ‘7’ or less roll a d4
•	 Fire: Place a Level ‘3’ Fire marker on the ship
•	 For a fort, resolve the explosion by:
•	 Hits: Roll a d10+d6, and apply the resulting total number of Hits.
If the section is destroyed, ignore the remaining steps.
•	 Crew Casualties: Roll a d4 and apply the resulting
number of casualties.
•	 Fire: Place a Level ‘3’ Fire marker on the section.

6.3.9	Fire
A fire starts on the target. Roll a d10 and, depending on the
result, place a new Fire marker:

•	 If the Crew Factor is greater than ‘10’ roll a d8
•	 If the Crew Factor is ‘8’, ‘9’ or ‘10’ roll a d6
•	 If the Crew Factor is ‘7’ or less roll a d4

Apply casualties up to ½ the current crew size (round down,
minimum “1” casualty). If the ship has casualties equal to its
full crew, ignore subsequent hits.
Example: The Atlanta has a Crew Factor of ‘9’, so a d6 is rolled.
On a result of 4, 5 or 6, 4 casualties are applied. On results of 1, 2
or 3, the actual result rolled is applied as casualties. For subsequent
Critical Hits, the original Crew Factor of ‘9’ is still used to determine what to roll.

6.3.6	Engine-Damaged (May Repair)
Target ship’s engine has suffered damage. Place an
Engine-Damaged marker on the ship. For a subsequent hit, replace Engine-Damaged with an EngineStopped marker.
•	 Ship applies a –2 DRM to all Maneuver rolls.
•	 If it is the target of a crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo attack, apply a –2 DRM to its Maneuver roll.

6.3.7	Engine-Stopped (May Repair)
Target ship’s engine has stopped; the ship is now
subject to drifting. Place an Engine-Stopped marker
on the ship (and remove an Engine-Damaged marker, if any). For a subsequent hit, mark “2” Hits on the
ship instead.
•	 If it is the target of a crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo, apply a –5 DRM to its Maneuver roll.

6.3.8	Explosion
Target ship/fort suffers an explosion:

•	 For a ship, resolve the explosion by:
•	 Hits: Roll a d10+d6 and apply the resulting total number of Hits.
•	 Roll a d10d6 gunnery attack vs. any ships grappled or
fouled with the target ship.
•	 Roll a d10 gunnery attack vs. any other ships in the
same Grid Box.

If the target ship sinks, ignore the remaining steps.

17

•	 Crew Casualties: Apply the resulting number of casualties to the target:
•	 If the Crew Factor is greater than ‘10’ roll a d8

•	 1-4: Level ‘2’
•	 5-8: Level ‘3’
•	 9-10: Level ‘4’

6.3.10	 Jam (May Repair)
A monitor’s turret(s) is jammed. Ship applies a –2
DRM to gunnery rolls. Place a Jam marker on the
ship. For a subsequent hit, mark “2” Hits on the ship
instead. For a non-monitor type ship, treat as a Collateral Critical Hit instead.
6.3.11	Magazine
Target ship/fort suffers a catastrophic explosion:

•	 For a ship, resolve the explosion by:
•	 Hits: Roll a d10+d8+d6 and apply the resulting total
number of Hits.
•	 Roll a d10d8d6 gunnery attack vs. any ships grappled
or fouled with the target ship.
•	 Roll a d10d4 gunnery attack vs. any other ships in the
same Grid Box.

If the target ship sinks, ignore the remaining steps.
•	 Crew Casualties: Apply the resulting number of casualties to the target:
•	 If the Crew Factor is greater than ‘10’ roll a d8
•	 If the Crew Factor is ‘8’, ‘9’ or ‘10’ roll a d6
•	 f the Crew Factor is ‘7’ or less roll a d4
•	 Fire: Place a Level ‘3’ Fire marker on the target ship
•	 For a fort, the section is destroyed.

6.3.12	Ram
Target ship’s ram is damaged. Apply a –5 DRM to
all ram combat resolutions (not the procedure to
determine if the ship contacts its target). Place a Ram
marker on the ship. For a subsequent hit, mark “2”
Hits on the ship instead.
6.3.13	 Rudder (May Repair)
Target ship applies a –4 DRM to all Maneuver rolls.
It may not attempt any crossing the “T” or Ram or
Spar Torpedo attacks. Place a Rudder marker on the
ship. For a subsequent hit, mark “2” Hits on the ship
instead.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

18

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

•	 If it is then the target of a crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo attack, apply a –4 DRM to its Maneuver roll.

6.3.14	 Spar Torpedo
Target ship’s spar torpedo is destroyed. Place a Spar
marker on the ship. For a subsequent hit, mark “2”
Hits on the ship instead. If the ship is not equipped
with a spar torpedo or it already expended its spar
torpedo in an attack, treat as a Collateral Hit instead.
6.3.15	Speed
For the first Critical Hit, place a Speed –1 marker on
the target ship; for the second, flip the marker to its
“Speed –2” side. For a third hit, mark “2” Hits on the
ship instead.

•	 Apply a –1 or –2 DRM to all Maneuver rolls as appropriate.
•	 If it is the target of a crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo attack, apply a –1 or –2 DRM to its Maneuver
roll as appropriate.

6.3.16	Smokestack
Ship’s funnel is destroyed, reducing draft to its
boiler. Place a Smokestack marker on the ship. For a
subsequent hit, mark “2” Hits on the ship instead. For
a monitor type ship, treat as a Collateral Critical Hit
instead.
•	 Apply a –2 DRM to all Maneuver rolls.
•	 If it is the target of a crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo attack, apply a –2 DRM to its Maneuver roll.

6.3.17	 Steering (May Repair)
Ship’s steering mechanism is damaged. Place a Steering marker on the ship. The ship may only move
within its current vertical or horizontal Band. It may
not attempt any crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo attacks. For a subsequent hit, mark “2” Hits on the
ship instead.

•	 Roll a d6 and on the result:
•	 1-3: Ship must stay in its vertical band. Place the ‘Steering’ marker vertically on the ship as a reminder.
•	 4-6: Ship must stay in its horizontal band. Place the
‘Steering’ marker horizontally on the ship as a reminder.
•	 If it is the target of a crossing the “T” or Ram or Spar
Torpedo attack, apply a –3 DRM to its Maneuver roll.

7.0	ACTION CARDS

There are 12 different types of Action Cards included in the
game; they are summarized below. The [#] following each card’s
name indicates the number of that specific card included in the
50-card deck. Each type may be played either during a Gunnery
Segment or a Movement Segment. Unless otherwise indicated,
multiple Action Cards of different types may be played at the
same time, combining their effects.
Example: Double Charge and Grapeshot Action Cards could
be played in the same combat, but two Grapeshot cards could not.
When played, most cards are discarded face-up next to the Action Card deck. Some cards are placed on ship cards for reference purposes. Once their action is complete, they are discarded.

7.1	 Double Charge [5]—Gunnery Segment

Cannot play in combination with Rapid Fire. Adds a modifier
to the combat resolution based on range, but there is automatic
Smoke placement and a chance of armament damage. After
resolving the combat, place a Light Smoke marker on the firing
ship or fort and roll for the armament damage: if the Challenge
fails, place an Armament Critical Hit marker on the firing ship
or fort. Do not apply any Hits as a result of placing the Armament Critical Hit marker.

7.2	 Grapeshot [5]—Gunnery Segment

Grapeshot cannot be played in combination with Incendiary
Shells, and may only be fired at Short or Point Blank Range
at ships or forts. It cannot be fired against monitor-type ships
unless one or more non-WL locations are currently marked
with a Shield –4 Protection Damage marker.
If the crew (through symbol or Shield damage) is vulnerable
and the target ship is not a monitor, it may suffer both crew
and smokestack damage from the same shot.
Resolve Grapeshot fire differently than normal combat. Compare the attack and defensive die rolls (including all normal
DRMs) and, if the attack roll is greater than the defense roll,

1) If the crew is subject to Grapeshot fire or the non-WL
location hit has a Shield –4 marker, apply crew casualties
equal to the difference up to ½ (round down) of the target
ship’s remaining crew factor with a minimum of “1” Hit.

	

Example: The attack die-roll result is an “8” and the defensive
result is a “2”; the difference is “6”. The target ship has a Crew
Factor of “8”, so “4” crew casualties are applied (1/2 of 8). The
remaining “2” casualties are ignored.

2) If the target ship is not a monitor, place a Smokestack
Critical Hit marker on the ship if the Hit Location equals
“3”, “4”, “5”, or “6”. If a damaged smokestack is hit again by
Grapeshot, ignore the effects. Do not apply any Hits as a
result of placing a Smokestack Critical Hit marker.

Never change the ‘Shield’ status of the position hit. Grapeshot
cannot cause Critical Hits (other than Smokestack per (2)
above).
© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

7.3	 Incendiary Shells [5]—Gunnery Segment

Cannot play in combination with Grapeshot. Apply a –1
DRM to the combat. This card may start a fire on the target ship
if the combat causes any damage (i.e., Hits are applied). Apply
all other damage caused by the combat normally including a
fire started from a Critical Hit.
•	 If the decision die roll is:
•	 Greater than: apply a Level 1 Fire marker
•	 Double: Level 2 Fire marker
•	 Triple or more: Level 3 Fire marker

19

7.8	 Scuttle [4]—Movement Segment

Play this card to sink a friendly grounded or un-powered ship. If
grounded or in a Grid Box with Shoal Depth of 2 or less, place a
Hulk marker [6.2.3J]. If the ship is grappled or fouled, the other
ship automatically breaks free. Award normal Victory Points.

7.9	 Slipped Anchor [2]—Movement Segment

Play this card to flip the Anchored marker on an opposing ship.
The same ship may never anchor again.

7.10	 Slow Maneuver [6]—Movement Segment

7.4	 Misfire [4]—Gunnery Segment

Play this card before an enemy makes a roll to hit. Apply a –2
die roll modifier to the combat. After resolving the combat,
roll for the armament damage: if the Challenge fails, place an
Armament Critical Hit marker on the firing ship or fort. The
player controlling the firing ship rolls the Challenge dice. Do
not apply any Hits as a result of placing the Armament Critical
Hit marker.
If the enemy played Rapid Fire, this card has no effect on the
second shot.

7.5	 Quick Maneuver [6]—Movement Segment

Play this card to improve a friendly powered ship’s Maneuver
attempt by applying a positive modifier of “+1”, “+2” or “+3” to
the maneuver dice roll.
The opposing side may play a single Slow Maneuver card on
the same ship to counteract its impact.

7.6	 Rapid Fire [5]—Gunnery Segment

Cannot play in combination with Double Charge. Play of
this card enables two shots in a row. If Grapeshot or Incendiary Shells is played in combination, these cards apply to
both shots. Roll the two shots individually, with the second
shot automatically targeting the same location as the first.
Any damage as a result of the first attack is taken into account
for the second. After resolving both shots, place a Light Smoke
marker on the firing ship.

Play this card to hinder an opposing powered ship’s Maneuver
attempt by applying a negative modifier of “–1”, “–2” or “–3” to
the maneuver dice roll.

The opposing player may play a single Quick Maneuver card
on the same ship to counteract its impact.

7.11	 Springs [1]—Movement Segment

Play of this card enables an anchored ship to conduct combat
without applying the negative fire modifiers. It is still subject
to the positive fire modifiers when fired at. Place the card on
the anchored ship, where it remains. Remove the card when
the Anchored marker is flipped or removed.

7.12	 Strike [4]—Movement Segment

Play this card to capture an opposing ship that is aground,
un-powered, or fouled with a hulk, obstruction, or one of your
ships. Compare the VPs of all ships under power in the same
Grid Box as the target (including ships fouled with the target).
If the friendly total exceeds the enemy total (always including
the target ship), the target ship immediately surrenders; otherwise the card has no effect. Place a Captured marker on the
surrendered ship and award double Victory Points. Captured
ships may not be recaptured by the original side during the
same scenario.

7.7	 Screen [3]—Movement Segment

Play this card when executing a Maneuver 0 Order to defend a
designated friendly ship in the same Grid Box. If the maneuver is successful, immediately select one opposing ship or fort.
During the next opposing Action Phase:
•	 The opposing ship or fort cannot fire upon the designated
ship (Exception: A battery using Plunging Fire [6.2.3D]).
•	 The opposing ship cannot attempt to make a Ram/Spar
Torpedo Attack or Crossing the ‘T’ of the designated ship.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

20

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

8.2	 Campaign Game Sequence of Play

8.0	CAMPAIGN GAME

The Iron &amp; Oak Campaign Game pits player-selected forces in
a series of randomly generated battles. As play unfolds, players
do not know the exact length of the campaign or the specific
mix of battle scenarios. The only thing known for certain is that
a campaign consists of at least 5 battles. Players must plan for
every possibility and assume they are in it for the long haul—not
unlike their historical counterparts.
Pick a fairly large play area so there is adequate room for all of
the ship cards, gameboard, markers, and card decks.

8.0.1 Campaign Scenarios:
During the American Civil War a few open water battles did
take place, e.g., Iron &amp; Oak Scenario 8. Nevertheless, the vast
majority of the battles were fought out in the many rivers, bays,
inlets and coastal areas. The Campaign Game mirrors those
brown water actions.
The various components required for each battle, including
the gameboard setup and Action cards, are different for each
scenario based on its rules and requirements and other playerdetermined conditions as set forth in the Campaign Game
section of the Play Book.

8.1	 Campaign Log

The Confederate and Union players each document the specific
campaign information on their respective Campaign Logs
including scenario types, ships selected, and outcomes. Players may fill out the Campaign Log in any convenient manner,
but the following are suggested notations for uniform record
keeping.

•	 List all starting ships by name, their individual Victory
Points, the total points for the starting force, and any ships
added through the play of Replacements Yard cards in
their respective sections.
•	 On the Battle # line, list the scenario type and whether the
Attacker or Defender. For Engagements, list the maximum
ship Victory Points allowed. If a Crew Grade Yard card
is played on your side, note whether you played it (‘+’) or
your opponent did (‘–’). If more than 10 battles are required,
use the back side or an additional page.
•	 List all ships committed to a battle and their Crew grades.
Circle those ships added through the play of Out of The
Mist Yard cards, and note any suffering the effects of
Limited Ammunition cards.
•	 Use each scenario’s blank map section to note banks, shoal
depths, current and direction and any other notations such
as obstructions and torpedo/mines.
•	 If the scenario is a Night Action [8.6], circle the “N” on
the scenario line.
•	 If you win the battle, circle the “W” on the scenario line.
If you lose, do nothing.
•	 At the conclusion of the campaign, summarize the results
at the bottom.

See page 22 for a sample Campaign Log.

1.	Campaign Setup
A. Select Forces (Union and Confederate)
•	 Select Ships
•	 Assign Crew Grades
B. Generate the First Battle Scenario
C. Assign Ships to the First Battle
2.	Pre-Battle Actions
A. Generate the Next Battle Scenario
B. Assign Ships to the Next Battle
3.	Battle
A. Set Up the Battle
B. Play the Battle
4.	Post-Battle Actions
A. Assess Victory
B. Return Ships
C. Discard Cards and Shuffle Decks
D. Draw and Play Yard Cards
E. Refit &amp; Repair Ships
F. Roll for the End of the Campaign

8.3	 Campaign Setup

8.3.1 Select Initial Forces
Union and Confederate players determine their campaign forces
based on the following criteria:

•	 Each side secretly selects and notes on their respective
Campaign Logs at least 6 and no more than 10 ships totaling 3,200 Victory Points or less. After both sides have
selected their ships, openly display them for review.
•	 Each side receives 2 Crack Grade and 2 Green Grade
markers and openly assigns them to their respective ships.
All remaining ships start play at Average Grade.

8.3.2 Generate the First Battle
Roll to determine the first battle’s scenario using the Campaign
Game procedure in the Play Book. Then secretly select and
record the forces for this battle as prescribed for that scenario.

8.4	 Pre-Battle Actions

8.4.1 Generate Next Battle Scenario
If the campaign will not end at the conclusion of the upcoming
battle, the side that last won a battle rolls one d10 to generate
the next scenario.

•	 If this is the start of the campaign and the first battle has
not yet been played, the player who did not roll to generate
the first battle scenario rolls for this one.
•	 Determine Attacker/Defender, Force Sizes, Current,
Shoals, Wind, and whether this battle will occur at night
[8.6], and record this information on the Campaign Logs.

8.4.2 Assign Ships to the Next Battle
Secretly record ships committed to the new battle, i.e., one battle
in advance. Captured ships are considered part of the capturing

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual
side’s force and may be committed normally. You may not use
any of the ships currently committed to the upcoming battle,
or those ships sunk or captured by the opposing side.
•	 Unless a side has no uncommitted ships remaining, at least
one ship must be committed to each battle, regardless of
its current repair status, if it
(1)	meets the Victory Point limit, if any, and
(2)	has not incurred heavy (/#) or greater crew casualties.
•	 If no ships are committed, the opposing side wins the battle
by default.
•	 If neither side is able to commit any ships, the Defender
wins the battle.

8.5	Battle

Simultaneously reveal the ships previously committed to the
current battle. Review the scenario rules and victory conditions,
set up the gameboard, apply any previously played Out of The
Mist and Limited Ammunition Yard cards, deal out the appropriate number of Action cards, and start play.

8.6	 Night Battles

Committed ships are not revealed at the start of the scenario.
Use these rules in addition to 6.2.4 if the battle is fought at
night.

8.6.1 Identification
Identified ships are face-up, while unidentified ships and False
Contacts start hidden (face down). All ships set up hidden in
night battles.
To identify any hidden ship or False Contact, each friendly
ship (not False Contacts) may search for one hidden ship or
False Contact in the same Grid Box at the end of its Movement
Segment. After designating the target, roll one d10:
•	 1-6:	 Search unsuccessful
•	 7-10:	 Target identified

Also immediately identify a ship if it fires its guns or attempts
a Crossing the ‘T’ [5.1.4], Spar Torpedo, or Ram Maneuver
[5.1.5].

Once identified, a ship remains face up for the remainder of
the battle; permanently remove False Contacts from play. Only
identified ships may be the target of gunfire, crossing the ‘T’
maneuvers, or spar torpedo or ramming attacks.

8.6.2 Movement
Ships may not attempt to move two Grid Boxes per turn at
night. Hidden ships use their actual Maneuver dice or may use
any dice smaller than their actual rating as a means to disguise
their identity. They may never use dice greater than their actual
rating. False Contacts use the same maneuver dice as the actual
friendly ship(s) they are mimicking.
8.6.3 Hazards
When encountering Shoals, Hulks, or Obstructions, apply a
–2 DRM to the Challenge roll in addition to any other modifiers [5.4].

21

8.7	 Post-Battle Actions

8.7.1 Assess Victory
If this was the last battle of the campaign [8.7.6], the side
winning the greatest number of battles is declared the winner.
If not, apply any previously played Crew Grade Yard cards.
8.7.2 Return Ships
Return all surviving ships from the battle to their respective
forces, including un-powered ships and ships fouled with obstructions or hulks. With the exception of Fires (automatically
extinguished), ships retain any and all damage, Critical Hits
(including reparable Critical Hits) and crew losses suffered
during the scenario.
8.7.3 Discard and Shuffle Cards
Discard all played Crew Grade (after determining any change
in grade), Out cf The Mist, and Limited Ammunition Yard
cards and shuffle that deck together with its discards. Return
all Action cards (played or unplayed) to that deck and shuffle.
8.7.4 Draw and Play Yard Cards
Both sides draw Yard cards if they committed ships to the
battle just completed.

•	 Deal 2 new Yard cards to the winning side.
•	 Deal 1 new Yard card to the losing side. If the losing side
did not commit any ships to the scenario, they are not dealt
a card.
•	 If neither side committed any ships to the scenario, do not
deal Yard cards to either side.

Both sides play any desired Fast Repair, Replacements, Yard
Fire or In Short Supply Yard cards, including those cards just
drawn, on their Navy Yards. Both sides may also play any desired
Crew Grade, Out of The Mist, or Limited Ammunition
Yard cards; they will apply to the immediately upcoming battle.
The side that most recently won a battle plays first. After all
cards are played, sides must discard if necessary to reduce their
hands to the limit of three Yard Cards each.

8.7.5 Refit and Repair
Both sides repair and refit their ships as desired, including any
captured ships [8.8]. Discard any Fast Repair, Replacements,
Yard Fire or In Short Supply Yard cards played after resolving their effects.
8.7.6 Campaign End
Starting after Battle 4, and following at the completion of
every even numbered battle thereafter, the player who won the
just-completed battle determines if the campaign will end at
the conclusion of the next odd-numbered battle. Roll one d10:
•	 Completion of Battle 4: on a result of 1-3, ends after
Battle 5;
•	 Completion of Battle 6: on a result of 1-5, ends after
Battle 7;
•	 Completion of Battle 8: on a result of 1-7, ends after
Battle 9;
•	 Completion of Battle 10 and every even-numbered
battle thereafter: on a result of 1-9, ends after the next
odd-numbered battle.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

22

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

8.8	 Repairing and Refitting Ships

Only the very lucky are able to return from battle without some
damage or crew loss. Players repair and refit their ships at the
conclusion of each battle at their Navy Yards before generating
a new one. This includes those ships already committed to the
next battle. Both sides receive a base set of repair, critical hit
and crew replacement points. The base amount for each side
may increase or decrease through a series of die rolls.

Players may expend repair, critical hit and crew replacement
points as desired. They are not required to expend any points;
however, points do not carry over from turn to turn. Ships may
be fully repaired, partially repaired or not repaired at all. It is
best to have one side conduct their repairs and refits while the
other side observes and then the other side does the same.
Note: Any Fast Repair and Yard Fire Cards played modify the
chance for both repair points and critical hit points.

8.8.1 Repair Points
Each side receives a base of “10” repair points to remove Hits
and protection damage from ships. Remove 1 Hit or ‘Shield’
for each repair point expended.
•	 Roll one d10, applying any modifiers from Fast Repair
and Yard Fire Cards. On a result of:
•	 1 or less: “–5” repair points
•	 2-9: No effect
•	 10 or more: “+5” repair points

8.8.2 Critical Hit Points
Each side receives a base of “3” critical hit points to repair
critical hit damage from ships. Remove 1 Critical Hit for each
point expended.
•	 Roll one d10, applying any modifiers from Fast Repair
and Yard Fire cards. On a result of:
•	 1 or less: “–2” critical hit points
•	 2-9: No effect
•	 10 or more: “+2” critical hit points
•	 The Engine-Stopped Critical Hit on the ‘target’ ship in a
Defend scenario is repaired automatically unless the ship
is captured.

8.8.3 Crew Replacement Points
Each side receives a base of “5” crew replacement points to
replace ship crew losses. Replace 1 crew factor for each replacement point expended.

•	 Roll one d10, applying any modifiers from Replacements
or In Short Supply cards. On a result of:
•	 Less than 1: “–3” crew replacement points
•	 1 through 9: No effect
•	 10 or more: “+3” crew replacement points
•	 If a ship receives replacements equal to more than half of
its base crew capacity (round up), Elite, Crack and Average
Grades decrease one level. Green Grade is unaffected.
•	 Elite, Crack and Average Grade crews may transfer from
ship-to-ship to consolidate and maintain a grade level.

•	 The entirety of the remaining crew on a captured ship
must be replaced by a new crew before the ship may be
committed to combat. Any grade the ship had, e.g., Elite,
Crack or Average, is lost. The new grade is Green.
•	 A ship may sail without a full crew, as long as it has less
than heavy (/#) crew casualties.

8.9	 Yard Cards

There are seven different types of Yard cards included in the
game; they are summarized below. The [#] following each card’s
name indicates the number of that specific card included in the
16-card deck. Unless otherwise indicated, multiple Yard cards
may be played at the same time, combining their effects.
Shuffle the Yard Card deck during Post-Battle Actions after
discarding any Crew Grade, Out of The Mist, or Limited
Ammunition Yard cards from the just-completed battle and
before drawing any new cards [8.7.3]. The maximum hand size
is three Yard cards. A side must discard any cards in excess of
the maximum hand size after playing any desired cards.

The friendly side always has the option of first playing any desired cards on their ships or Navy Yard. The opposing side may
then play any desired cards on the opposing ships or Navy Yard.
Fast Repair and Replacements cards may also be played in
response by the friendly side to cancel out the play by the opposing side of Yard Fire and In Short Supply cards, respectively.

8.9.1 Crew Grade [4]
After both sides reveal their ships at the start of a scenario, play
this card on either the friendly or opposing side to potentially
increase or decrease a randomly-chosen ship’s grade based on
the outcome of the scenario. After determining the results at
the end of the battle, if any, discard the card.

When selecting the affected ship, apply the following criteria:
•	 Do not include any Barge or Steamer;
•	 If the battle was won, do not include any ship that suffered
crew casualties greater than the light threshold (#/) or
incurred a Captain Critical Hit [6.3.3]. For example, USS
Hartford may not be included if it has incurred 9 or more crew
casualties;
•	 If the battle was lost, a ship with a Captain Critical Hit
must be selected if any are present.

A ship’s grade may only increase if the battle was won. Increase
the ship’s grade by a single level and mark the ship with the
appropriate grade marker if other than Average Grade.
A ship’s grade may only decrease if the battle was lost. Decrease
the ship’s grade by a single level and mark the ship with the
appropriate grade marker if other than Average Grade.

A ship’s grade can never be greater than Elite or less than Green.

8.9.2 Fast Repair [2]
Play this card on your friendly Navy Yard. It may add additional
repair and/or critical hit points. Roll individually for each type,
applying a +2 die roll modifier [8.8.1-2]. You may play both
cards for a +4 die roll modifier. Discard after determining the
results.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

Circle Side

List Ships
Ships Total Points

Replacements
additional ship

Out of the Mist
additional ship

Night Action
Battle Type

Crew Grade
increase

Map configuration
with shorelines,
current, shoal,
depths, wind and
obstructions

Battle won

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

23

24

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

You may also play this card in response to cancel a Yard Fire
Card. Discard both cards.

9.0	OPTIONAL RULES

8.9.3 In Short Supply [2]
Play this card on an opposing Navy Yard. It may limit or reduce
the number of crew replacements by applying a –2 die roll
modifier [8.8.3]. A player may play both cards of this type for
a –4 die roll modifier. Discard after determining the results.

Players desiring increased realism may elect to use any or all of
the following rules. They should only be used if all players agree.

8.9.4 Limited Ammunition [2]
After both sides reveal their ships at the start of a battle (including ships appearing Out of The Mist), randomly select
an opposing ship (other than a Barge or Steamer). A side may
play only a single card per ship. The ship must apply a –1 DRM
to all gunnery combat dice rolls [6.2.1].

9.2	Tenders

You may also play this card in response to cancel a Replacements card. Discard both cards.

9.1	 Low Freeboard

When a WL hit location (1 or 8) is rolled against a monitor
or USS Spuyten Duyvil, reroll the location d8 and apply this
second result, regardless of its location.
When towing another ship [5.3], treat CSS Bombshell and USS
Zouave as having twice their actual undamaged Hits when
calculating the Maneuver DRM.

9.3	 Alternating Movement

8.9.5 Out of the Mist [2]
Play this card to add a single non-committed ship to the friendly
side in the upcoming battle. If the ship is valued at 500 or more
Victory Points, the opposing side may also add a single noncommitted ship valued at less than 500 Victory Points.

Instead of one side completing the first four Phases before the
other, both sides conduct each of these phases simultaneously.
Before beginning Turn 1, divide the Order card sets into odd
and even groups: 1, 3, 5, 7, 9, 11, 13, 15 and 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12,
14, 16. The side designated to move first in the scenario (or the
Attacker in a campaign game) will use the odd numbered group.

Discard at the end of the battle.

9.3.1 Status Phase
Both sides conduct each of the five steps of this phase simultaneously. Each side must still check any Level 5 Fires first before
checking the status of its other fires.

A side may play only a single card per battle, although both
sides could play the card resulting in up to four additional ships.

8.9.6 Replacements [2]
Play this card on a friendly Navy Yard. It may add an additional
ship or additional crew replacements, not both, by applying
a +2 die roll modifier when determining crew replacements
[8.8.3]. A player may play both cards for two ship attempts,
or a single ship attempt with a +2 die roll modifier, or a single
ship attempt and a +2 die roll modifier for crew replacements,
or a +4 die roll modifier for crew replacements. Discard after
determining the results.

If an additional ship is added, select it from the group of friendly
ships out of play. A ship previously sunk may not be selected.
A lower Victory Point value ship may be selected instead of
the indicated value if desired or if one is not available. The ship
enters play at Average Grade.
You may also play this card in response to cancel an In Short
Supply Card. Discard both cards.

8.9.7 Yard Fire [2]
Play this card on an opposing Navy Yard at the end of a scenario.
It may limit repair and/or critical hit points. Roll individually
for each type, applying a –2 die roll modifier [8.8.1-2]. You
may play both cards for a -4 die roll modifier. Discard after
determining the results.
You may also play this card to cancel a Fast Repair card.
Discard both cards.

9.3.2 Order Phase
Both sides simultaneously assign orders to their ships per 3.2.
A ship may be assigned any Order card set # within its side’s
group, and is not required to keep the same Set # from turn
to turn. A side may not skip any sets when assigning Orders.
Example: The Confederate side has two ships and goes second in
Scenario 2, Hampton Roads, so the Confederates will use sets 2 and
4 in this battle. When assigning orders on Turn 1, the Confederate
player chooses to use Set 2 for CSS Virginia and Set 4 for Patrick
Henry On Turn 2, he may (but need not) decide to switch this order
and use Set 2 for Patrick Henry and Set 4 for Virginia.

9.3.3 Action Phase
Ship #1 executes its order and fires first, followed by ship #2,
and so on.
If an order was valid when given but has become illegal, e.g.,
the only enemy ship in your Grid Box is now across your stern
and you have a Maneuver 0 Cross the ‘T’ order, you may change
your order to Maneuver 0.

9.3.4 Replace Card Phase
The side moving first decides whether or not to set aside and
replace one Action card in its hand [3.4], then the other side.

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

25

26

Iron &amp; Oak Rules Manual

INDEX

Note: Where there are multiple entries, numbers in bold face indicate
primary references.

Action Cards 1.3.2, 3.3.1B-C, 3.4, 5.5.6, 7.0; Replacement of 3.4, 9.3.4
Aground see Grounded
Anchor 4.1, 5.1.2, 5.5; Slipped 7.9; and Springs 7.11;
Weigh 4.2
Band 1.1, 6.3.17
Bank 1.1, 5.2
Blockade Battle Symbol 1.3.1H
Boiler Hit 4.0, 4.3.2, 5.2, 6.3.2
Bow-On 5.1.6, 5.5.1, 6.2.2; Escaping 5.1.3, 5.1.6-7, 5.5.3; Gunnery
DRM 1.3.1K, 5.6.5, 6.2.3C
Campaign 8.0; Battle Generation 8.2.2, 8.4.1-2; End 8.7.1, 8.7.6;
Repair 8.7.5, 8.8, 8.9.2, 8.9.7; Setup 8.3; Victory 8.7.1
Capture 6.2.3I, 7.12; and Repairs 3.1.1
Cards 1.3; see also card types (e.g., Action Cards)
Casualties 6.2.3G, 6.3.5, 6.3.8, 6.3.11, 7.2, 8.4.2; Heavy 1.3.1E, 3.1.2,
6.2.3G, 8.4.2, 8.8.3; Light 1.3.1E, 6.2.3G, 8.9.1
Challenge Resolution 1.6.1B
Collateral Hit 6.3.4, 6.3.10
Crew 1.3.1E; Casualties 6.2.3G, 6.3.5, 6.3.8, 6.3.11, 7.2, 8.4.2; Grade
3.1.1-2, 6.2.3I, 8.1, 8.3.1, 8.9.1; Replacement 8.8.3, 8.9.3, 8.9.6
Critical Hit (CH) 6.2, 6.2.2, 6.3; Repair of 3.1.1, 8.8.2
Crossing the ‘T’ 5.1.4, 5.3.1, 5.5; Across the Bow 5.1.2, 5.3.1, 5.5.1,
5.6.1; Across the Stern 5.1.2, 5.3.1, 5.5.2
Current 5.1.1, 5.2
Damage 3.5.1; Heavy 6.2.3F
Dice 1.6; Challenge-Response 1.6.1B; Gunnery 6.2;
Rolls 1.6.1; Sum 1.6.1C
Draft 1.3.1F, 5.4, 5.4.1; When Damaged 6.2.3F
Drifting 3.3, 4.0, 5.0, 5.2, 5.4, 5.5.3
Engine-D Hit 4.3.1, 6.3.6
Engine-S Hit 4.0, 4.3.2, 5.2, 6.3.7
Environment 1.1
False Contact 8.6.1
Fire 3.1.2, 6.3.8-9, 6.3.11, 7.3; and Repair Parties 3.1.1, 3.1.2
Fort Counters 1.2; Gunnery from 6.0, 6.2, 6.2.3D, 7.1;
Range to/from 6.1; Sections 6.0, 6.2
Fouled 5.1.2, 5.4-5, 5.5.3, 5.6iv, 5.6.1, 6.3.2, 7.12; Becoming 5.4.2,
5.6.4; Drifting when 5.2; Sinking while 6.2.3J, 7.8
Gameboard 1.1; Entering 5.1, 5.1.6; Exiting 5.1, 5.1.6, 5.2
Grapeshot 7.2; Symbol 1.3.1H
Grappled 4.3.1-2, 5.3, 5.4, 5.6.1, 6.3.2; Drifting when 5.2; Sinking
while 6.2.3J, 7.8
Grid Box 1.1; and Gunnery Combat 6.1; Movement Into/Within
5.0, 5.1-3
Grounded 4.3, 5.1.2, 5.2, 5.4.1, 5.5, 5.6.1, 7.12; and Gunnery 6.2.3E;
Sinking while 6.2.3J, 7.8
Gunfire Markers 6.2.4; Placing 3.3.2E; Removing 3.3.2A
Gunnery 3.3.2C-D, 5.6.5, 6.0, 7.1-4, 7.6-7, 8.6.1; Dice 1.3.1K; DRMs
6.2.1, 6.2.3E, 6.2.3G, 6.2.4, 6.3.1, 6.3.3, 6.3.10, 7.3-4, 7.11, 8.9.4;
Procedure 6.2; and Repair Party 3.1.1; and Smoke 6.2.3C
Hazards 5.1.3, 5.4-5, 5.6i; at Night 8.6.3

Hits 5.6.2-3, 6.2; Critical 6.3; Locations 1.3.1G, 6.2, 6.2.2; to Sink
6.2.3J
Hulks 4.4, 5.4, 5.4.2; Placing 6.2.3J, 7.8, 7.12, 8.6.3
Immobile Ship 4.0, 5.3
Limited Guns 1.3.1K, 6.2.3A
Low Freeboard 9.1
Maneuver 3.3.1D, 4.0, 5.0, 5.1, 5.3-6, 5.6.5, 6.3.3, 6.3.15-16, 7.5, 7.7,
7.10; Chart 1.3.1D; Dice 1.3.1D, 5.1, 5.5; at Night 8.6.2-3; Opposing 5.1.2, 5.5, 8.6.2
Markers 1.4
Mines see Torpedo-Mines
Misfire 3.3.2D, 7.4
Monitor 1.3.1H, 7.2, 9.1; Gunnery by a 6.2.3B; Jam 6.3.10
Movement 1.6.1A, 3.1.3, 3.3.1, 5.0; Cards 3.3.1B-C, 7.0; and Hazards
5.4, 8.6.3; see also Drifting, Maneuvering
Night Identification 8.6.1; Combat 6.2.4, 8.6.1; Movement 8.6.2-3
Obstructions 4.4, 5.4, 5.4.2, 7.12, 8.6.3; Heavy 4.4, 5.4.2
Orders 3.2, 3.3.1A, 4.0; Cards 1.3.3, 3.2, 9.3
Plunging Fire 6.2.3D
Powered Ship 4.0, 4.3.1
Ram 5.1.2, 5.1.5, 5.5.1, 5.6, 6.2.3H, 6.3.2, 6.3.6-7; Attack Resolution
5.6.3; CH 6.3.12; and Gunnery 6.1; Rating 1.3.1I
Range 5.6.5, 6.1, 6.2.4, 7.2; Point Blank 6.1, 6.2.3B
Refloating 4.3
Repair 3.1.1; Campaign 8.7.5, 8.8, 8.9.2, 8.9.7; Party 3.1.1
Retirement 6.2.3G, 6.2.3H
Screen 5.1.3, 7.7
Scuttling 7.8
Shields 5.6.2-3, 6.2, 6.2.1, 6.3.4, 7.2
Ship Captured 6.2.3I; Cards 1.3.1, 7.2; Counters 1.2;
Gunnery 6.0
Silenced Forts 6.2.3K
Sinking 5.6, 6.2.3I, 6.2.3J, 7.8
Smoke 3.1, 3.1.3; Placement 6.2.3C, 7.1, 7.6; Removal 3.1.3, 5.1.6-7
Smokestack 7.2; CH 6.3.16
Spar Torpedo 1.3.1J, 5.1.5, 5.5.2, 5.6, 6.2.3H, 6.3.6-7, 6.3.13, 6.3.1517; CH 6.3.14; Attack Resolution 5.6.2
Stern-On 5.1.6, 5.5.2, 6.2.2; Escaping 5.1.3, 5.1.6-7, 5.5.3; Gunnery
DRM 1.3.1K, 6.2.3C
Strike see Capture
Torpedo-Mine 5.4, 5.4.3
Towing 5.1.2, 5.3, 9.2
Turn Track 1.1
Unfouling 4.4
Un-powered Ship 4.0, 4.3.2, 7.8, 7.12
Victory 3.5.1; Campaign 8.7.1; Phase 3.5; Points 1.3.1C, 6.2.3I, 7.8,
7.12
Wind 3.1.3
Yard Cards 8.1, 8.7.3-4, 8.9

© 2013/2014 GMT Games, LLC

GMT Games, LLC

P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308

</rulebook>
			
						                           
						               													<description>Iron and Oak is game of ship-to-ship combat set during the American Civil War. As a tactical representation of naval warfare, each of the ships is accurately modeled for offensive capability including gunnery, ramming and spar torpedoes; for defensive capability including damage and five distinct armored or wooden hit locations; and for maneuverability, crew size and draft.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;You command 70 famous ships of the era, including the Union: Onondaga, Tecumseh, Winnebago, Monitor, Osage, Minnesota, Brooklyn, Hartford, Essex, Carondolet, Kearsarge, Ossipee, Queen of the West, Iroquois, Spuyten Duyvil; and the Confederate: Tennessee, Virginia, Atlanta, Palmetto State, Arkansas, Albemarle, Alabama, Florida, General Beauregard, Sumter; and many more.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Many of the 14 scenarios, in this easy-to-learn game, are playable in an hour or less. Included are 13 historical and 1 hypothetical engagements featuring Hampton Roads, Mobile Bay, Trent&amp;rsquo;s Reach, Wassaw Sound, the duel between Alabama and the Kearsarge, and the saga of the Arkansas, which may be played as three individual scenarios or as a linked mini-campaign.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;In addition, forts bristling with guns make their appearance to challenge the will of the ship captains. If that was not enough to heat things up, scenario based optional rules add a few interesting &amp;lsquo;what if&amp;rsquo; situations to expand on play.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;If you are interested in commanding your own fleet, Iron and Oak includes a standalone campaign module where player selected forces fight it out in the many rivers, bays, inlets and costal areas. The campaign game recreates the brown water actions, typical of the period, in a series of randomly generated battles. As play progresses, the players do not know the exact length of the campaign or the specific mix of the battles. Players must not only manage the unfolding battles, but must also strategically allocate resources and repair and refits their ships. The 16 card Navy Yard deck is used to plot a course through and influence the challenges of the campaigns.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Two or more players battle it out on an 22&amp;rdquo; x 34&amp;rdquo; map that features an area movement grid. This simple approach controls ship movement as well as all combat action. Gone are the long periods of inaction, typical of ACW tactical naval games, as these early steam-era ships struggled to maneuver into battle.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;This innovative game system places the emphasis on quick action and tactical decision making. The 50 Action Cards are used to assist and enhance play, not drive it. Each time you battle it out, whether in a scenario or campaign game, the action unfolds in a very different manner. Do you wish to employ hot shot or incendiary shells? Is now the best time to rapid fire or is it wise to maneuver and ram? Should you allocate part of the crew as a repair party? Is that enemy ship going to maneuver into your torpedo (mine) field? These and many other possibilities exist through the play of the action cards. Or, you may decide to not play any action cards at all and just maneuver and shoot. You control how and when the action will unfold.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;At its core Iron and Oak is a naval simulation. It accurately models the close-range slugging matches typical of the period. You have the opportunity to play out the various battles to their conclusion. Will history repeat itself, or will a new account be written? Will the Monitor&amp;rsquo;s 11&amp;rdquo; Dahlgren smoothbores blast through Virginia&amp;rsquo;s armor plating or will their battle again end in a stalemate? Will the powerful Tennessee win out against Admiral David Farragut&amp;rsquo;s Union fleet or again fall to his superior numbers? Will the Atlanta defeat the two Union monitors in kind or again slip aground and strike her colors. This time, you get to determine the outcome. You are not bound by history&amp;rsquo;s stories.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2013" />
						               				<minplayers value="2" />
						               				<maxplayers value="2" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="8">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="5" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="3" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="7" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="3" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="90" />
						               				<minplaytime value="90" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="90" />
						               				<minage value="12" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="7">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="4">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="3" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="1" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1048" value="American Civil War" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1102" value="Civil War" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1008" value="Nautical" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1019" value="Wargame" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2046" value="Area Movement" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2072" value="Dice Rolling" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="14835" value="Country: USA" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="61979" value="Players: Two Player Only Games" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="1922" value="James M. Day" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="2652" value="Charles Kibler" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="71" value="Rodger B. MacGowan" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="78647" value="Louis Prang" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="52" value="GMT Games" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="180" />
			<average value="6.74406" />
			<bayesaverage value="5.61871" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="6892" bayesaverage="5.61871" />
																				<rank type="family" id="4664" name="wargames" friendlyname="War Game Rank" value="1046" bayesaverage="6.08806" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.55237" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="645" />
			<trading value="24" />
			<wanting value="28" />
			<wishing value="84" />
			<numcomments value="95" />
			<numweights value="32" />
			<averageweight value="2.5938" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>