<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="12283">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/MS2xFXOTVpfPPmPl1kAEhQ__thumb/img/nTH_6Vi0ZQ4H2TFv4m13Qq-yimY=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic72411.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/MS2xFXOTVpfPPmPl1kAEhQ__original/img/boJ6-mNuYF1n1KI0TEt5winwVFA=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic72411.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Manifest Destiny" />
				<rulebook>Manifest Destiny

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC
P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308
www.GMTGames.com

1

#0406
© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

Manifest Destiny

2

1.0 OVERVIEW
Manifest Destiny is a card driven strategy game for 3 to 5 players set in the Americas, between 1760 and 2000. Each player
controls one of five mercantile empires and attempts to fulfill
their destiny. The five empires are based in Louisiana, Mexico,
Pennsylvania, Quebec, and Virginia. The player best responding to the opportunities the game presents fulfills their destiny—
and wins!

2.0 OBJECT OF THE GAME
The object of the game is to be the player with the most Victory
Points at the end of the investment or expansion phase after someone reaches at least 30 Victory Points. Purchasing Progressions,
researching Breakthroughs, and controlling the most Cities earn
Victory Points.

3.0 COMPONENTS
3.1 Each game of Manifest Destiny includes:
•
•
•
•
•
•

This Rule Booklet
One Reference Booklet
One Mapsheet
64 Influence Cards (50 Progress Cards and 14 Destiny Cards)
Five Product Payout/Sequence of Play cards
One sheet of stickers

• Three Sheets of Deeds (two of sheet 1, and one of sheet 2).
These include:
—20 Breakthrough Deeds (2 sets of 10 cards)
—75 Progression Deeds (5 sets of 15 cards)
• One full-color Breakthrough Chart
• Five full-color Progress Mats
• Five sets of Control Tokens (1/4" cubes, 25 in each set)
• Each player also gets 12 1/2" cylinders in his player color.
These tokens are used for the following:
—Seven are used as Breakthrough Tokens
—One is used for a Victory Point Token
—One is used for a Profit Token
—One is used for a Turn Order Token
—One is used for a Turn Order Choice Token
—One is provided as a spare
• 20 City Tokens (1/2" blocks, gray)
• Five Native Tokens (1/2" blocks, dark red)
• Three Tourist Tokens (1/2" blocks, orange)
• Two Technology Tokens (1/2" blocks, brown)
• One Surplus Token (1/2" block, black)
• Five Tokens to indicate +100 on the Profit Track (1/2" blocks,
light blue)
• One Most Cities Victory Point Token (1/2" block, light green)
• One Panama Canal Token (1/2" block, black)
• One Era Track Token (1/2" block, white)
• Four spare Tokens (1/2" blocks, white)
• $38,000 play money in denominations of $5, $10, $20, $50,
$100
• five 6-sided dice

INFLUENCE CARDS
Progress Cards

Destiny Cards
Card #
Era the card may be
used in. In this case its
a Multiple Era Card
(8.13) and can be used
in all three Eras
(recycled).

Progression
Deed

Event

Both the Event
and the Product
Payout occurs
when the card is
played.
Either the Event or
the Product Payout
may be used—not
both.

Not used in the
3-player game

Product Payout

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

Breakthrough
Deed

Manifest Destiny

3

3.2 Tokens and Progress Mats

4.3 Three Player Setup

See page 11 for a description of the tokens and stickers and their
initial placement. Before your first game, number the Progress
Mats (using the stickers supplied) 1 through 5 in the upper left
hand corner.

Use the Five Player Setup with the following exceptions: Remove the following Influence Cards from their respective decks:
Hudson Bay Company, Remember the Alamo, Ben Franklin,
Thomas Jefferson, Robert Fulton, War of 1812, Star Spangled
Banner, Davy Crockett, Samuel Morse, P.T. Barnum, Reconstruction, Seward’s Folly, Thomas Edison, The 60’s, Amelia
Earhart, Dust Bowl, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Lawyer, Elvis
Presley, and Civil Disobedience.

3.3 Rule References
Numbers in parenthesis represent references to other sections of
the rulebook.

3.4 Map Board
The map is of the United States, Canada, Mexico, Central
America and Foreign Markets. The United States includes Alaska
and Hawaii. The map is divided into the following regions:
Canada, Northern US, Southern US, Northwest (includes Alaska),
Southwest (includes Hawaii), Mexico, Central & South America,
and Foreign Markets (Foreign Markets are Asia, Australia, Europe, Middle East, and Africa).

3.5 Control Tokens
Each player has 25 Control Tokens available during the game.
These tokens are used for controlling territories on the map, tracking Pioneers, tracking Breakthroughs, and purchasing Cities, Pioneers, and Cards.

4.0 GAME SETUP
4.1 Five Player Setup
Each player selects a set of 25 colored Control Tokens and 12
cylinder tokens and receives $60 to start the game.
Separate the Influence Cards into 4 decks: Era 1 Destiny Cards
(Cards #1-6), Era 1 Cards (Cards #14-32 and #61-64), Era 2
Cards (Cards #7-9 and #33-46), Era 3 Cards (Cards #10-13 and
#47-60).
Each player starts with three cards. Randomly deal each player
one Era 1 Destiny Card and then shuffle the remaining Era 1
Destiny Card with the Era 1 Card Deck. Deal each player two
additional cards from this deck. Place the remainder of the Era 1
deck face down on the board. Place the Era 2 and Era 3 decks off
to the side for later use.
• Place each player’s Profit Token on the 30 Space of the Profit
Track.
• Place each player’s Victory Point Token on the 0 Space of the
Victory Point Track.

4.2 Four Player Setup
Use the Five Player Setup with the following exceptions: Remove the following Influence Cards from their respective decks:
Hudson Bay Company, Thomas Jefferson, Davy Crockett, P.T.
Barnum, Reconstruction, Seward’s Folly, Amelia Earhart, Dust
Bowl, Elvis Presley, and Civil Disobedience.
• Place each player’s Profit Token on the 20 Space of the Profit
Track.
No movement or expansion is allowed in Canada.

Place each player’s Profit Token on the 20 Space of the Profit
Track.
No movement or expansion is allowed in Canada or Mexico.

5.0 TURN SEQUENCE
Unless otherwise noted, players move in turn order during each
phase, each player completing a phase before the next player
begins his phase. Once the following player has taken an action,
a player may not change actions previously taken or take any
additional action.
Each turn is broken up into five phases:
1. Turn Order Phase
2. Card Play Phase
3. Investment Phase
4. Expansion Phase
5. Adjustments Phase
Prior to the first turn, there is an additional Home Territory Selection Phase.

6.0 HOME TERRITORY
SELECTION PHASE
In this phase, players select their Home Territory by bidding for
the right to choose their Home Territory.

6.1 Determine Bid Order
Each player places one of his cylindrical tokens in an opaque cup.
One player draws the tokens (one by one) from the cup. The order
in which the tokens are drawn determines the bidding order.

6.2 Place Bids
Players bid by placing any amount of money in multiples of $5
(including zero) on the table. After all players have had a chance
to bid, players will choose their Home Territory based on their
bids, from highest to lowest. If two or more players bid the same
amount, whoever bid the amount first will choose ahead of the
other tied players.

6.3 Select Home Territory
Beginning with the highest bidder and continuing in order of
amount bid, players select their Home Territory. They place a
Control Token colored side up on their Home Territory, pay the
amount of their bid and receive a Progress Mat, numbered 1-5
(3.2), corresponding to the order in which they choose their Home
Territory.

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

4

Manifest Destiny

6.4 Home Territories Available
Five Player game: Louisiana, Mexico, Pennsylvania, Quebec,
and Virginia
Four Player game: Louisiana, Mexico, Pennsylvania, and Virginia
Three Player game: Louisiana, Pennsylvania, and Virginia

7.0 TURN ORDER PHASE
At the beginning of each turn, players choose their turn order for
the coming turn. Players choose their turn order based on the
Turn Order Choice Box (8.62). Players indicate their Turn Order by placing one of their tokens on the appropriate space of
the Turn Order Track.
For the first turn, players choose turn order in the same order
they chose their Home Territory (6.3).

8.0 CARD PLAY PHASE
During the Card Play Phase, players may play Influence Cards
from their hand, in turn order, by placing them face up in front
of them. The cards remain face up until the beginning of the
next Turn Order Phase. Players may play (in any order):
• Possibly One Destiny Card from the current Historical Era
(subject to Destiny Card restrictions; see 8.2); and/or
• Any number of Progress Cards from the current Historical
Era.

8.1 Historical Eras
The top of each card lists an Historical Era or Eras. Era 1 spans
1760-1860; Era 2 spans 1861-1920; Era 3 spans 1921-2000.
Cards can only be played if the Era on the top of the card matches
the current Era of the game turn. Use the Era token on the Era
Track to record which Era the game is in and which cards can be
played.
8.11 Eras: When an Era deck is exhausted, shuffle the cards
from the next Era deck and the recycled cards together to form
the next deck. Cards played in the current turn are not recycled
at this time. If eligible to be recycled, the cards played in the
current turn will be recycled in the next Era.
8.12 New Era: A new Era begins once the first card in the new
Era deck is drawn. When this happens, the next Card Play Phase
is a transition turn. This means that cards from the previous Era
and the new Era may be played. During a transition turn, if the
Era affects how the card is applied, the player playing the card
may choose which Era applies.
NOTE: As soon as a new era begins, the era token moves into
the 1/2 or 2/3 box during the transition turn, and then into 2 or 3
at the end of the card play phase.
8.13 Multiple Era Cards: Certain cards may be played in more
than one Era, indicated by having multiple Era listed on the top
of the card. After being played, these cards are eligible to be

recycled at the beginning of the next Turn Order Phase by adding them to the deck of the next Era. Some cards can be played
in either of 2 Eras, indicated on the card as “Era 1 or 2” or “Era
2 or 3”. These cards are not recycled.

8.2 Destiny Cards
When a Destiny Card is played, both the event and the product
payout (8.331) occur.
8.21 One Destiny Card Per Turn. Except as allowed by Section 8.22 below, only one Destiny Card may be played during
each turn by all of the players (so if the player moving first plays
a Destiny Card, no other player could play a Destiny Card that
turn).
8.22 Patriotism: A player owning the Patriotism Breakthrough
may play one extra Destiny Card each turn (one if one has already been played and two if none has been played).

8.3 Progress Cards
8.31 Leader Cards provide discounts on Progressions and possibly some other benefits. These discounts are applicable only
to the player playing the card unless two players are collaborating (9.351). If a player plays a Leader Card that provides a discount on a Progression the player already owns, the player receives a rebate of 1/2 of the listed credit. Rebates are only available from Leader Cards. Discounts from event cards do not entitle a player to rebates.
8.32 Event Cards trigger actions that affect the play of the game.
These include items such as creating products, natives occupying territories, expansion roll modifications, movement enhancements, profit adjustments, territory control changes, counter cards
or response cards.
8.321 Creating Products: Internet, Teddy Roosevelt, and Babe
Ruth place additional Product Tokens in Territories. These tokens remain until the end of the game and add the stated Product
to this Territory, even if control of the Territory changes.
8.322 Natives: The Native Sovereignty card adds Native Tokens to certain Territories. These tokens act as deterrents to expansion and must be defeated in a competition roll in order to
expand into that Territory. The Homestead Act card can be used
to remove Natives.
8.323 Expansion Roll Modifications: Cards that effect expansion rolls may allow either fewer Control Tokens to be spent to
attempt a competition roll, winning ties when attacking, or rerolling a competition roll. Examples are: War of 1812 and Star
Spangled Banner.
8.324 Movement Enhancements: These cards allow movement
to certain Territories during expansion that a player would not
otherwise be able to reach. An example is Oregon Trail.
8.325 Profit Adjustments: Some cards provide for adjustments
to a player(s) Profit. Examples include: Abolitionists/Civil Rights
Movement and Reconstruction.
8.326 Territory Control Changes: These cards include placing
Control Tokens in a Territory, replacing another player’s Con-

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

Manifest Destiny
trol Token with your own, or eliminating Control Tokens in a
Territory. When a card results in a player gaining control of a
Territory, the player has the choice of placing a token as a New
Presence (10.22), or an Established Presence (10.23). If a card
results in a player ceding Territories to another player, the losing
player chooses the Territories, though they must be accessible to
the player gaining them. If a card requires Territories to be ceded
and no player may legally take them, the Territories are left vacant. Examples of the different territory control cards include:
Revolutionary War, Homestead Act, Trustbusters, and Lawyer.
8.327 Counter Cards: These cards counter the effects of an
event card. They can be played during another player’s turn to
counter another player’s card play. When a counter card is played,
the player playing the first card suffers the effect of the card
instead. A card may not be played against a player who has played
the counter to the card during his Card Play Phase earlier in the
same turn. Counter cards are President, which counters Spy, and
Abraham Lincoln, which counters Civil War. If President is
played as Technology, it does not counter Spy during that turn.
8.328 Response Cards: In addition to the counter cards, there
are also response cards, which also may be played during another player’s card play. They are played in response to a card
play made by another player and void the effects of the played
card. The original card remains played for turn order purposes
only. The response cards are President and Supreme Court.
8.33 Event/Product Cards contain both an event and a product
payout. The player playing the card must decide to execute either the event or the product payout.
8.331 Product Payouts: When a product payout occurs, each
player controlling territories producing that product receives a
payout. The amount paid is based on the number of territories of
that product controlled by each player, up to a maximum of six.
A territory with two of the same product (Middle East: Oil and
Central America: Produce) counts twice. The payout is increased
by one level if the player has built one or more cities in territories containing that product. A player who controls a territory
with two or more products receives payouts for all products in
the territory when the appropriate product card is played.
8.3311 Surplus: Once a product is paid out, the product is in
surplus for the remainder of the turn. In addition, the Black Tuesday and The Depression Event Cards place all products in surplus for the remainder of the turn. When one of these two cards
are played, place the Surplus Token in the Surplus All Box on
the map to indicate that all products are now in surplus. At the
end of the Card Play phase, the Surplus token is removed from
the map.
8.3312 Effects of Surplus: Payouts for products in surplus are
reduced by one level for the remainder of the turn.
Example: 3 Livestock in surplus would pay $10 rather than $20
and 1 Livestock in surplus pays $0.

8.332 Multiple Recipients: All tied players qualifying for the
effect of a played card are affected by the card. Cards that have
effects on multiple players may affect the same player multiple

5

times. For example, if a card affects the player with the most
Victory Points, the Highest Profit, and the most Cash on Hand,
one player could be the recipient of all three results if he had
most VP’s, Highest Profit, and most Cash.
8.333 News: President and Supreme Court may be played as
“News.” Unlike other cards, cards played as News may be played
without using the event or product listed on the card. They would
be played as “News” for their card number only (8.62).
8.334 Breakthrough Steps: Some leaders provide one or more
steps needed in researching Breakthroughs. When the card is
played, place a Breakthrough Step token on the indicated step(s)
on the Breakthrough Chart (9.412). If the step(s) allow a player
to complete the Breakthrough, that player may claim the Breakthrough (9.42) during this Card Play Phase. Collaboration is not
allowed during this phase.

8.4 Held Cards
Players may hold up to three cards at the end of the Card Play
Phase without penalty. Players lose 5 Profit for each extra card
held beyond three.
8.41 Storytelling: Players owning the Storytelling Breakthrough
may hold four cards before incurring the penalty. Owners of the
Storytelling Breakthrough also are allowed to discard cards (8.5).

8.5 Discarding Cards
Cards may not be discarded unless a player owns the Storytelling
Breakthrough. A player owning the Storytelling Breakthrough
may discard one card face down and out of play when Storytelling
is acquired and then once per turn during each Card Play Phase.

8.6 Turn Order Tokens
8.61 Card Numbers: Each card has a number between 1 and
64. Cards are numbered sequentially, with Destiny Cards being
1-14 and Progress Cards being 15-64.
8.62 Turn Order Choice: After everyone has completed their
Card Play Phase, the Turn Order Choice for the following turn is
determined. Turn Order Choice is based on the highest numbered card a player played. The player who played the highest
numbered card receives 1st Choice, the 2nd highest—2nd Choice,
etc. Each player places one of his cylindrical tokens in the appropriate Turn Order Choice box on the map to indicate this.
This comes into play in the next Turn Order Phase (7.0). If two
or more players did not play a card, they receive the Turn Order
Choice in the order in which they chose their Home Territory.
This can be determined by looking at the numbers on the Progress
Mats.
8.63 Priority Turn Option: Each player has a Priority Turn
Option that may be used once during the game. This option allows a player to exchange their Turn Order Choice with another
player’s Turn Order Choice to allow them an earlier choice of
turn order during the next Turn Order Phase. Once a player has
used this once-per-game option he places one of his Control
Tokens in the Priority Turn box located on the map. This Control Token is lost to the player for the remainder of the game and
signifies that his Priority Turn Option has been used.

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

Manifest Destiny

6

PROCEDURE: During a player’s turn during the Card Play
Phase, Investment Phase, or Expansion Phase, a player may elect
to use their Priority Turn Option by announcing this intent. The
player then takes the 1st Choice space with each other player
exchanging their space for the next highest number.
If more than one player uses their Priority Turn Option in the
same game turn, the second player using it would receive the
2nd Choice space and the players who haven’t used their priority option would once again exchange their space for the next
highest number.
Example: Based on card play this turn, Bill has the 1st Choice,
Steve the 2nd, Charlie the 3rd, Ken the 4th, and Debbie the 5th. If
Debbie uses her Priority Turn Option during her investment phase,
she would take the 1st Choice space from Bill, Bill would get the
2nd, Steve the 3rd, Charlie the 4th, and Ken the 5th. If subsequent
to this, Charlie then plays his Priority Turn Option, Debbie would
keep the 1st Choice space, Charlie would get 2nd, Bill 3rd, Steve
4th, and Ken would keep 5th.

9.0 INVESTMENT PHASE
Each player, in turn order, performs an Investment Phase. During the Investment Phase, each player may, in any order they
wish, perform the following actions:
•
•
•
•

Purchase Control Tokens
Purchase a City, a Pioneer and/or a Card (with Circus)
Purchase one or more Progressions
Research Breakthroughs

9.1 Purchase Control Tokens
A player may purchase Control Tokens for $5 per token, up to
the maximum allowed based on their turn order. The maximum
allowed for each player is based on the player’s position in the
turn order. The maximum tokens are as follows:
Maximum Tokens Available
Five
Player
Game

Four
Player
Game

Three
Player
Game

First Player

3

3

3

Second Player

5

5

5

Third Player

7

7

7

Fourth Player

9

7

Fifth Player

7

Free tokens received from Influence Cards or the Turnpike
Breakthrough are not counted against the maximum allowed
to be purchased. A player may also be limited by the number
of tokens not already in use on the map, as Pioneers, or for
claimed Breakthroughs. When a player buys Control Tokens,
place the purchased tokens in the Purchased Token Box on the
Progress Mat.

9.11 Tolerance Progression: The Tolerance Progression allows
a player’s maximum to be increased by 2.

9.2 Purchase a City, Pioneer, and/or Card
9.21 The cost of Cities, Pioneers and Cards is tied to the number
previously purchased that turn. The first of each type costs one
token, the second two tokens, the third three tokens, etc. City,
Pioneer and Card boxes printed on the map are used to keep
track of how many of each has been purchased. As each is bought,
place a token from your purchased tokens into the corresponding City/Pioneer/Card box on the map. Return any additional
tokens needed to buy the City, Pioneer, or Card from your purchased tokens back into stock. At the end of the turn, these tokens are returned to each player. A player may buy one of each
of the items if he wishes to and has enough tokens.
9.211 Mechanization: Each Turn, the Mechanization Breakthrough allows a player to purchase his choice of a City, Pioneer
or Card for one token regardless of its normal cost.
9.22 Cities: A player may acquire one city per turn. Cities are
acquired by purchasing them with tokens or for free through the
Electricity Breakthrough. When a City is acquired, the player
places a City Token in any Territory in which the player has an
Established Presence, provided the Territory does not already
have a city.
9.221 City Attributes: A City increases the product payout for
the Territory (8.331) and provides a Territory with a defensive
advantage (10.245).
9.23 Pioneers: A player may acquire one Pioneer per turn subject to Pioneer limits (9.231). Pioneers are acquired by purchasing them with tokens or for free through Influence Cards. When
a player acquires a Pioneer, the player places a Control Token
from stock on the indicated space on the player’s Progress Mat.
9.231 Pioneer Limits: In Era 1, a player may not own more
than 2 Pioneers; in Era 2, a player may not own more than 3
Pioneers; in Era 3 a player may not own more than 4 Pioneers.
Pioneers who have been used to claim Breakthroughs do not
count against Pioneer limits. Therefore, if a player starts the turn
with their maximum Pioneers and uses one to claim a Breakthrough (9.42), they could then purchase an additional Pioneer
that turn for use on the next turn.
9.232 Pioneer Attributes: Each Pioneer provides one die roll
toward researching a Breakthrough (9.4). When acquired, Pioneers may be used immediately, provided a research roll has not
yet been made during the current player’s turn. Pioneers also are
available for research during each subsequent game turn. Pioneers may research different Breakthroughs on different turns.
9.233 Free Pioneers: Certain Influence Cards grant a player a
free Pioneer. A player is not required to take the free Pioneer. If
a player cannot (due to Pioneer limits) or chooses not to take his
free Pioneer when the Influence Card is played, the free Pioneer
is forfeited.
9.24 Cards: A player may purchase one Influence Card per turn
with purchased tokens provided he owns the Circus Progres-

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

Manifest Destiny
sion. When a player purchases an Influence Card, he immediately draws the next Influence Card in the deck.
9.241 Think Tank Attribute: A player(s) owning the Think Tank
Breakthrough may keep the Influence Card drawn or take the
next Influence Card from the deck (after which the rejected Influence Card is reshuffled into the current deck). If multiple players are receiving Influence Cards at the same time, all players
get their Influence Cards before the Think Tank Attribute is used.
This attribute can be used anytime a player receives an Influence Card.
9.2411 End of Era Use: If a player draws the last Influence
Card in an Era and wants to use the Think Tank Attribute, the
first Influence Card of the next Era is taken and the original
Influence Card is shuffled into the new Era deck.

9.3 Purchase Progressions
Progressions may be purchased for the amount listed on the
Progress Mat, less any credits provided by applicable Influence
Cards. When a player purchases a Progression, the player places
its Progression Deed on the matching space on the player’s
Progress Mat.
9.31 Purchase Restrictions - Categories: Progressions within
a Category (e.g., Transportation, Telecommunications, Government, Leisure, and Culture) must be purchased in order: first
level, then second level, then third level.
9.32 Purchase Restrictions - Levels: Players may not purchase
Level 3 Progressions (three VP Progressions) until after they
have purchased all of the Level 1 Progressions (one VP Progressions).

collaborate with only one player in each game turn and the collaboration must be agreed to during each Game Turn. Unity also
allows collaboration on completing Breakthroughs (9.423). Licensing and Breakthrough collaboration may be used in the same
turn provided the rule of collaborating with only one player in
each Game Turn is adhered to.

9.4 Research Breakthroughs
Breakthroughs are special inventions or characteristics that occurred during the course of history. Players research these in an
effort to discover the Breakthrough. Once discovered, the Breakthrough provides Victory Points and special attributes.
9.41 Conducting Research: A player conducts research by selecting a Breakthrough that has not been previously claimed and
rolling one die for each Pioneer that he owns. A player may only
research one Breakthrough during each Investment Phase. A
player who claims a Breakthrough as a result of an Influence
Card played in the Card Play Phase (8.334), may research another Breakthrough in the Investment Phase.
9.411 Research Limitations: Players may not research level 2
Breakthroughs (two VP Breakthroughs) until the start of Era 2
and may not research level 3 Breakthroughs (three VP Breakthroughs) until the start of Era 3. Players may research the eCommerce Breakthrough before meeting its pre-requisite (owning Computers) but may not claim it until the pre-requisite is
met.
9.412 Research Steps: A player rolling a number that matches
a step of the Breakthrough being researched, places a Break-

9.33 Progression Bonuses: When a player has purchased all
Level 1 Progressions (one VP Progressions), the player’s Profit
increases by +10; when a player has purchased all of the Level 2
Progressions (two VP Progressions), the player’s Profit increases
by +20.
9.34 Progression Victory Points: Purchased Progressions are
worth Victory Points equal to their level (1–3), as indicated on
the Progress Mat. When a Progression is purchased, the purchasing player’s VP Token is increased on the VP Track by the
VPs listed on the Progress Mat.
9.35 Progression Attributes: Each Progression has an associated attribute, which becomes available immediately upon the
purchase of the Progression. The only exception is Unity, whose
attribute is not available until next turn.
9.351 Collaboration (Licensing): Each turn during the Investment Phase, a player owning Unity may collaborate with one
other player who also owns Unity. In order to collaborate, both
players must own Unity before the Investment Phase begins. If
both players who own Unity agree to collaborate, they may share
any combination of played Leader Influence Cards as mutually
agreed. If players share a Leader, the player who wishes to use
the other player’s Leader pays the other player a licensing fee of
one-half of the amount of the credit for each Progression purchased and gets all of the benefits of the Leader. A player may

7

EXAMPLE OF RESEARCH: Both Red and Blue are researching “Think Tank”. Red only needs “3” to complete the Breakthrough, Blue needs 1,3 and 4. Red has two pioneers so is allowed two die rolls. He rolls a 1 and a 6. The “1” has no effect,
but the “6” can be used for any number and so Red uses it for
the “3” and completes the Think Tank Breakthrough. Red receives the Think Tank deed, 2 VPs and removes his four red
Breakthrough tokens from the track for future use. He moves
one of his Pioneers from his Pioneer box to the dashed circle to
indicate he has claimd the Breakthrough. The blue token is returned to Blue.

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

8

Manifest Destiny

through Step Token on the corresponding number on the Breakthrough Chart. A roll of a ‘6’ may become any number the player
wishes. Numbers that are not needed or already rolled are research dead ends and are ignored. Players who have previously
purchased the Innovation Progression may re-roll one research
die per turn. This re-roll occurs before a player decides the
number for a “6” roll.
9.413 Multiple Research Attempts: More than one player may
research the same Breakthrough. A Breakthrough’s research steps
may be completed over more than one turn.
9.414 Breakthrough Step Tokens Limit: Each player is limited
to seven Breakthrough Step Tokens. A player may voluntarily remove a Breakthrough Step Token from an uncompleted Breakthrough. Breakthrough Step Tokens are returned to a player when
someone claims the Breakthrough that the tokens were on.
9.42 Claiming Breakthroughs: The first player to complete all
of a Breakthrough’s required steps (including e-Commerce’s prerequisite) has succeeded in researching the Breakthrough. That
player claims the Breakthrough by placing one of his Pioneers
on the indicated space on the Breakthrough Chart. That Pioneer
may no longer be used for Research (9.41). All players reclaim
their Breakthrough Step Tokens that were used in researching
that Breakthrough. Breakthroughs may only be claimed during
the Investment Phase except for Breakthroughs completed by
the play of an Influence Card (8.334)
9.421 Breakthrough Deeds: The player completing the research
on a Breakthrough receives a Breakthrough Deed corresponding to the Breakthrough claimed and places it next to his Progress
Mat. No other player may claim the Breakthrough. These Deeds
represent Victory Points based on their level (1 VP for level-1, 2
VPs for level-2, 3 VPs for level-3). When the Breakthrough is
claimed, increase the player's VP Token on the VP Chart.
9.422 Breakthrough Attributes: When a Breakthrough is
claimed, all attributes of the Breakthrough are immediately
available.
9.423 Collaboration (Research): Each turn during the Investment Phase, a player owning Unity may collaborate with one
other player who also owns Unity. Both players must own Unity
before the Investment Phase begins to collaborate. In order to
collaborate, the collaborating players, by combining their existing research steps on a Breakthrough, must have completed all
steps of a Breakthrough. The Breakthrough is then claimed by
both of the collaborating players during the Investment Phase of
the earlier moving player. Neither player may make a research
roll that Game Turn. Both players place a Pioneer on the Breakthrough Chart (9.42) and take a Breakthrough Deed (9.421). A
player may collaborate with only one player in each Game Turn
and the collaboration must be agreed to during each Game Turn.
Unity also allows collaboration on licensing Leader Influence
Cards (9.351). Licensing and Research collaboration may be used
in the same turn provided the rule of collaborating with only one
player in each Game Turn is adhered to.

10.0 EXPANSION PHASE
Players move in turn order during the Expansion Phase and may
use any remaining tokens they purchased during the Investment
Phase to maximize their territorial empire.

10.1 Placing Tokens
Players may place Control Tokens in any Territory adjacent by
land to a Territory in which they have an Established Presence
(10.23) or from their Home Territory. Territories that are connected at one of its corners, including the four-corner space, are
considered adjacent. Once Control Tokens are placed on the board
they cannot be voluntarily removed unless the Wireless Progression is purchased (10.19).
10.11 Westward Ho Limitations: Players may not place Control Tokens in or through territories in the Northwest or Southwest until they have purchased the Westward Ho Progression.
10.12 Eastern and Western South America: Eastern and Western South America are considered adjacent. Western South
America is on the Pacific Coast and Eastern South America is
on the Atlantic Coast.
10.13 Telegraph Attribute: Players who have purchased the Telegraph Progression may expand through
an adjacent Territory to an adjoining Territory provided the adjacent Territory is not an Established Presence of another player. A player may not use Telegraph to expand through a Territory containing Natives or across water.
10.14 Railroads Attribute: Players who have
purchased the Railroads Progression may place
Control Tokens in any territory within a Region
in which the player has an Established Presence as long as placement does not take place across water. A player may use Railroads to expand beyond Territories controlled by Natives or other
players.
10.15 Steamships Attribute: Players who have
purchased the Steamships Progression may place
Control Tokens in any territory on the same coast
as an Established Presence of that player. The Atlantic coast includes the Gulf of Mexico. Central
America and Oaxaca border both coasts. Hawaii, Eastern South
America, and Western South America can only be reached via
Steamships. Alaska and Cuba can only be reached via Steamships or Ferry (10.17).
NOTE: Alaska connects to British Columbia, not Washington.
Quebec is on the Atlantic coast.
PANAMA CANAL: Once the Panama Canal event has been
played, all coastal Territories are considered on the same coast
for Steamships. Upon the play of this event, place a black token
on the Panama Canal space between Yucatan, Oaxaca, Central
America border to indicate that the Panama Canal is now open.

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

10.16 Airplanes Attribute: Players who have purchased the Airplanes Progression may place Control Tokens in any Territories other than Foreign
Markets and in up to three Foreign Market Territories.

Manifest Destiny

9

10.161 Foreign Market Restrictions: In order to place Control
Tokens in a Foreign Market Territory using Airplanes, the player
must meet one of the following pre-requisites:

take control (attacker) must place Control Tokens equal to the
Territory’s Control Number in the Territory and win a competition die roll.

• have an Established Presence with a City located on the shore
of the same ocean, Atlantic (including the Gulf of Mexico) or
Pacific, as the Foreign Market Territory, or

10.241 Competition Die Rolls: To win a competition die roll,
the attacker rolls two dice and the defender rolls one die. The
high roll on any die wins. The defender wins ties unless an Influence Card states otherwise (10.242) or the attacker has Television (10.243). The loser of the Competition Die Roll must remove his control tokens from the Territory. If the loser’s Control
Tokens were established they are placed in the Loss Box (10.26).
New Presences lost are returned to their owner.

• have a City in another Foreign Market.
10.17 Ferry: Any Territory connected by a white dashed line is
automatically adjacent by Ferry. Players may not use the Telegraph or Railroads attribute in connection with a Ferry.
10.18 e-Commerce Attribute: The player(s) who owns the eCommerce Breakthrough may place Control Tokens in any Territory on the board (including Foreign Markets).
10.19 Wireless Attribute: A player who purchases the Wireless
Progression may, on the turn the player acquires the Wireless
Progression, remove up to five of the player’s Control Tokens
from any territory on the board (subject to the Turn Order maximum), without cost or loss of Profit, and re-allocate them to
purchase a Pioneer, purchase a City, purchase a Card with Circus, or place them in the player’s Purchased Tokens box for use
anywhere on the board (including Foreign Markets) during the
player’s next Expansion Phase.

10.2 Controlling a Territory

10.242 Card Adjustments: Certain event cards may modify or
affect the die rolls.
10.243 Television Attribute: A player who has purchased the Television Progression wins all ties when
attacking.
10.244 Telephone Attribute: A player who has purchased the
Telephone Progression rolls three dice when attacking.
10.245 City Defense Adjustments: If the Established Presence
Territory has a City in it, the player attempting to take control
must spend 1 additional Control Token to make the attempt. In
addition, the defender gets an extra die roll. If the Territory containing the City is defeated, the City remains in the Territory.

Each Territory can be controlled by spending Control Tokens.
These Control Tokens must come from the player’s Purchased
Token Box on his Progress Mat.
10.21 Controlling a Vacant Territory: Each vacant Territory
can be controlled by spending Control Tokens equal to the
Territory’s Control Number (Control Numbers vary between 1
and 3). Partial control, for example placing one token in a ‘2’
territory, is not allowed.

10.246 Pro Sports Attribute: A player who has
purchased the Pro Sports Progression may attack
Territories containing Cities with 1 less token than
is normally required.
10.247 Home Territory Adjustments: A player rolls an extra
die if attacking or defending in that player’s Home Territory.

10.22 New Presence: When a player takes control of a Territory, place one Control Token in the Territory and return the remaining Control Tokens used (if any) to stock. Indicate that the
control is a New Presence by placing the Control Token with its
white side face up.
NOTE: Alternatively, if players do not wish to use the stickers they
can indicate a New Presence by placing their Control Token on the
Control Number box printed in the territory, and then moving it off
the box when it becomes established.

10.23 Established Presence: A New Presence still in place at
the end of the Adjustments Phase becomes an Established Presence. Indicate an Established Presence by flipping the Control
Token over. A player must have an Established Presence in order to collect payouts from and expand from a Territory. Established Presence Territories do not increase a player’s Profit
(11.11), nor count as Territories taken when determining the
Expansion Bonus Card recipient.
10.24 Controlling an Established Presence Territory: To take
control of a Territory in which there is an Established Presence
of another player or Natives (8.322), the player attempting to

EXAMPLE OF COMPETITION DIE ROLLS: Yellow has an
established presence in both Utah and Colorado. Red wishes
to take control of both Territories. Red first places one token in
Utah (the required amount) and declares a Competition Die
Roll. Yellow rolls a 4, and Red rolls a 1 and a 5—Red wins and
the Yellow token is removed. Next Red attacks Colorado which
requires two tokens. Both players roll their Competition Die
Rolls. Yellow rolls a 3 and Red rolls a 2 and a 3. Defender
wins ties, so Yellow wins and Red removes his two tokens from
Colorado.

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

10

Manifest Destiny

10.248 Rock ‘n Roll Attribute: The player(s) who owns the
Rock n’ Roll Breakthrough may re-roll their first competition
roll for each Territory attacked.
10.25 Multiple Competitions: The attacker may compete in a
Territory as many times as the player’s supply of Control Tokens in the Purchased Tokens Box allows.
10.26 Loss Box: An Established Presence that is removed from
the board, for whatever reason (including as a result of card play)
is placed in the Loss Box. New Presences lost are returned to
their owner. Tokens in the Loss Box are returned to players at
the end of the turn.
10.27 Expansion Bonus Card: The player with the most New
Presences at the end of the last player’s Expansion Phase draws
an Influence Card from the deck. If there is a tie for most New
Presences, the player who moved first during the turn receives
the Influence Card.

11.5 Urban Renaissance Attribute
The player(s) owning the Urban Renaissance Breakthrough receives $10 for each City that they control through an Established
Presence in the Territory (10.23). If Cold War has been played
that turn, the player with Urban Renaissance does not receive a
payment from a city in any affected Foreign Market.

11.6 Motion Pictures Attribute
The player(s) owning the Motion Pictures Breakthrough receives
$5 from each non-owner. Players who have previously purchased
the Television Progression are immune and do not have to make
the payment.

11.7 Return Tokens
Return all tokens in the Turn Order Track, Loss Box (10.26,
11.12) and in the City, Pioneer and Card Boxes (9.21) to their
owners.

11.8 Draw a Card
In turn order, each player draws an Influence Card from the deck.
After the Adjustment Phase, the turn is over and a new turn begins,
starting with a new Turn Order Phase (7.0).

11.0 ADJUSTMENTS
11.1 End of Phase Profit Adjustment
Once all players have expanded, each player’s Profit Token is
adjusted for New Presences (10.22) and Control Tokens in the
Loss Box (10.26).

12.0 Game Etiquette
12.1 Showing of Cards

11.11 Profit for New Presences: Each player’s Profit is adjusted
by +1 space ($5) for each New Presence he has on the board.

Players may not show their Influence Cards to other players.

11.111 Computers Attribute: If a player has purchased the Computers Progression, his Profit is adjusted by +2 spaces ($10) for
each New Presence he has on the board.

12.21 Hidden Money: Money may be kept secret, but must stay
on the table. The only time money must be revealed is when an
Influence Card is played that has an effect based on a player’s
cash on hand. If such an Influence Card is played, all players
must reveal their cash on hand.

11.12 Control Tokens in the Loss Box: Each player’s Profit is
adjusted by –1 space ($5) for each Control Token he has in the
Loss Box. Once a player’s Profit has been adjusted for the tokens in the Loss Box, the tokens are returned to the player’s
stock for future use.
11.13 Minimum Profit: All players have a minimum Profit of
$20. Do not move any player’s Profit Token below the $20 level.
11.14 Profit over $100: If a player’s Profit exceeds $100, place
a +100 Profit token under the player’s Profit token.

11.2 Changing Control Tokens to Established
Presence
All New Presences now become Established Presences (10.23).

11.3 End of Phase Profits
Following the adjustment of the players’ Profit Tokens, each
player is paid cash equal to the player’s Profit.

11.4 Safety Net Attribute
A player who has purchased the Safety Net Progression collects
his Safety Net payment based on his Profit position (i.e. the player
with the lowest income receives the largest amount). If there is a
tie in Profit, all players tied qualify for the higher payout provided they own Safety Net.

12.2 Money:

12.22 Fractions: Fractions are rounded off to a player’s detriment.

13.0 END OF GAME
The game ends:
• At the end of the current Investment Phase (if the last Influence Card is drawn during the Investment Phase) or the next
Investment Phase (if the last Influence Card is drawn during
any other phase) once the last Card is drawn or
• At the end of the current Investment Phase when a player
reaches at least 30 Victory Points or
• At the end of the current Expansion Phase when a player
reaches at least 30 Victory Points.
Cards remaining in players’ hands do not get played.
The player with the most Victory Points at the end of the Game
wins. If there is a tie, whichever tied player has the most Cash
wins. If still tied, the player with the Highest Profit wins.

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

Manifest Destiny

11

Description of Tokens
Use one of the white
tokens to indicate current
Era. The remaining four
white blocks are extras.

Use one of the black
tokens to indicate the
Panama Canal has been
built. Place it aside at start
of game (10.15).

Use the five dark-red
tokens and the five Native
stickers to indicate Native
presence. Place these aside
at start of game (8.322).

Use one of the black tokens
to indicate a Surplus in all
products. Place in the
Surplus All box when this
occurs (8.3311).

Natives

Dark-Red Blocks

Black Block

x5

x1

x5

x1

Use the five light-blue
blocks to indicate +100 on
the Profit Track (stack the
player's Profit Token on
top of the block).

Use the three orange
blocks and the three
Tourist stickers to add
Tourist product to a
territory. Place these aside
at start of game (8.321).

Use the two brown blocks
and the two Technology
stickers to indicate
Technology has been added
to a territory. Place these
aside at start of game (8.321).

Use the light-green block
and the 2 VP sticker to
represent 2 Victory Points
for owning the most Cities.
The player awarded these
points places the block on
his Progress Mat.

Light-Blue Blocks

Orange Blocks

Brown Blocks

Light-Green Block

x5

x3

x2

x1

Ps

V

Black Block

2

White Blocks

Half Inch Cylinders

Use the 20 gray tokens to
signify a city.
Five (one of each
player color) are used
on the VP Track.

Five (one of each
player color) are used
on the Profit Track.

Five (one of each
player color) are used
on the Current Turn
Order Track.

x5

x5

x5

Gray Blocks

x20
Each player gets 25 small blocks in his player
color. These tokens are used for controlling
territories on the map, tracking Pioneers,
tracking Breakthroughs, and purchasing
Cities, Pioneers, and Cards. Place a sticker on
one side of each token to facilitate showing a
New Presence (10.22).

1/4 inch Blocks

x125

Place a G sticker on the
green blocks, a B sticker
on the blue blocks, a Y
sticker on the yellow
blocks, etc.

Each player uses seven
of the tokens in his
player color to track
research steps achieved
in Breakthroughs
(9.412).

Five (one of each
player color) are used
to track the Turn Order
Choice for the next
turn (8.62).

Five (one of each
player color) are
spares.

x35

x5

x5

© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

Manifest Destiny

12

# of Territories
Resource

1

2

3

4

5

6

Produce

5

10

15

20

30

40

Livestock

5

10

20

30

40

50

Timber

5

10

20

30

45

60

Grain

10

20

30

40

60

80

Textiles

10

20

40

60

80

100

Ore

10

25

50

75

100

125

Fur

10

30

60

90

120

-

Tobacco

10

30

60

90

120

-

Oil

10

30

60

90

120

150

Gold

20

40

70

100

150

200

Technology

20

40

70

100

150

200

Tourist

20

40

70

100

150

200

GMT Games, LLC
P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308
www.GMTGames.com
© 2004 GMT Games, LLC

</rulebook>
			
						                           
						               													<description>Manifest Destiny is a card-driven multi-player strategy game for 3 to 5 players set in North America from colonial times to the present. Designed by Bill Crenshaw as the successor to the Age of Renaissance, and developed by Ken Gutermuth, Manifest Destiny combines the strategic components of earlier, longer civilization-based games with the elegance of streamlined European gaming. While reminiscent of its predecessors in some respects, it is significantly simpler and quicker to play. Designed to appeal to a wide range of gamers, Manifest Destiny combines several unique elements that require strategic balancing to succeed.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Each player controls a mercantile empire as it expands into territories containing new markets across the continent. Players use cash to purchase Progressions and tokens. Progressions give players additional capabilities during the game. Tokens are used for territorial expansion and to purchase Pioneers, cities and additional cards.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Each game is unique, with no standard path to victory. The game has several elements that keep all players competitive; cards and Progressions are designed to assist lagging players. How you balance the competing opportunities will determine whether you achieve your destiny.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2005" />
						               				<minplayers value="3" />
						               				<maxplayers value="5" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="17">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="10" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="9" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="9" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="2" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="8" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="5">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="9" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="5+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="9" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="180" />
						               				<minplaytime value="180" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="180" />
						               				<minage value="12" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="4">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="7">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="7" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1015" value="Civilization" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1021" value="Economic" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1001" value="Political" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2018" value="Campaign / Battle Card Driven" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2013" value="Commodity Speculation" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2015" value="Variable Player Powers" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="22783" value="Admin: Better Description Needed!" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="14835" value="Country: USA" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="3618" value="Bill Crenshaw" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="43278" value="John Gast" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="71" value="Rodger B. MacGowan" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="140" value="Mark Simonitch" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="52" value="GMT Games" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="582" />
			<average value="6.49263" />
			<bayesaverage value="5.74313" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="4549" bayesaverage="5.74313" />
																				<rank type="family" id="5497" name="strategygames" friendlyname="Strategy Game Rank" value="1626" bayesaverage="5.82018" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.60489" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="915" />
			<trading value="79" />
			<wanting value="23" />
			<wishing value="87" />
			<numcomments value="280" />
			<numweights value="83" />
			<averageweight value="3.1928" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>