<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="199561">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/PZt3EAAGV3dFIVuwMR0AEw__thumb/img/1m4aryOW1MOpq-8jGkF6gDTJmCY=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic3525224.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/PZt3EAAGV3dFIVuwMR0AEw__original/img/5ug9EeKlH_ucJEUXaFpTZbBJ1GY=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic3525224.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Sagrada" />
			
						                               				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Саграда" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Саґрада" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="ซากราดา" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="サグラダ" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="聖家族大教堂 SAGRADA" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="사그라다" />
				<rulebook>Eglomise Brush
2

ra S

ro
Au

dis

agra

Luz Celestial
Frac

tal Dr
ops

12 Wind ow
Patte rn Card s

90 Dice
(18 x 5 Colors – red, yellow,
green, blue, purple)

Move any one die in your window
ignoring color restrictions
You must obey all other
placement restrictions

12 Tool Card s

2

Dice Bag

4 Window Frame
Player Boards

Light

Sets of
1

Shades

& 2 va

lues an
ywhere

1
Obje 0 Publi
ctive c
C a rd
s

24 Favor Tokens
1-4
Players

30 - 45
Minutes

#

4 Score Markers

Age 13+

You are an artist competing with fellow artists to
create the most beautiful stained glass window
in the Sagrada Familia. Your glass pieces are
represented by dice, which have a color and a
shade - indicated by the values on the dice (the
lower the value the lighter the shade).

Green •	Privat
e

Sum of valu

es on green

dice

5 P ri v a
O b je c ti v e te
C a rd s

STOP!

Round Track (front)
Score Track (back)

Overview

Shades of

We’ll teach you how to play! Visit

FloodgateGames.com/Sagrada
and watch a video explanation.

Each round, players will take turns drafting from
a pool of dice, placing these dice on their window.
Players must place them within the color and
shade restrictions on their Window card, and never
have adjacent dice of the same color or value.
After 10 rounds, players score points based on
public and private objectives — the highest scoring
artisan is the winner!

Credits
GAME DESIGNERS
Daryl Andrews (@darylmandrews)
Adrian Adamescu (@Aadrian131)
GAME DEVELOPMENT
Ben Harkins (@BenHarkins)

PLAYTESTING Nikhil Katarya, Andreea Adamescu, Tyler Anderson, Tanya Andrews,
Gina Angelea, Rob Baksh, Chris Bell, Steve Caires, Jen Farmer, Jon Gilmour, David
Leung, Stephen Sauer, Emily Tinawi, Nate Anderson, Brian Schrier, Evan Pedersen,
Josh Slivken, Michael Guigliano, Dan Marta, Samuel Bailey,
Curtis Clark, Kelsy Clark, Karl Liggin, Raul Taveras, Jax
Sperling, Benny Sperling, and the Game Artisans of Canada

GRAPHIC DESIGN & ILLUSTRATION
Peter Wocken Design LLC (@PeterWocken)

EDITING Emily Tinawi, Simon Rourke, David Castillo

PUBLISHED BY
Floodgate Games (@FloodgateGames)

www .F loodgate G ames . com

Special Thanks to all of our Kickstarter Backers!
Second Printing

Player Setup

Game Setup

1•	 Shuffle the Private Objective Cards (Gray die

on the back) and give 1 to each player face down.
Players may secretly look at this card.
2•	 Give each player 2 random Window Pattern
Cards and 1 Window Frame Player Board.
Each player selects 1 of the 4 Window Patterns to
play (front or back), the other card isn’t used.
Note: Windows have varying difficulty from level 3
(easiest) to 6 (hardest) as indicated near the name.
Difficult windows give more Favor Tokens
3•	 Give each player the number of Favor Tokens
indicated by the difficulty number on their card.
4•	 Slide the selected Window Pattern Card into the
bottom of the Player Board.
5•	 Place a Score Marker that matches the color of
each player’s board next to the Round Track,
these are used during End Game Scoring.

A•	 Place the Round Track near the center of the

play area.
B•	 Shuffle all of the Tool Cards and place 3 face up
in the center of the play area.
C•	 Shuffle all of the Public Objective cards (Blue
die on the back) and place 3 face up.
D•	 Place all 90 dice in the Dice Bag.
E•	 Randomly select a player to be the Start Player
and give them the Dice Bag. One suggested method
is whoever most recently visited a cathedral.
Set aside all remaining Objective, Tool and Window
Cards, they are not used during the game

Note: Setup is the same for 2, 3 or 4 players

A

5
2

Eglomise Brush
2

Grozing Pliers
1

Lathekin
4

B
Move any one die in your window
ignoring color restrictions
You must obey all other
placement restrictions

After drafting,
increase or decrease the value
of the drafted die by 1

Move exactly two dice, obeying
all placement restrictions

1 may not change to 6, or 6 to 1

Note: This symbol is only used in Solo Play

C
5

Column Color Variety
Columns with no
repeated colors

2

Light Shades
Sets of 1 & 2 values anywhere

4

D
Victory Point (VP) value for
each complete set of this type

1
4

Luz Celestial

E
3

Color Variety
Sets of one of each
color anywhere

Gameplay

Placing Dice

Each game of Sagrada is played over 10 rounds.

When placing a die on a Window:

Each round, the Start Player (the player with the
Dice Bag) pulls dice out of the Dice Bag at random
and rolls them. The number of dice pulled depends
on the number of players:
2 Players - 5 Dice
3 Players - 7 Dice
4 Players - 9 Dice
2 per player, plus 1 additional die
Once rolled, these dice form the Draft Pool.

• First die: Each player’s first die of the game must be
placed on an edge or corner space
• Every other die must be adjacent to a previously
placed die, touching diagonally (different row and
column) or orthogonally (same row or column)
• The die must match the color or value restriction
of the space. White spaces have no restrictions
Example - A red space on the window may only be
filled by a red die (any value). A space showing a 3
may only be filled by a die showing a 3 (any color)
• Dice may never be placed orthogonally adjacent to
a die of the same color or the same value. Example
- Two red dice or two dice showing a 3 may not be
placed side by side
Players may choose not to draft a die during their turn.

Beginning with the Start Player, each player takes a
turn in clockwise order. On a player’s turn, they may
perform each of the following actions in any order:
• Select 1 die from the Draft Pool and place it in
an open space on their Window
• Use 1 Tool Card by spending Favor Tokens
Each action is optional — A player may choose to
perform both actions, only one action or pass their
turn taking no actions.
Turns proceed clockwise with each player taking
a turn or passing. Example - Emily takes a turn (1),
then Ben (2), then Mari (3)
Ben

5

Note: Any die may be placed on a white space as
long as all the above restrictions are obeyed

Example: This Red 2 die has
three spaces that meet all
placement restrictions
Fractal Drops

2
6

1
Emily

3

4
Mari

(Start Player)

Once the last player has completed their first turn,
the round continues in reverse order (counterclockwise). Beginning with the last player,
each player takes a second turn (selecting a second
die from the Draft Pool, etc.) Example - Mari takes
her second turn (4), then Ben (5), then Emily (6)
Once the Start Player has taken their second turn,
proceed to the End of the Round.

Tip: Being the first to use each Tool Card costs
the fewest Favor Tokens. However, Tool Card
abilities become more useful later in the game
as player’s Windows fill with dice.

Tip: Try to avoid placing dice next to a matching space
(such as a 2 die next to a 2 space or red die next to a red
space) so a future die can still be placed in that space

Tool Cards & Favor Tokens
Players may spend Favor Tokens to gain a special
ability from 1 Tool Card during their turn:
1. Place Favor Tokens on the Tool Card — 1 if
there aren’t any tokens on the card, otherwise
place 2.
2. Use the ability listed on the Tool Card
Players may choose not to use a Tool Card on
their turn.
Grozing Pliers
1

After drafting
increase or decrease ,
the value
of the drafted die
by 1
1 may not change
to 6, or 6 to 1

Fractal Drops

End of the Round

Scoring Example

If this was the end of the 10th round, it is the end of
the game — proceed to End Game Scoring.

1
2
3
4
5
This example uses the Public
Objectives shown in G ame S etup and
A
this final Window.
Public Objectives
B
Column Color Variety: 5 VP from
each of column 4 and 5, 10 VP total. C
0 points for column 1 and 3 since
they’re incomplete, 0 VP from column
2 since there’s a repeated green die. D
Fractal Drops
Light Shades: 2 VP for each set of
1-value & 2-value dice (1’s at B2, B4. 2’s at A3, D4, B5). 4 VP total
for two pairs, the third 2-value die is not part of a pair and is not
counted.
Color Variety: Three sets of 1 of each color give 4 VP each, 12 VP
total.
T ip : The number of Sets of a type will always be the count of dice
with the fewest quantity of that type
Private Objective: Shades of Purple would sum the values for
purple dice (C1, C4, and A5), giving 5 + 6 + 6 = 17 VP total.
Favor Token: 1 VP for each remaining. None remain so 0 VP.
Open Spaces: -1 VP for each open space (A1, B3, and C3), -3 VP total.
Total: 10 VP + 4 VP + 12 VP + 17 VP + 0 VP - 3 VP = 40 VP Total!

End Game Scoring

Dice Placement Mistakes

All remaining dice are placed on the Round
Track, covering the number space for the just
completed round. If multiple dice remain (due
to players skipping a draft action) these do not
cover additional number spaces.

The Dice Bag is passed clockwise to the next
player. This player is now the Start Player —
players then begin another round. Example - Ben is
now the start player for the second round

The game ends at the end of the 10th round.
1. Clear the dice off the Round Track and flip it
over to the Score Track side.
2. Use each player’s Score Marker to track their
position on the Score Track, flipping the marker if
they exceed 50 points.

If a Player’s Window is ever found to break any of the placement
restrictions, that player must immediately remove dice (of their
choice) from their Window until all restrictions are obeyed. These
dice are out of play and any resulting open spaces will count
against their score as normal.

Solo Play Rules
When playing Sagrada by yourself, you’re trying to beat a Target
Score. The Target Score is the sum of the values from all the dice
on the Round Track at the end of the game.

Setup

Each player tallies their Victory Point total, gaining
points from:
• Each Public Objective Card - Players may
gain points from each card multiple times.
Row/Column-based objectives only score for
completed Rows/Columns (no open spaces).
• Their Private Objective Card - Summing the
values of their dice of the specified color.
• Favor Tokens - 1 Victory Point for each
unspent token.
• Players Lose 1 Victory Point for each open
space on their window.
The player with the highest Victory Point
total is the winner. Ties are broken by most
points from Private Objectives, most remaining
Favor Tokens, then finally by reverse player
order in the final round.

Each game is set up as normal with a few small changes:
• Favor Tokens are not used.
• 2 Public Objectives and 2 Private Objective are placed face up.
• Place Tool Cards based on the level of difficulty you wish to play,
between 1 Tool (Extreme Challenge) and 5 Tools (Easy).

Gameplay

Each game is played as normal in 10 rounds, with a few small changes:
• Each round, pull 4 dice from the Dice Bag and roll them.
• Take 2 turns, choosing to draft and place a die (as normal) and/or use
a Tool Card, or pass.

Tool Cards

Eglomise Brush

2
Tool Cards may be used only once by spending
dice from the Draft Pool. To use a Tool Card place a
die from the Draft Pool that matches the color shown on the top-left
of the Tool Card.
Note: Each Tool Card may only be used once. Both the die spent
and the Tool Card are now removed from play.

End of the Round

Move any one die in your window
ignoring color restrictions

You must obey taking
all other
All remaining dice are placed on the Round Track as normal,
placement restrictions
care to not change the value of any dice. If no dice remain, use a
Score Marker as a placeholder.

End Game Scoring

The game ends after the end of 10th round. Before flipping the Round
Track, add up the Target Score.
• The Target Score is the sum of the values from all the dice on the
Round Track. Dice used to pay for Tool Cards are not counted.
• Tally your Victory Point total as normal (selecting only one of the
two Private Objectives), however, you lose 3 Victory Points for
each open space.
• If your Victory Point total is greater than the Target Score, you win!

</rulebook>
			
						               													<description>Draft dice and use the tools-of-the-trade in Sagrada to carefully construct your stained glass window masterpiece.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;In more detail, each player builds a stained glass window by building up a grid of dice on their player board. Each board has some restrictions on which color or shade (value) of die can be placed there. Dice of the same shade or color may never be placed next to each other. Dice are drafted in player order, with the start player rotating each round, snaking back around after the last player drafts two dice. Scoring is variable per game based on achieving various patterns and varieties of placement...as well as bonus points for dark shades of a particular hidden goal color.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Special tools can be used to help you break the rules by spending skill tokens; once a tool is used, it then requires more skill tokens for the other players to use them.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The highest scoring window artisan wins!&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2017" />
						               				<minplayers value="1" />
						               				<maxplayers value="4" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="393">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="14" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="127" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="111" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="181" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="146" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="14" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="121" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="188" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="5" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="100" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="194" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="28" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="5" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="20" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="154" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="45" />
						               				<minplaytime value="30" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="45" />
						               				<minage value="14" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="116">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="9" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="48" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="46" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="5" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="34">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="3" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="28" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="3" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1017" value="Dice" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1028" value="Puzzle" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2912" value="Contracts" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2072" value="Dice Rolling" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2875" value="End Game Bonuses" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2978" value="Grid Coverage" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2041" value="Open Drafting" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2048" value="Pattern Building" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2004" value="Set Collection" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2819" value="Solo / Solitaire Game" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2828" value="Turn Order: Progressive" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2897" value="Variable Set-up" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="18639" value="Cities: Barcelona (Spain)" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="8374" value="Crowdfunding: Kickstarter" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="50196" value="Game: Sagrada" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="65163" value="Mechanism: Dice Drafting" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="4705" value="Organizations: The Game Artisans of Canada" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="5666" value="Players: Games with Solitaire Rules" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="56419" value="Theme: Art" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="75454" value="Theme: Art style – Art Nouveau" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="253493" value="RiaCon Window Pattern Card (fan expansion for Sagrada)" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="309707" value="Sagrada: 2020 Promo Pack" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="244262" value="Sagrada: 5-6 Player Expansion" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="286275" value="Sagrada: Horizontal Symmetry" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="225269" value="Sagrada: Promo 1 – Vitraux/Balboa Bay Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="309221" value="Sagrada: Promo 10 – Dice Tower 2020 Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="329601" value="Sagrada: Promo 11 – FLGS 2020 Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="310565" value="Sagrada: Promo 12 – Tantrum House Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="348593" value="Sagrada: Promo 14 – Game Boy Geek 2021 Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="351368" value="Sagrada: Promo 16 – CuseCon 2021 Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="346200" value="Sagrada: Promo 17 – Gathering of Friends 2021 Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="233638" value="Sagrada: Promo 2 – Alpenglow/Komorebi Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="252099" value="Sagrada: Promo 3 – International Tabletop Day Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="236940" value="Sagrada: Promo 4 – BoardGameGeek Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="270329" value="Sagrada: Promo 5 – Watch It Played Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="250293" value="Sagrada: Promo 6 – Man Vs Meeple Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="250292" value="Sagrada: Promo 7 – Game Boy Geek Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="347022" value="Sagrada: Promo 8 – Apollo/Godfather Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="329515" value="Sagrada: Promo 9 – Man Vs Meeple Window Pattern Card" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="359142" value="Sagrada: The Great Facades – Glory" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="301561" value="Sagrada: The Great Facades – Life" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="263695" value="Sagrada: The Great Facades – Passion" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="88370" value="Adrian Adamescu" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="67502" value="Daryl Andrews" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="39902" value="Peter Wocken" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="21756" value="Floodgate Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="10768" value="Cranio Creations" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="34522" value="CrowD Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="2366" value="Devir" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="39390" value="Engames" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="26380" value="FoxGames" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="15605" value="Galápagos Jogos" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="45134" value="Geekach Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="36210" value="Lanlalen" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="25203" value="Lex Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30521" value="Mandoo Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="5400" value="Matagot" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="38392" value="MEBO Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="7992" value="MINDOK" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30552" value="One Moment Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="39" value="Pegasus Spiele" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="36563" value="Reflexshop" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="32251" />
			<average value="7.50846" />
			<bayesaverage value="7.36068" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="169" bayesaverage="7.36068" />
																				<rank type="family" id="4666" name="abstracts" friendlyname="Abstract Game Rank" value="10" bayesaverage="7.31666" />
											<rank type="family" id="5499" name="familygames" friendlyname="Family Game Rank" value="30" bayesaverage="7.38137" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.15588" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="50900" />
			<trading value="455" />
			<wanting value="854" />
			<wishing value="6689" />
			<numcomments value="4489" />
			<numweights value="666" />
			<averageweight value="1.9234" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>