<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="166384">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/Ehx72XRdSeQHISVXcZVnHg__thumb/img/sPJVWjzGcEpiseZGdoD6HNR9nRI=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic2453926.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/Ehx72XRdSeQHISVXcZVnHg__original/img/bI3PgKtvAGiD59QYya-pqasF_tk=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic2453926.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Spyfall" />
			
						                               				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Agent Trouble" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Agent Undercover" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="El Espía (que se perdió)" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Mamy Szpiega!" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Superšpión" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Κατάσκοπος" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Знахідка для шпигуна" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Находка для шпиона" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="スパイフォール" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="스파이폴" />
				<rulebook>Rulebook

“Loose lips sink ships” is a saying that dates back to the days of WWII. It also represents
a vital wartime principle. There were lots of things that could give spies away — rust-free staples
in their documents, square-headed nails in the soles of their boots, and so on... This game offers
everyone an opportunity to walk a mile in the shoes of both a spy who’s close to having their
cover blown and the special agent who’s hot on the spy’s heels.

Contents
•	 240 cards (30 decks of 8 cards each)
•	 30 ziplock bags
•	 Rulebook
You will also need to keep track of time during
the game, so make sure you have a stopwatch
handy. One of the players probably has one on
their cell phone.

Overview
A game of Spyfall is made up of several short
rounds. In each round the players find themselves
in a certain location with a specific role assigned
to each player. One player is always a spy who
doesn’t know where they are. The spy’s mission is
to listen carefully, identify the location, and keep
from blowing his cover. Each non-spy must give an
oblique hint to the other non-spies sugges-ting that
he knows the location’s identity, thus proving he’s not
the spy. Observation, concentration, nonchalance,
and cunning — you’ll need all of them in this game.
Stay on your toes!

Objective
The spy’s objective is to avoid exposure until the
end of a given round or identify the current location.
The non-spies’ objective is to establish consensus
on the identity of the spy and expose him or her.

Preparing for Round One
Before the first round begins, sort all the cards
into location decks. Each deck should have seven
cards with identical illustrations and one spy card.
Each deck goes in a separate ziplock bag. All cards
should be face down, with the spy card on top.
All the locations are shown in the middle spread
of the rulebook. The players are advised to study it
well before the first round begins. This should give
the “potential spies” an idea of the kinds of locations
they will have to choose from during the game. We
strongly advise the spies not to study the middle
spread during the game — that’s a dead giveaway.

Beginning of the Round
Each game is a series of short rounds, the number
of which is agreed upon by the the players before
the beginning of the game. We recommend playing
five rounds for your first session (this should take
about an hour).
A new dealer is chosen for each round. The dealer
participates in the game as a regular player. The
most suspicious-looking player is the dealer in the
first round. This player takes all the card ziplock
bags out of the box, turns them face down, shuffles
them, and chooses a random ziplock bag. The dealer
then removes the cards from the selected ziplock
bag very carefully to avoid turning them over.

Location Card
Corporate Party

Location

Game Flow

Role
Manager

Spy Card

The dealer selects a number of cards that corresponds to the number of players from the top of the
stack, shuffles them, and gives a card to each player.
If there are five players, five cards are played. The
remaining cards are not turned over. Put them aside
carefully — you won’t be needing them. Each player
looks at their card without letting the others see it,
then places it face down in front of them.
The dealer for each successive round is the
player who was the spy in the previous one. That
player selects a new deck and deals the cards as
described above.

The dealer starts the stopwatch, and the game
begins. The dealer then asks one of the players a
question, calling them by name: “Tell me, John...” The
questions usually pertain to the current location. This
is prudent, but not mandatory. Questions are asked
once; no follow-up questions are allowed. Responses
can take any form. The player who answers the
question proceeds to ask any other player a question
of their own, but cannot ask a question of the player
who just asked them a question. The order in which
the questions are asked is established by the players
themselves and based on the suspicions they have
after hearing the questions and answers.

Note: If you are not the spy, your card will also
specify your role at the given location. Before the
beginning of the game, the players should agree on
whether they will adhere to the role on their card and
play the corresponding role or not. We strongly
recommend doing this in order to make the game more
interesting, but not for your first few game sessions.
For example, if you’re a college professor and
somebody asks you why you missed the faculty party,
you can complain about your age and arthritis; if you’re
a student, you might want to express your outrage at
not having been invited by the senior faculty.
The name of the role might seem to suggest that
you’re playing a male character, but all characters
can actually be either male or female. So the flight
attendant on the airplane could also be a stewardess, or the actor could also be an actress.

Sample Round
Anne, Juan, Maria, and Isaac find themselves in the
crusader army. However, Anne isn’t aware of this
because she got the spy card. Juan gets the Knight,
Maria the Squire, and Isaac the Archer. They all play
their parts and try to identify the spy. Anne’s goal is
to identify the location without blowing her cover.

Maria the Squire asks the first question: “Isaac, do
you remember which sea we took a dip in yesterday?“
Isaac the Archer naturally names the Mediterranean,
and Anne the spy takes notice: the location could be
the beach or the pirate ship. Isaac can’t ask Maria,
so he asks Juan, “Juan, when do we get paid — is it
at the beginning of the month, or the end?“ All the
other players are on the alert, since the question
might identify Isaac as the spy. However, Isaac is
just sounding out his fellow players. Since Juan is
a knight and not a spy, he answers the question
easily: “Who knows? We’ll get paid whenever the
commander feels like paying us.“ Anna the spy is
thoroughly confused — now she suspects the location
might be the military base or the submarine. Juan
asks her next question: “Hey Anne, what did they
serve for dinner yesterday? I couldn’t make it.“ Anne
is evasive: “Oh, you know, the usual stuff — potatoes,
nothing special.“ This is where other players start
to suspect her of being the spy — as crusaders,
they’re well aware that Columbus won’t be bringing
that particular plant back from the New World for
another three hundred years or so...

End of Round
Note: The players can agree on a different round
length. Make sure you decide how long you want
rounds to be before you start the game. First-time
players might want to play longer rounds — say,
12-15 minutes.
A round ends when one of the following three
things happen:
1.	Eight minutes have passed
When time runs out, each player (starting with
the dealer) gets to accuse another player of being

the spy. Players are now free to discuss their
suspicions. If ALL players agree with the dealer’s
accusation (the accused doesn’t get to vote), then
the accused player’s card is revealed. If a spy card
is revealed, each of the non-spy players win. If a
non-spy is revealed, the spy wins.
	 If the dealer’s choice is not unanimously convicted,
the accusation phase proceeds to the player on
their left. The accusation phase continues until a
unanimous vote is achieved. If no one is convicted
of being the spy after each player has had a turn
as accuser, the spy wins. A player may be accused
multiple times during this phase (and never gets
to vote on their own behalf).
2.	 When a Player Gets Suspicious
Each player may stop the clock once per round
to declare one of the players a suspect and
ask the others to vote. If all players agree (the
suspect doesn’t get a vote), the game ends
and that player’s card is revealed. If there is not
unanimous agreement, restart the clock, and
the player who made the accusation cannot use
this action again this round, but can still make an
accusation after time has run out (see #1). It’s in
the players’ best interest to perform this action.
It might also benefit the spy to use this action
in order to divert suspicion from themselves.
The same person may be the target of multiple
accusations during a round.
Note: Players should abstain from discussing the
spy’s identity during voting. The players’ arguments
“for“ and “against“ the spy’s identity could inadvertently
reveal the location’s identity to the spy.

3.	 At the Spy’s Request.
The spy can stop the clock at any time (except
when the clock has already been stopped by
another player) by revealing their spy card to the
other players. The spy is then allowed to consult
the location list in the middle spread of the
rulebook and identify the current location. The
spy wins if they identify the location correctly.
Otherwise the other players win.
Note: The spy may only reveal his card while the
game clock is running, and has not run out!
Once the round is over, the cards from that round
are returned to the dealer and can no longer be
played in the current game. The ziplock bag with this
deck is returned to the box.

Objectives and Strategies
The objectives of the non-spy players are to
identify the spy and avoid revealing their location.
Therefore, the non-spies should refrain from being
too explicit in their questions: (for example, “How
much cash did the robbers steal yesterday?“ The
spy will instantly identify the location as the bank).
However, when a player’s questions and answers
are too vague, other players might start suspecting
them of being the spy, enabling the real spy to win.

The spy’s objective is to listen as carefully as possible to what the other players say and do their best to
avoid blowing their cover while also trying to identify
the location before eight minutes have passed. A spy
who doesn’t attempt to guess the location is taking
a risk — it is entirely possible that the other players
will identify them after discussion and voting.

Non-Spy Victory
•	 Victory: Each non-spy player earns 1 point
•	 The player who initiated the successful
accusation of the spy earns 2 points instead

End of the Game

Scoring
Tally up the points earned by the players at the
end of the round based on the results.

Whoever scores the most points after the
agreed-upon number of rounds wins the game.

Spy Victory
•	 Victory: The spy earns 2 points if no one is
successfully accused of being the spy
•	 The spy earns 4 points if a non-spy player is
successfully accused of being a spy
•	 The spy earns 4 points if the spy stops the
game and successfully guesses the location

Credits
Publisher: Hobby World LLC
Created by: Alexander Ushan
Game development: Hobby World • Art: Uildrim and Sergey Dulin
Directors: Mikhail Akulov and Ivan Popov • Editor-in-Chief: Vladimir Sergeyev
Rulebook copy and editing: Alexander Kiselev, Valentin Matyusha, and Matt Hyra • Design and layout: Ivan Sukhovey
Proofreading: Olga Portugalova • Publisher contact: Nikolay Pegasov (nikolay@hobbyworld.ru)
Special thanks to Ilya Karpinsky.
No part of the rulebook, game contents, or corresponding artwork may be copied
or published without the consent of the copyright holder.

© 2014 Hobby World LLC. All rights reserved.
©2015 Cryptozoic Entertainment. www.cryptozoic.com.

</rulebook>
			
						               													<description>Spyfall is a party game unlike any other, one in which you get to be a spy and try to understand what's going on around you. It's really simple!&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Spyfall is played over several rounds, and at the start of each round all players receive cards showing the same location &amp;mdash; a casino, a traveling circus, a pirate ship, or even a space station &amp;mdash; except that one player receives a card that says &amp;quot;Spy&amp;quot; instead of the location. Players then start asking each other questions &amp;mdash; &amp;quot;Why are you dressed so strangely?&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;When was the last time we got a payday?&amp;quot; or anything else you can come up with &amp;mdash; trying to guess who among them is the spy. The spy doesn't know where he is, so he has to listen carefully. When it's his time to answer, he'd better create a good story!&amp;#10;&amp;#10;At any time during a round, one player may accuse another of being a spy. If all other players agree with the accusation, the round ends and the accused player has to reveal his identity. If the spy is uncovered, all other players score points.  However, the spy can himself end a round by announcing that he understands what the secret location is; if his guess is correct, only the spy scores points.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;After a few rounds of guessing, suspicion and bluffing, the game ends and whoever has scored the most points is victorious!&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2014" />
						               				<minplayers value="3" />
						               				<maxplayers value="8" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="204">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="153" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="154" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="14" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="150" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="11" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="97" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="64" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="5">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="76" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="91" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="7" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="6">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="131" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="45" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="7">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="50" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="104" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="9" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="8">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="30" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="97" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="34" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="8+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="4" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="13" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="96" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="15" />
						               				<minplaytime value="15" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="15" />
						               				<minage value="13" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="38">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="14" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="14" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="27">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="286" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="5" />
					<result level="287" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="18" />
					<result level="288" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="4" />
					<result level="289" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="290" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1023" value="Bluffing" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1039" value="Deduction" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1079" value="Humor" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1030" value="Party Game" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1081" value="Spies/Secret Agents" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2073" value="Acting" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2893" value="Communication Limits" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2047" value="Memory" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2028" value="Role Playing" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2892" value="Roles with Asymmetric Information" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2866" value="Targeted Clues" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2814" value="Traitor Game" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2017" value="Voting" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="70948" value="Digital Implementations: Tabletopia" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="56318" value="Misc: No Table Needed" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="49383" value="Players: One versus Many" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="166638" value="Spyfall: Cathedral promo cards" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="289184" value="Spyfall: Dracula's Castle" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="191942" value="Spyfall: Gaming Convention promo cards" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="172193" value="Spyfall: Ice Hockey Stadium promo cards" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="260353" value="Spyfall: Produce Farm promo cards" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="183969" value="Spyfall: The Box Is Not Enough" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="286102" value="Spyfall: The Roman Senate promo cards" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="258093" value="Spyfall: UFO promo cards" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameintegration" id="221371" value="DC Spyfall" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameintegration" id="193308" value="Spyfall 2" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameintegration" id="256085" value="Spyfall: Time Travel" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="78199" value="Alexandr Ushan" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="69037" value="Sergey Dulin" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="69038" value="Uildrim" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="18852" value="Hobby World" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="25074" value="BoardM Factory" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="46980" value="Brädspel.se" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="7162" value="Brain Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="4335" value="Competo / Marektoy" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="12024" value="Cryptozoic Entertainment" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="2400" value="Desyllas Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="26990" value="Dexy Co" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="29797" value="El Dragón Azul" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="917" value="dV Giochi" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="155" value="Gigamic" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30940" value="Hemz Universal Games Co. Ltd." />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="25996" value="Jumping Turtle Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30399" value="Ludicus" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30521" value="Mandoo Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="32395" value="NeoTroy Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="49167" value="NewGame" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="32581" value="PaperGames (III)" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="22" value="Piatnik" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="14346" value="Planplay" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="41167" value="Popcorn Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="7466" value="Rebel Sp. z o.o." />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="21053" value="REXhry" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="39774" value="Tower Tactic Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="25973" value="Zacatrus" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="35809" value="Zhiyanjia" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="19659" />
			<average value="6.83206" />
			<bayesaverage value="6.70424" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="753" bayesaverage="6.70424" />
																				<rank type="family" id="5498" name="partygames" friendlyname="Party Game Rank" value="57" bayesaverage="6.74603" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.41749" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="27207" />
			<trading value="912" />
			<wanting value="276" />
			<wishing value="2740" />
			<numcomments value="3179" />
			<numweights value="473" />
			<averageweight value="1.2368" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>