<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="22677">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/YXPeeJn7kpl8zPDZTG3oig__thumb/img/UqaOnLvKdClP4rAtKV0X9-_m_h8=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic691074.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/YXPeeJn7kpl8zPDZTG3oig__original/img/VAS4qwA2iNwIpSyB0GG2lcDFIc8=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic691074.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Stalin&#039;s War" />
				<rulebook>Living Rules

The Eastern Front

1941-45

RULE BOOK
TABLE OF CONTENTS
1.0 	 Introduction................................................................... 2
2.0 	 Components................................................................... 2
3.0	 Terminology and Abbreviations.................................... 4
4.0	 Game Set-up.................................................................. 5
5.0	 Determining Victory...................................................... 6
6.0	 Sequence of Play........................................................... 6
7.0	 Strategy Cards............................................................... 7
8.0	 Zones of Control (ZOC).............................................. 10
9.0	 Stacking....................................................................... 10
10.0	Movement.................................................................... 11
11.0	 Combat........................................................................ 12
12.0	Exploitation................................................................. 14
13.0	Supply.......................................................................... 15

14.0	Replacements............................................................... 16
15.0	Weather........................................................................ 17
16.0	Special Units................................................................ 17
17.0	Oil................................................................................ 18
18.0	Banked OPS................................................................. 18
19.0	National Restrictions................................................... 19
20.0	German Mobile Defense.............................................. 19
21.0	Bidding........................................................................ 19
22.0	Tournament Scenario................................................... 20
23.0	Optional Rules............................................................. 20
24.0	Easily Forgotten Rules................................................. 21
25.0	Unit Set-up................................................................... 21
Index.................................................................................... 22

GMT Games, LLC • P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308
www.GMTGames.com
© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

2

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

RULES OF PLAY

1.0	 INTRODUCTION

2.0	 COMPONENTS

Stalin’s War is a two-player game simulating the course of the Second World War on the eastern front, from the German invasion of
the Soviet Union on June 22, 1941 to the fall of Berlin in May, 1945.
These rules are organized into numbered sections, with some
sections further subdivided into subsections (for example, 2.1
and 2.2). In a number of places in the rules, you will see references made to rules sections and subsections that are related to
the one you are reading.
This is the “Living Rules” document for the game. It includes
errata and clarifications to the original rules. To aid readability,
errata and additional rules are indicated in red text, while clarifications are shown in blue text.

Credits
Designer: Ted Raicer
Developer: Paul Marjoram
Art Director: Rodger MacGowan
Box Art and Design: Rodger MacGowan
Map & Cards: Charles Kibler
Game Manuals & Player Aid Card: Charles Kibler
Counters: Mark Simonitch
Playtesters: Don Clarke, Paul Horvath, Stefan Mecay,
David Hoskins, Francois Trebosc, Jeff Kinney, David Aud, Jeff
Behan, Jesse Escobedo, Jim Lauffenberger, Tim Tow, Michael
Dauer, Nicolas Pei, Thomas Francois Stanislau
Proofreading: Jonathan Squibb, J. Peter Rich
Production Coordination: Tony Curtis
Producers: Tony Curtis, Rodger MacGowan, Andy Lewis, Gene
Billingsley and Mark Simonitch

Stalin’s War includes the following:
•	
•	
•	
•	

One 22” by 34” map.
88 5/8” die cut counters
280 1/2” die cut counters
2 player aid cards

2.1	

•	
•	
•	
•	

One rules booklet
One playbook
110 Strategy Cards
Two 6-sided Dice

THE GAME MAP

The game map consists of a pattern of hexes superimposed on
a map of the terrain over which the 1941-45 campaigns were
fought. Individual hexes contain various symbols representing different types of terrain. These are shown on the Terrain
Key printed on the map; their effects are listed in the Terrain
Effects Chart.
The game map also contains a number of charts and tracks to
record various game functions. These include the General Records Track (used to record the accumulation of Replacements
and Axis Victory Points), Fire Tables (used to resolve combat),
the Action and Consecutive OPS Tracks, the Eliminated Unit
Boxes, and the Turn Record Track.
The map also marks two Axis Logistical Zones: the Paulus
Zone (Russia, east of the Paulus line), and the Caucasus Zone
(Russia, south of the Caucasus line). Note that the Paulus Line
is considered to extend along the Kerch straits; e.g., a unit in
Novorossiysk is considered to be east of the Paulus Line.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

3

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

2.2	

THE PLAYING PIECES

2.2.1	 Combat Units
Combat units come in two different sizes. The 5/8” counters are
Large Combat Units (LCUs) and the 1/2” counters are Small
Combat Units (SCUs). LCUs represent Armies and SCUs represent Corps, except for the Soviet Union where LCUs represent
Fronts and SCUs represent Armies or Corps. SCUs depict forces
of between 20,000 and 60,000 men. LCUs represent large bodies of troops (up to 300,000 men) supported by heavy artillery,
air units etc.
	
	

Full	
Strength	

Reduced	
Strength	

Unit	
Size	

Single 	
Step	

No ZOC

2.3	

RO: Romania	

THE STRATEGY CARDS

2.3.1 	 Each player has his own deck of 55 Strategy Cards,
subdivided into 2 groups: 25 cards labeled Blitzkrieg Cards and
30 cards labeled Total War Cards. Each player begins the game
using only his Blitzkrieg Cards.
2.3.2 	 All Strategy Cards may be played as an Operations
(OPS) card or a Replacement Point (RP) card. Strategy/Event
Cards may also be played as an Event Card. Strategy/Combat
Cards may also be played as Combat cards during combat.
2.3.3 	 Strategy Cards that have an asterisk (*) following their
Event Name must be removed from the game immediately following their play as an Event or Combat card.

4
	 Combat	 Movement	
Attack	
Movement	
	No Rebuild			 Defense		
ID	

2.2.3 	 Counter Abbreviations
	 GE: Germany	
IT: Italy	
	 SU: Soviet Union	
HU: Hungary

Unit
Type

			 RP Values	
	 OPS	
GE	
GE	
Axis	
	 Value	
Infantry	 Armor	 Minor	

Card
ID #

The numbers printed across the bottom of a Combat Unit are its
Combat Strength and Movement Allowance. Some Combat Units
have two numbers across the bottom of the counter, while some
have three numbers. If there are three numbers the first two are
the Combat Strength subdivided into Attack and Defense Combat
Strengths (the left-most and center numbers respectively), used
depending on whether the unit is attacking or defending.

	 Card
	 Type

•	 Combat Strength is a measure of a unit’s ability to inflict
damage in Combat.

	 Event
	 Name

•	 Movement Allowance (MA) is a measure of a unit’s ability to
move.

	 Combat
	 Card

Note that an SCU may be weaker in Combat than an LCU with
a lower Combat Strength because LCUs perform their Offensive
or Defensive Fire on a better Combat Fire Table than SCUs.
Most LCUs and SCUs are printed on both sides of the counter.
The two sides are called steps. Most Combat Units have two
steps, although some weak units have only a single step. Single
step units have a light ‘half-stripe’ over their ID number to enable players to identify them as single-step without having to
turn them over. For two-step units the front side of the counter
represents the unit at full strength and the reverse side represents
the unit at reduced strength. Exception: Partisan counters consist
of Inactive (front) and Active (back) sides. Note: Many German
LCUs have four steps, represented on two different counters.
When the first two steps are eliminated, the unit is replaced on
the map by its second counter.
Some Combat Units are marked with an asterisk on the left side
of the counter. This indicates that this step of the unit may not
be rebuilt. A unit with an asterisk on all its steps is permanently
removed from the game when it is eliminated.
2.2.2 	 Game Markers
There are several types of Game Markers included in the game.
Their use is described in the rules.

	
	
	
	
	

Asterisk
(remove from
game when
played as an
Event)

	 Event
	 Text

2.4	 DAMAGED/MISSING
COMPONENTS OR QUESTIONS?
If there are any damaged or missing components, please contact
us at:
GMT Games
P.O. Box 1308
Hanford, CA 93232-1308
If you have any questions about the rules, we’ll be glad to answer
them if you send them to the address above with a self-addressed,
stamped envelope. For faster response, we’re on the Internet at
www.gmtgames.com, or at www.consimworld.com (where
you will find discussion forums for both GMT and Stalin’s War).

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

4

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual
General Government: German-annexed Poland
Germany: Germany is defined as the area marked “Greater
Germany”, including “General Government”, as well as the
hex containing Konigsberg. (This is important for placement of
German units.)
Guard: Any Soviet unit with a G in its unit ID.
Hex Control: Players should keep track of who controls the
following: Towns, Cities, Ports, Fortresses, Oil, and Victory
Point Hexes. Control of such hexes changes over to the enemy
at the instant an enemy unit enters it, as well as during the Attrition Phase under particular circumstances (see 13.3.9). Control
markers are provided to be used where needed.

3.0	 TERMINOLOGY AND
ABBREVIATIONS
*: If a Strategy Card with this symbol is played as an Event or
a Combat Card, it is permanently removed from the game after
this Action Round. It is not removed from the game if it is used
as an OPS or RP card.
Active Player: The player taking an action during his part of
the Action Round.
Axis: Collective term for German, Romanian, Hungarian and
Italian forces, and the German Vlassov unit.
Design Note: The Vlassov unit was made up of Russian POWs
armed by the German. In terms of command it was German;
in terms of quality it was Axis.

Banked OPS: OPS that a player may save for use during OPS
rounds later in the game turn.
Combat Card [CC]: A card that is used to influence combat
resolution. Such cards are indicated by having their OPS value
in red type and by the notation “CC” to the right of the event
name. Combat Cards are considered to be Event Cards.
Combat Strength: The offensive and defensive combat ability
of a unit, used to resolve combat on the Fire Tables. Some units
have their Combat Strength subdivided into distinct Attack and
Defense Strengths.
Draw Pile: Face down stack of cards from which players draw
their hands at the end of each turn.
Event Name: An Event’s Name which is underlined indicates
that the Event is a prerequisite for another Event. There will be
a marker for these Events, as well as for other Events with longterm effects. Players may use these markers on the Turn Record
Track as a reminder that the Event has occurred.
Festung: Fortresses declared by the Axis player.
Fortress Supply: A unit that is using a fortress as its supply
source (see 13.2.4) is in Fortress Supply.
Full Supply: A unit that can trace supply to a full supply source
is in full supply.

Logistical Lines: The map is divided by two Logistical Lines:
the Paulus Line and the Caucasus Line. Axis units in the zones
defined by these lines may have reduced movement and combat
ability.
Loss Number: The result from a Fire Table during Combat.
Movement Allowance (MA): The maximum number of Movement Points a unit may spend each turn.
Movement Points (MP): The cost to enter a hex during movement, as indicated on the Terrain Effects Chart. Hexes in Stalin’s
War cost 1, 2 or 3 MP to enter. Note: Some hexsides cost additional MPs to cross.
OPS Value: The number of OPS points which a player may
spend for movement or combat in an Action Round. Each card
has an OPS value of between 1 and 4.
OPS Round: Any round in which a player spends OPS for the
purpose of Movement or Combat.
Other Fronts box: A box on the mapboard that is used to hold
units sent away from the East Front by play of Events on Strategy
Cards. Units that enter the Other Fronts box at reduced strength
remain at reduced strength if and when they re-enter the game.
The Axis player chooses which units are sent to the Other Fronts
box as a result of Soviet Event play.
Out of Supply (OOS): Units lacking a supply line to a supply
source.
Panzer: A term used to denote German armor units.
Replacement Points (RPs): Points used to rebuild lost combat
steps.
Soviet Union: For game purposes, the Soviet Union is considered
to include all Baltic States hexes.
Victory Point (VP) Hex: Any hex containing a yellow star.
When control of any of these hexes changes, the VP marker on
the General Records Track should be adjusted by 1 in favor of
the new controlling player.
Zone of Control (ZOC): The ability of combat units to project
their influence into adjacent hexes. Not all units have a ZOC
(see 8.1).

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

4.0	 GAME SET-UP
4.1	

see 7.3.2). Players may take any valid Action in his round, except
that they may not take a Replacement or Reinforcement Action.

MARKER SET-UP
4.1.1	 Place the Turn Record marker on the June 1941
space of the Turn Record Track.
4.1.2	 Place the Victory Point marker on the 7 space
and the Axis and Soviet Hand Limit markers on the 6
space of the General Records Track.
4.1.3	 Place the Replacement Point and
Banked OPS markers on the 0 space of the
General Records Track.
4.1.4	 Place each player’s Consecutive OPS marker
on the 0 space of their Consecutive OPS track.

4.1.5	

Place all other markers within easy reach.

4.2	

UNIT SET-UP

4.2.1	 Place the units for both the Axis and the Soviet players
in the hexes listed in section 25.0.
4.2.2	 Place units that do not start the game in play to one side.
They may enter play as the game progresses.

4.3	

INITIAL STRATEGY CARDS

4.3.1	 Set aside Soviet cards 1 through 6 for later use (see 7.1.3),
then shuffle the remaining Soviet Blitzkrieg Cards and deal 6 to
the Soviet player. Before doing so, the Soviet player is allowed
to draw one Blitzkrieg card of his choice to add to his hand. This
card can be any non-reinforcement Blitz deck card, or Soviet
Reinforcement card number 4 (North Caucasus and Voronezh
Fronts, plus 62nd and 64th armies). If the Soviet player exercises
this option, he should only be dealt 5 further Blitzkrieg cards, so
that his hand size is still 6. Please note that, per rule 4.4.1, neither
player may take a Reinforcement round during turn 1, so if the
Soviet player does draw Card number 4 in this way he will have
to hold on to it until at least turn 2 before using it.
4.3.2	 Shuffle the Axis Blitzkrieg Cards and deal 6 to the Axis
player.
4.3.3	 Set aside the Axis and Soviet Total War cards for later use.
Note: Unfortunately, Axis Cards 51, 52, and 55 have the wrong labels. They should be labelled Total War, rather than Blitzkrieg, cards.
Thus, they need to be placed in the Total War deck at the beginning
of the game (rather than placing them in the Blitzkrieg deck).

4.4	

5

BARBAROSSA SPECIAL RULES

Design Note: The following rules simulate the Soviet unpreparedness for the initial Axis offensive, Operation Barbarossa.

4.4.1	 Turn 1 (June 1941) consists of a single Axis Action
Round, followed by a single Soviet Action Round. Exception: If
the Axis player has the Steppe Fox event, and chooses to play it,
he may immediately play a second card (and this second card determines which type of Round it is for Consecutive OPS purposes;

4.4.2	 Units begin the game in their historical set-up positions.
Consequently, Axis units may not move on Turn 1. They may
perform combat, advance after combat, and conduct exploitation
normally.
4.4.3	

No units may enter Hungary on Turn 1.

Design Note: Hungary was neutral until July 1941.

4.4.4	 Soviet units may not move or attack into Romania on
Turn 1.
Design Note: Soviet forces were initially under orders not to
enter either Hungary or Romania.

4.4.5	 Attrition is checked as normal this turn (i.e., check Axis
attrition at the end of the Axis Action Round and Soviet attrition
at the end of the Soviet Action Round). The remainder of the
sequence of play for a normal game turn is then followed (Draw
Strategy Cards and End of Turn Phases), ignoring Replacements.
4.4.6	 On Turn 1 (June 1941), Exploiting German Panzer
Corps ignore all non-swamp terrain effects.
4.4.7 	 On Turns 1 (June 1941) and 2 (Summer 1941), Soviet
Fronts may not participate in attacks on hexes that contain only
German Panzer Corps.
Design Note: The Soviets were simply not prepared in the
Summer of 1941 to deal with German blitzkrieg operations at
a level that would allow units the size of fronts to counterattack
panzer spearheads.

4.4.8	 On Turns 1 (June 1941) and 2 (Summer 1941), Soviet
Mech Corps in different hexes may not combine in attacks against
hexes containing only German Panzer Corps. The effects of
Combat Cards or Events do not override this restriction.
Design Note: Soviet Mech units in the Summer of 1941 proved
incapable of this sort of coordination.

4.4.9 During turns 1 to 4 (only), Axis play of cards for Reinforcements and/or Replacements does not reset the Axis Consecutive OPS marker (see 7.3.2).

4.5	

SOVIET MOBILIZATION

4.5.1	
As an exception to the normal Reinforcement rules (see
7.5.2) during turn 2 (only), the Soviets may play two cards as reinforcements. Note that these two cards must be played in two separate
and non-consecutive Action Rounds. Furthermore, the Soviet player
also receives OPS when playing these two cards on turn 2 (only).
This allows the player to spend OPS for movement and combat as
usual, but note that in this instance the reinforcements placed may
move, but not attack, in the round that they are placed. Reinforcement units are placed at the beginning of the Round, before any
movement has occurred. As such, normal stacking limits do apply
(see 9.0). When played in this manner, each of these two reinforcement cards leave the Consecutive OPS count unchanged (see 7.3.2).

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

6

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

4.5.2	 Furthermore, during turns 2 and 3 (only) the Soviet
player receives 3 RPs automatically. These RPs are spent during the Replacement Phase of that turn, as usual. This does not
impact the number of RP plays the Soviet player may make that
turn. (i.e., up to 2 other cards may be played as RPs during those
turn; see 7.4).

5.0	 DETERMINING VICTORY
5.1	

GENERAL RULES

5.1.1	 During the course of the game players keep track of the
VP level. The VP level starts at 7. It increases by 1 whenever the
Axis gain control of a VP hex, and decreases by 1 whenever the
Soviet player gains control of a VP hex. Some events also affect
the VP level.

6.0	 SEQUENCE OF PLAY
Stalin’s War is played in turns, each of which is subdivided into
Phases and Segments which must be strictly followed in the
order listed below.

A. ACTION PHASE
Each Action Phase is divided into five identical Action Rounds.
Each Action Round consists of an Axis Action Round followed
by a Soviet Action Round. The Axis Action Round allows the
Axis player to take one action; The Soviet Action Round allows
the Soviet player to take one action.

B. ATTRITION PHASE

•	 If the VP level is 20 or more during the End of Turn Phase of
any turn

The Axis Attrition Segment takes place immediately upon the
conclusion of the 5th Axis Action Round. The Soviet Attrition
Segment takes place immediately upon the conclusion of the 5th
Soviet Action Round. During the Attrition segments, OOS units
belonging to the active player are eliminated and OOS friendlycontrolled Cities, Ports, Oil, and Victory Point hexes become
controlled by the enemy (see 13.3.9).

•	 If the Axis controls all of the Oil hexes on the map for two
consecutive End of Turn Phases

C. REPLACEMENT PHASE

5.1.2	
The Axis player wins an Automatic Victory in one of
four ways:

•	 If the Axis controls Moscow, Leningrad and either Rostov or
Sevastapol at the end of Turn 4 (Winter 1942)
•	 If, at the end of Turn 8 (Winter 1943), the Axis controls
Moscow, Leningrad, Stalingrad and Sevastopol, and has cut
the supply line to Baku (so that Baku no longer acts as a full
supply source for the Soviets—see 13.2.3).
5.1.3	 The Soviet player wins an Automatic Victory in one of
four ways:
•	 If the VP level is 0 or less during the End of Turn Phase of any
turn
•	 If the Soviets control Berlin, Budapest (both Buda and Pest),
Bucharest and Konigsberg at the end of any Soviet Action
Round
•	 If no supplied Axis unit has moved to the east of the Paulus
Logistical Line before the end of Turn 4 (Winter 1942)
•	 If the Soviets control all VP spaces in the Soviet Union at the
end of any turn between Turns 2 and 12 (inclusive).
•	 The Soviet Player wins at the end of Turn 10 if the German
player has 9 or fewer VPs.
5.1.4	 The Campaign Scenario ends if either player achieves
an Automatic Victory, or at the end of Turn 18 (Summer 1945).
If neither player has won an Automatic Victory by the end of the
Turn 18 Action Phase, the Axis player wins. There are no draws.
5.1.5	 The Tournament Scenario ends at the completion of Turn
8 (Winter 1943). Players count the number of VP spaces in the
Soviet Union which are controlled by the Axis at that point: the
Axis player wins if the Axis control 9 or more VP spaces; the
Soviet player wins if 8 or fewer VP spaces are controlled by the
Axis. See Section 22.0 for more details.

SOVIET SEGMENT: The Soviet player spends any Replacement Points (RPs) accumulated through play of RP Cards this
turn (see 7.4). Any RPs not spent are lost.
AXIS SEGMENT: The Axis player spends any Replacement
Points accumulated through play of Cards for RPs this turn (see
7.4). Any RPs not spent are lost.

D. DRAW STRATEGY CARD PHASE
Players may discard any Strategy Cards remaining in their hand
(see 7.6.2). The Soviet player decides first. Each player then
draws cards from their Draw Pile to bring their hand to their
current hand size (see 7.1.3). Each player begins with a hand
size of 6 cards. Changes in control of Oil hexes and the effects
of certain Event Cards may change a player’s hand size (see 7.6).

E. END OF TURN PHASE
•	 The Axis player may remove friendly Trench markers from
the map
•	 The Soviet player may remove friendly Trench markers from
the map
•	 Any remaining Banked OPS are lost (set the markers for both
players to zero).
If the war has not ended due to Automatic Victory or reaching
Turn 18 (Summer 1945), advance the Turn marker to the next
space on the Turn Record Track and begin the Sequence of Play
again with the first Axis Action Round.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

7

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

7.2.3	 The players continue to alternate taking Actions until
each player has taken five Actions.
7.2.4	 As players take Action Rounds they record what type
of round they have taken using a set of Action Round markers,
placing them in the on-map Action Round boxes corresponding
to the action that was taken in that round. These on-map boxes
are color-coded green if the corresponding action advances the
Consecutive OPS count, yellow if it leaves it in place, and grey
if it resets the Consecutive OPS count to 0. Players record the
number of Consecutive OPS they have spent (see 7.3.2) by placing the Consecutive OPS marker on the on-map Consecutive
OPS track.

7.0	 STRATEGY CARDS
7.1	

GENERAL RULES

7.1.1	 In Stalin’s War, the Strategy Cards are the heart of
the game. The players initiate most actions, including Combat,
through the play of Strategy Cards.
7.1.2	 Each player has their own deck of Strategy Cards, subdivided into two groups: Blitzkrieg Cards and Total War Cards.
Each player begins the game using only their Blitzkrieg Cards.
The Total War cards are added when Total War is initiated.
7.1.3	 During the Draw Strategy Card Phase of each turn, the
players draw cards from the Draw Pile to bring their hand to
their current hand size. Exception: During turn 1 and turns 3-6,
the Soviet player receives certain reinforcements automatically,
from the cards that were placed to one side at the beginning of
the game (see 4.3.1), and then draws cards from his Draw Pile
to bring himself up to his current hand limit. Specifically:
a) During turn 1, automatically draw cards 1 and 2 (so they will
be available for use on turn 2);
b) During turn 3, automatically draw card 3;
c) During turn 4, automatically draw card 4;
d) During turn 5, automatically draw card 5;
e) During turn 6, automatically draw card 6.
7.1.4	 Each Strategy Card may be used in one of three possible ways: Operations (OPS), Replacement Points (RP), or as an
Event. The same card can be used in the same or a different way
each time it is played during a game, but each card may only be
used in one way each time it is played. Exception: Reinforcement plays during Soviet Special Mobilization (see 4.5).

7.2	

ACTION PHASE

7.2.1	 Strategy Cards are played during the Action Phase of
each turn. There are five Action Rounds per Action Phase. In
each Action Round, each player is allowed to take one Action.
7.2.2	 The Axis player conducts the first Action in each Action
Round.

7.2.5	 Note that, in direct contrast to most other ‘card-driven’
games that you may be familiar with, most movement does not
require the expenditure of OPS. More specifically, in any action
phase in which a player has played a card for OPS, played an
event that grants OPS, or taken the first of the two Automatic 0
OPS Round options below, that player is free to move all of his
units. Note that some movement does require OPS expenditure
(see 7.3.3). In this latter case movement will be limited by the
amount of OPS that are available.
7.2.6	 The action taken in an Action Round depends upon
whether the player plays a Strategy Card or not:
If the player has a Strategy Card, he may play one as an OPS
Round, RP, or Event.
OR
If the player has no Strategy Cards in their hand, or chooses
not to play one, the player may take an Automatic 0 OPS
Round. No Blitz markers may be placed as a result of combat
in such a round (combat may still be possible because of OPS
used from ‘Banked OPS’ (see 18.0)). A player has two options when taking such a round. First, the player may move
or conduct combat with any units. In this case the consecutive
OPS marker (see 7.3.2) remains in place (it is not reset to 0)
and the number of OPS received during this round is not affected by the consecutive OPS marker. Second, a player may
choose to neither move any units nor activate any spaces for
combat in a 0 OPS round, in which case the player may reset
the consecutive OPS count to 0 and is allowed to discard one
card from his hand and replace it with a card drawn from the
top of the Draw Pile if desired. Note that there are restrictions
on the execution of 0 OPS Rounds during a Rasputitsa round
(see 15.1.1).

7.3	

OPERATIONS

7.3.1	 If a Strategy Card is played as an OPS Card, the player
is allowed to spend a number of OPS Points equal to the modified
OPS Value of the card (see 7.3.2).
7.3.2	 Players receive fewer OPS for Strategy Cards that are
played for OPS in consecutive rounds. This is tracked using the
Consecutive OPS counter (one for each player), which begins
the game in the 0 space on the Consecutive OPS track. If a player
plays a Strategy Card as an OPS Card, place the Round marker

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

8

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

for that Round in the “OPS Round” box of the on-map Action
Rounds area. This box is colored green as a reminder that such
a play advances the Consecutive OPS count. The Consecutive
OPS count is then immediately increased by 1, and the counter
on the Consecutive OPS track is moved accordingly. The number
of OPS received for this card play is then reduced by the number
indicated in the space currently occupied by the Consecutive OPS
counter. Broadly speaking, this results in the player receiving one
less OPS for each consecutive round in which they have played
cards for OPS. (But note the exceptions for Soviet Mobilization
(see 4.5.1) and some ‘0 OPS’ plays (see 7.2.6).) These effects are
cumulative and do carry over from one turn to another. When,
during their Action Round, a player plays a Strategy Card for
RPs or an event, or takes a 0 OPS round in which no units move
or are involved in combat (see 7.2.6), immediately reset the
consecutive OPS marker to 0. Exception: The Consecutive OPS
count is never reset during a Rasputitsa Round (see 15.1.1).

7.3.5	 After all Movement is completed, the active player may
use any remaining OPS to mark hexes with Combat markers.
These markers may be placed in any hex. Once all such markers have been placed, units in these hexes may initiate Combat.
The target of attacks need not be specified in advance. Combat
is always voluntary, and no unit is required to attack. A unit may
move, including expending an OPS for movement, and still initiate
Combat if an OPS is spent to place a Combat marker on the hex
it is in when its movement is complete. Note that hexes can be
marked for both movement and combat (at a total cost of 2 OPS).

Example: Suppose the Consecutive OPS count is at 0 at the
end of the previous turn (for example, a card was played for
RPs during the player’s last Action Round). During Action
Round 1 the Axis player plays a Strategy Card for 4 OPS.
The Consecutive OPS marker is placed on the Consecutive
OPS on-map track on the “1st, Full OPS” box, and the full 4
OPS are received for activation for movement and combat. If
the Axis player plays a Strategy Card for OPS during Action
Round 2 and that card again has a printed OPS value of “4”,
the Consecutive OPS marker is placed in the “2nd, –1 OPS”
box and the player receives 4–1=3 OPS. If the Axis player also
plays a Strategy Card for OPS during Action Round 3 and it
has a printed OPS value of “4”, the Consecutive OPS marker is
placed in the “3rd, –2 OPS” box and the card’s value is reduced
by two and will be worth only 2 OPS. If, in the next round, the
Axis player plays a card as an event, the consecutive OPS count
is reset, and the marker is placed in the “0 N/A” box.

7.4.2	 The Soviet player may play a Strategy Card as an RP
Card twice per turn.

7.3.3	 A player is free to move any and all of his units, subject to
the restrictions below, during each Action Round in which he either
plays a card for OPS, or takes a 0 OPS round. Movement requires
the expenditure of OPS only under the following circumstances:
•	 It costs 1 OPS for a stack of one or more friendly units in an
enemy ZOC to completely vacate the hex in which it begins the
Action Round. However, if at least one unit which started the
Action Round in a hex remains in it, all other friendly units may
leave that hex without spending any OPS. Note: Moving units
into a hex during an Action Round does not allow all the units
which started in that hex to be moved without expending an OPS.
Exceptions: Friendly units may leave an enemy ZOC while
advancing after Combat and during Exploitation movement
without having to spend OPS.
•	 Strategic Movement (either rail or sea) costs 1 OPS per unit
moved. Only SCUs may use Strategic Movement (see 10.2).
Exception: Axis Naval Evacuation (see 10.2.7).
Note: Movement during ‘advance after combat’ or exploitation
never requires OPS expenditure.

7.3.4	 Place a Move marker in each hex where an
OPS was spent. (This is simply to help you keep track
of how many OPS have been spent.)

7.4	

REPLACEMENT POINTS

7.4.1	 If a Strategy Card is played as a Replacement (RP)
Card, the player marks the number of RPs listed in the RP Box
for each nationality on the General Records Track. The player
may not conduct any other actions (e.g., movement) besides
marking the RPs during this Action Round. Exception: Certain
Strategy Cards specifically allow the player both to mark RPs
and either conduct the card’s Event or use the card for OPS. This
is indicated in the text of such cards.

7.4.3	 The Axis player may play a Strategy Card as an RP Card
once per turn. (Exception: The Axis may play 2 RP cards during
Spring Turns in 1942 and 1943 only.) The Axis player may also
play one Strategy Card with an Event that provides RPs as an
Event each turn.
7.4.4	 Players may not play a Strategy Card as an RP Card if
they played a Strategy Card as an RP Card in their previous Action Round this turn. However, players may play an RP card in
the last Action Round of one turn and in the first Action Round
of the next turn.
7.4.5	 RPs are spent during the Replacement Phase of each
turn (see 14.0).

7.5	

EVENTS

7.5.1	 General Rules
7.5.1a 	 If a Strategy Card is played as an Event, the instructions
on the card must be followed. The player may not move units
unless explicitly permitted by the event.
7.5.1b 	 A card may be played as an Event even if some or all of
its effects are not applicable. For example, the Soviet side may
play the Event Operation Bagration, which as part of its effect
activates partisans, even if there are no partisans on the board.
7.5.1c 	 If a Strategy card with an asterisk (*) symbol is played
as an Event, it is permanently removed from the game at the end
of the Action Round. The card is not removed from the game if
is used as an OPS or RP card.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual
7.5.2	 Reinforcement Event Cards
7.5.2a 	 Each player can bring new units (reinforcements) into
play by using Strategy Cards that give reinforcements as Events.
Only Events with the word “Reinforcements” in the event name
are considered to be Reinforcement cards. Only one Reinforcement card may be played per turn by each player.
Exceptions: 1. Neither player may play a Reinforcement card
during the June 1941 turn; 2. The Soviet player may play two
reinforcements during Soviet Mobilization (see 4.5).
7.5.2b	 If a player cannot place all of the reinforcements listed
on a card on the map, the card may be played but units not placed
are permanently removed from the game.
7.5.2c	 Axis-player reinforcing units are placed in that nation’s
capital and/or any friendly-controlled Full Supply sources, Cities, or Fortresses in that nation (provided the city/fortress is in
full supply — judge this as you would for a friendly unit in the
same hex); the Soviet player places units similarly, but may also
place reinforcing units in Towns that are in full supply. There are
several exceptions noted on the Event Cards and below.
•	 Soviet Total War (TW) Fronts (i.e., Front units received as
reinforcement on Total War cards) are exchanged on a one for
one basis for full- or reduced-strength fully supplied on-map
Soviet Blitzkrieg Fronts. These units are listed in green text as
a reminder. Place the TW Front in the hex of the Blitz Front
they are replacing, while the replaced Blitz Front is removed
from the game. The TW Front enters at full-strength regardless
of the strength of the removed Front.
•	 Most Soviet Total War Guard Armies with a “G” designation
(i.e., “4G” through “11G”) are exchanged on a one for one
basis for full- or reduced-strength fully supplied on-map
Soviet Army (only) SCUs. Place the Guard Army in the hex
of the Soviet Army it is replacing; the replaced Soviet Army
is permanently removed from the game. These units are listed
in green text as a reminder. The Guard Army enters at fullstrength regardless of the strength of the removed Soviet Army.
Design Note: Guards armies 1G-3G were formed directly,
not from existing armies, and so go onto the map without
replacing any army.

•	 Soviet Guard Tank Armies (units with a “GT” designation)
are exchanged on a one for one basis for any full- or reducedstrength fully supplied on-map Soviet Tank Armies. Place the
Guard Tank Army in the hex of the Tank Army it is replacing; the
replaced Soviet Army is permanently removed from the game.
These units are listed in green text as a reminder. The Guard
Tank Army enters at full-strength regardless of the strength of
the removed Tank Army. Note: If a Soviet Reinforcement card
brings on both Guard tank armies and regular tank armies, those
units can be placed in any order. Consequently, the regular tank
armies that are placed are eligible to be replaced by the Guard
tank armies, per the above rules.

9

7.5.3	 Reinforcing units listed inside parentheses () are placed
on the map with their flipped (weaker) side uppermost.
7.5.4	 Soviet Invasion Event Card
The Soviet Black Sea, Black Death card allows the Soviet Marine Army to move from any friendly port on the Black Sea to
any unoccupied coastal hex. After landing, the Marine Army is
always in supply in a coastal hex as long as the Soviets control
one port on the Black Sea.
7.5.5	 Combat Cards
7.5.5a 	 Combat Cards are Events that can be played during a
Combat to influence it. First, the Attacker chooses whether to
play Combat Cards, and reveals those cards; then the Defender
does the same. Combat Cards are the only cards which can be
played during the opponent’s Action Round.
7.5.5b 	 If a player plays any Combat Cards and wins the Combat, the player places those Combat Cards face up on his side of
the map. (Exceptions: 1. Combat Cards marked with an asterisk
(*) are permanently removed from play immediately after use;
2. Combat Cards that explicitly state they may only be used
once per turn are immediately dicarded.) The player may, if he
chooses, use these face up cards to influence Combat in future
Action Rounds. The cards may be used to influence one other
Combat per Action Round (not including the current Action
Round), initiated by either player, in which their conditions apply, for the balance of the turn (however, see 7.5.5c). Note that
Soviet Combat Cards Operation Uranus and Sturmovik, and Axis
Combat Cards Sleighride and Führer’s Firemen, are exceptions to
this rule. They affect all attacks that round, regardless of combat
results, after which they are discarded.
7.5.5c 	 If a player loses a Combat and has used any Combat
Cards, whether played specifically for this Combat or saved from
a previously won Combat, those Combat Cards are discarded.
7.5.5d 	 At the end of each Turn, all Combat Cards which were
played must be discarded even if the player was victorious in
every battle in which the card was used. Place the cards in the
player’s Discard Pile.
7.5.5e 	 A Combat Card can be used a maximum of once per
Action Round until it is lost due to 7.5.5c or 7.5.5d. (Exceptions:
Operation Uranus, Sturmovik and Luftwaffe Support; see 7.5.5b.)

•	 Italian units enter at Bucharest and/or Odessa (in each case if
Axis controlled).
•	 The capital of Hungary is Buda.
© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

10

7.6	

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual
ZOCs have no effect on Advance After Combat or Exploitation.
Also recall that moving units into a hex during an Action Round
does not allow all the units which started in that hex to be moved
without expending an OPS (see 7.3.3).

HAND SIZE

7.6.1	 General Rules
The maximum/minimum hand size is as follows:
•	 No player may ever have a hand size greater than 7.
•	 No player may ever have a hand size less than 4. Exception: The
Axis player has no minimum hand size on turns 16 through 18.
The maximum/minimum hand size may change because of:
•	 Control of Oil hexes (see 17.1)
•	 Play of certain Events that reduce hand size
7.6.2	 Both players have the option to discard any or all of the
Strategy Cards remaining in their hand before they draw new
cards. Players may examine the cards that their opponent
discards.
7.6.3	 If a player needs to draw a Strategy Card but their draw
pile is empty, reshuffle the discards to form a new draw pile.
7.6.4	 Total War is triggered at the beginning of the Card Draw
Phase if it is turn 6 or later and either of the following conditions
are satisfied:
•	 Either player has removed 12 “*” Strategy Cards from the
game by playing them as Events.
•	 The players have removed a combined total of 20 “*” Strategy
Cards from the game by playing them as Events.
Total War can never be triggered before Turn 6.
When Total War is triggered, each player adds their Total War
cards to all their discards and undrawn Blitzkrieg cards and
reshuffles them to form a new Draw Pile.

9.0	 STACKING

8.0	 ZONES OF CONTROL (ZOC)

9.1	

GENERAL RULES

8.1 	
The following units have Zones of Control when in full
supply (see 13.1.2):

9.1.1	

A maximum of four (4) combat units may stack per hex.

9.1.2	

Only one LCU may stack per hex.

•	 All LCUs
•	 Soviet Mech Corps, Tank Armies, and Guard Armies
•	 German Panzer Corps
No other units have ZOC. Units without a ZOC are indicated by
the presence of a faint white square at the border of their playing
piece. Units in fortress supply (see 13.2.4) have no ZOC.

9.1.3	 The following unit types do not count for stacking, but
there may only be one of each type per hex:
•	
•	
•	
•	

Stalin
the Bunker
Soviet Fortified Zone
Partisans (Active or Inactive).

8.2 	
ZOCs extend into all adjacent hexes, with the following exceptions: ZOC do not extend across impassable hex-sides
(i.e., lake and sea hex-sides); ZOCs do not extend into Fortress
or Festung hexes; Axis ZOCs do not extend into a hex with a
Soviet Fortified Zone marker.

9.1.4	 Stacking is in effect at all times except during regular
and strategic movement, exploitation, and retreat (although it
applies at the end of movement, exploitation, and retreat).

8.3 	
All units must stop upon entering an enemy ZOC.
Units in an enemy ZOC may only exit the hex if a friendly unit
remains in the hex or an OPS is spent to allow the unit(s) to move.
Units may not move directly from one enemy ZOC to another,
or retreat or trace supply through an enemy ZOC. (Exception:
friendly units negate enemy ZOC for retreat and supply only.)

9.2.1	 Hungarian and Romanian units may never stack in the
same hex.

9.2	

9.2.2	

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

SPECIAL RULES

Partisans may never stack with any other Soviet units.

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

11

10.2.2	 Units may move any distance by rail along rail lines.
They may begin their move in an enemy ZOC provided the hex
contains another friendly unit, and provided that unit does not
itself use Strategic Movement, but they may not thereafter enter
a hex in an enemy ZOC. Axis units using rail movement may
ignore one Inactive Partisan unit, but must stop upon entering a
second such hex in a single rail move.
10.2.3	 A player may use all rail hexes for rail movement,
provided they can trace an uninterupted line of rail hexes free
of enemy units, enemy ZOC, or enemy controlled city/oil/VP/
Port/Fortress hexes to a friendly supply hex. Exception: Axis
units may not use rail movement in the USSR during Turns 1-4,
or in the Baltic Republics (Latvia, Estonia and Lithuania) during
turns 1-2.
10.2.4	 Axis units may never use rail movement in the Caucasus
Zone. Soviet units may never use rail movement in Germany.

10.0	MOVEMENT
10.1	 GENERAL RULES
10.1.1	 Clear hexes cost 1 MP to enter regardless of the presence of towns/cites/fortresses/festungs. Movement costs for other
terrain types are listed on the Terrain Effects Chart.
10.1.2	 If multiple terrain types exist in a hex, the unit pays the
greatest of the associated MP costs. For example, it costs 2MPs
to enter Astrakhan (hex 3032).
10.1.3	 Movement must be from hex to adjacent hex. Hexes
may not be skipped.
10.1.4	 A unit may never spend more Movement Points than its
Movement Allowance in a single turn. Unused Movement Points
cannot be accumulated for future turns or transferred to other
units. Exception: Units may always move a single hex (only),
even if the cost of that move would ordinarily be greater than
their MA, provided the movement is legal in every other way.
(For example, a Soviet shock unit, with a MA of 2, may enter a
mountain hex.)
10.1.5	 Supplied Axis units that start their move east of the
Paulus Logistical Line on Turns 1 to 4 have their Movement
Allowance reduced by 1.
10.1.6	 Units may not enter a hex that contains enemy units.
Exception: Axis units may move through, and stack with, Inactive Soviet Partisans.

10.2	 STRATEGIC MOVEMENT
10.2.1	 If a Strategy Card is played as an OPS Card, the player
may also use Strategic Movement to move SCUs. Strategic
Movement occurs at the same time as regular movement. However, a unit cannot use normal movement or attack on the same
round that it uses strategic movement. It costs 1 OPS per SCU
to move by rail or by sea. The German Bunker unit may not
use Strategic Movement. A player may expend OPS to conduct
Strategic Movement during the same Action Round that OPS are
also spent for other movement or attacks.

10.2.5	 The Axis player may use Strategic Movement to Sea
Move one SCU per turn in the Baltic Sea and one SCU per turn
in the Black Sea/Sea of Azov. The unit must start and end its
move in a friendly port, (the presence of enemy ZOC does not
prevent such a move), and may not move east of a port under
Soviet control.
10.2.6	 The Soviet player may use Strategic Movement to
Sea Move 1 SCU per ACTION ROUND in the Black Sea/Sea
of Azov only. The unit must start its move in a friendly port,
but may move to any non-enemy-controlled hex, regardless
of the presence of enemy ZOC, but never west of an Axiscontrolled port.
10.2.7	 The Naval Evacuation Event allows the Axis player to
evacuate any 1 LCU from a port hex to another friendly port hex
farther west. The LCU is automatically reduced to its last step
strength.

10.3	 TRENCHES
10.3.1	 A player may attempt to build a trench in
a hex containing one of his LCUs by expending 1
OPS. The LCU may not move, but other units in the
hex may move freely. After all Movement for the
Action Round is complete, the player rolls a die for each hex
which has an LCU attempting to entrench. If the die roll is 1-3
place a Trench marker in that hex. Only one entrenchment attempt
can be made per hex per Action Round. Note: The Soviet player
may attempt to entrench only after play of the People’s Militia
Event, the Axis only after play of the Hedgehogs Event.
10.3.2	 Friendly Trenches are removed from the map either
when the hex becomes enemy controlled or enemy occupied or
as the player chooses during the End of Turn Phase. The number
of trench markers provided with the game is an absolute limit.
10.3.3	 Trenches must be placed in spaces containing an LCU
even when placed as a consequence of an event (i.e., People’s
Militia).

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

12

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual
11.1.9	 The Axis player may not attack the Leningrad hex until
the Nordlicht Event has been played, the Moscow or Gorki
hexes until the Taifun Event has been played, or the Stalingrad
hex or any hex in the Caucasus Logistics Zone until the Blau
Event has been played. They may however move into these
hexes at any time if they are vacant. Once the appropriate card
has been played, one or more of the restricted hex(es) has been
entered, or control of at least one the space(s) has been gained
due to attrition, the relevant restriction is removed for the rest
of the game.
Example: If an Axis unit moves into a vacant Moscow hex, Axis
units are now free to enter/attack Moscow and Gorki at any time.

11.0	 COMBAT

11.1.10	 Axis units may not attack across any Volga hexside south
of Saratov unless either Moscow or Stalingrad is Axis-controlled.
These hexsides are marked on the map with a white, dashed line.

11.1	 GENERAL RULES

11.2	 COMBAT RESOLUTION

11.1.1	 A Combat can be initiated only during an Action Round by combat units in a hex containing a
Combat marker. Combat is voluntary and not all units
in a hex have to attack.
11.1.2	 The active player is called the Attacker and the nonactive player is the Defender.
11.1.3	 Each Combat may involve only one defending hex,
and only one attacking LCU. Combat is normally between two
adjacent hexes. Units in other hexes may attack in combination
with units from the first attacking hex, as long as there is a Panzer/Tank/Mechanized unit in the additional hex that is attacking
the defending hex, and provided that hex is also activated for
Combat. Exception: The Soviet Zhukov event allows the Soviet
player to ignore the requirement for mechanized units in the
additional hex of attacks that arise from use of that event.
Example: If Soviet units attack an Axis unit from three adjacent
hexes, two of those hexes would have to contain an attacking
Tank Army or Mechanized Army.
11.1.4	 A single hex may be attacked only once per Action
Round. All units in a single hex defend as a whole, except for
units which have retreated into that hex during that Action Round
(see 11.4.5). Empty hexes may not be attacked.
11.1.5	 Units in a single hex do not have to participate in the
same Combat (or any Combat). They may attack different adjacent hexes.
11.1.6	 Each unit may participate in only one Combat per Action
Round. A unit’s Combat Strength may not be divided between
multiple Combats.

11.2.1	 Each Combat is resolved using the following procedure,
in the order given:
1. Designate the Combat: The active player designates which
units are attacking and which hex they are attacking. Supply
status of defending units is now determined.
2. Determine Combat Strengths: Each player totals the
Combat Strengths of the units involved in the Combat to
determine his total Combat Strength. This step is conducted
simultaneously.
3. Play Combat Cards: The Attacker may play any number
of Combat Cards whose conditions are met by this Combat.
In addition, the Attacker may use any Combat Cards that are
in front of him whose conditions are met by this Combat and
which have not been used in a previous Combat during this
Action Round. After the Attacker plays and selects all his
Combat Cards, the Defender has the opportunity to play and
select Combat Cards using the same procedure outlined for the
Attacker. Exception: a player may not use CCs in a combat if
all his forces in that combat are OOS (see 13.3.4).
4. Determine Fire Column: Each player determines which
Fire Table he will use. If the player’s units contain one or more
LCUs (even if reduced), the player fires on the LCU Table;
otherwise, the player fires using the SCU Table.
Exception: If a stack contains three or more Panzer SCUs
it automatically fires on the LCU Combat table in attack or
defense. If attacking, these units must attack the same hex in
order to fire on the LCU column. The units are treated as SCUs
for all other purposes (e.g., taking losses).

11.1.7	 Active Partisan units may never attack or defend with
other Soviet units.
11.1.8	 Only attacking units participating in a Combat may take
losses or advance. If there are non-participating units in the attacking hex, they are not allowed to take losses or advance, but
they may be able to Exploit.
© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual
Each player finds his Combat Strength on the appropriate Fire
Table. Note that the attacker may shift a number of columns
depending upon the Terrain Effects of the defending hex to
determine his Fire Column. Both players may also shift a
column due to effects of German Mobile Defense (see 20.0).
Each player will also shift one column to the left if any of his
units are OOS (see 13.3.5). The Axis player may also shift due
to the effects of weather (see 15.1.2). Finally, the Axis player
shifts one column to the left when attacking during turns 1-4
if the unit or units being attacked in that combat are east of the
Paulus Line and all attacking units are in full supply. This step
is conducted simultaneously. All column shifts are cumulative.
Design Note: The column shift relating to the Paulus Line
reflects the poor supply chain to easternmost Axis units
during the early stages of the offensive. As such, it does not
apply to OOS units, since they will already receive a column
shift for being out of supply.

Column shifts cannot cause the Fire Column to be off the
Tables. If the column shifts would take the Fire Column below
the leftmost column or above the rightmost column, any additional shifts are ignored.
5. Determine Results: Each player rolls a die and cross references it with his Fire Column to determine his result. This step
is conducted simultaneously.
6. Take Losses: Each player must now apply the Combat losses
required by his opponent’s result, Defender first.
7. Determine Combat Winner: If one side (only) is completely eliminated, then the other side is considered the winner
of the combat. Otherwise, the player who inflicts the higher
Loss Number wins the Combat. Note that neither Combat
Cards that inflict or remove step losses, nor the extra Soviet
loss that results from use of the Zhukov event, affect determination of the combat winner. The losing player must discard
all played and selected Combat Cards. The winning player is
allowed to keep any played or selected Combat Cards active
unless the text on the card explicitly prohibits this, or the Event
name is asterisked (the Combat Cards stay face-up in front of
the player and can be used in subsequent Action Rounds). If
both players’ Loss Numbers are the same, or all units of both
sides are completely eliminated, both are considered to have
lost and must discard any selected Combat Cards. Exception:
The attacker wins if all of the following conditions apply:
•	 The Loss Numbers are the same
•	 The Attacker has a surviving fully-supplied Mechanized/
Guard/Tank/Panzer SCU
•	 The Defender does not have a surviving fully-supplied Mech/
Guard/Tank/ Panzer SCU
•	 The defending hex does not contain a Swamp, Trench, Festung,
or Fortress.

13

8. Defender Retreat: If the requirements are met (see 11.4),
the defender may have to retreat one or two hexes. The defender may have the option to cancel the retreat by taking an
additional step loss (see 11.4.3 and the Terrain Effects Chart).
9. Attacker Advance/Place Blitz markers: If the
defender retreated or was completely eliminated,
the attacker has the option to advance with any remaining units into the vacated hex, regardless of ZOC (see
11.5). If the Attacker has units that are allowed to Exploit, he
may place a Blitz marker in the vacated hex, as long as at least
one such unit advances into it and the hex is not forest, rough,
swamp, mountain, city, Fortress, Festung, across a major
river or the Kerch crossing (see the Terrain Effects Chart).
Exception 1: If the Soviets received no Lend-Lease Banked
OPS at the start of any Turn (see 18.3), no Soviet Blitz markers
may be played that Turn.
Design Note: This exception reflects the effects of a lack of
trucks and spare parts if shipments from the US are cut off.

Exception 2: No Blitz markers may be placed during a 0 OPS
round (see 7.2.6).
A player may place no more than 4 Blitz markers in a single
round. If a Blitz marker is placed, the attacker may advance
into that hex in excess of stacking limits if desired, but stacking will be checked as usual after exploitation is complete. If
an attack involves multiple attacking units, some of which are
crossing river hexsides, a Blitz marker may only be placed if
the attacker advances an exploitation-capable unit across a
non-major river hexside into the defender’s vacated hex.

11.3	 TAKING LOSSES
11.3.1	 The result of each player’s die roll on the fire table is
their opponent’s Loss Number.
11.3.2	 Losses are taken by reducing or eliminating combat
units. Each step removed from a unit counts one towards fulfilling
the Loss Number. No unit may take a second step loss in a combat
(including losses from Combat Cards) unless every other combat
unit of that side has taken a step loss in that combat. Exception:
the Stalin counter may take a step loss only if all other combat
units in its hex have been eliminated.
11.3.3	 Important rule: The first step loss in any attack (not
defense) must be taken from a panzer, tank or mechanized unit
if possible.
11.3.4	 Asterisked results can cause a loss only to an SCU. If
the affected player only has LCUs involved in the combat, no loss
is taken (but the original loss number is still used to determine
the winner of the combat in step 7 of 11.2.1). A player may not
choose to apply an asterisked result to an LCU.
11.3.5	 Note that Combat Cards that alter losses (e.g., the Tiger
Event) take effect after the winner of the battle is determined.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

14

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

11.3.6	 Eliminated units are available for recreating during the
Replacement Phase. Place such units in the Eliminated Units box
where they are available to be be replaced in any subsequent
Replacement Phase (see 14.0). However, Axis LCUs that are
eliminated while they are OOS are placed on the turn record
track three turns later. When the Turn marker advances into a
space that contains Axis LCUs, they are placed in the Eliminated
Units box and may now be replaced. Exception: The Soviet
Southwest Front is represented by two counters. The first time
that the Soviet Southwest Front is eliminated it is replaced by
the counter corresponding to its weaker version. Place the replacement SW Front counter in the Eliminated Units box and
permanently remove the original SW Front unit.

11.4	 RETREATS
11.4.1	 If the Attacker wins the Combat, any defending units not
eliminated must retreat unless the defender uses the No Retreat
option (see 11.4.3). Exception: Defending units in a Festung
must ignore all retreats and do not lose any additional steps.
Retreating units may retreat to different hexes.
11.4.2	 The number of hexes of the retreat depends upon the
difference in the Loss Numbers. If the difference is zero or one,
the defender must retreat one hex. Otherwise, the defender must
retreat two hexes.
11.4.3	 No Retreat Option: Defending units in Forests, Mountains, Rough, Swamps, Trenches, or Fortresses may chose to
ignore a retreat by taking one additional step loss. The step loss
can be from any defending unit, without regard to the restrictions
of 11.3.2. The one additional loss cancels the retreat, regardless
of the number of retreat hexes required. At least one defending
step must remain in the hex after the additional loss or the No
Retreat option may not be taken.
11.4.4	 Units which cannot perform a retreat nor use the No
Retreat option are eliminated. Units that are eliminated for failure
to retreat, or eliminated while OOS, are treated as if they were
eliminated due to OOS (see 13.3.8).
Units which retreat must follow the restrictions below:
•	 Must retreat a number of hexes exactly equal to that required
by 11.4.2.
•	 May not enter a hex containing an enemy unit nor an enemy
Fortress/Festung.
•	 May not retreat from a port by sea.
•	 May not retreat into an un-negated ZOC (see 8.3).
•	 May not retreat back into the original defending hex if
retreating two hexes.

Retreats should also obey the following conditions, where possible, where the items are listed in order of priority (from highest
to lowest priority).
•	 Must avoid retreating into enemy-controlled cities if possible,
but may retreat into an empty city if not. They do not gain
control of enemy controlled hexes they retreat through, but
they do gain control of the hex in which they end their retreat.
•	 Must end their retreat in supply if possible.
•	 Axis units may not retreat into a hex containing an Inactive
Partisan marker if any other retreat route is available. Axis
units which are forced to retreat into a hex with an Inactive
Partisan marker stop their retreat in that hex.
11.4.5	 If defending units retreat into a hex which is attacked
later in the same Action Round, the units which already retreated
do not add their Combat Strength to the Combat against this
hex. In addition, if any Loss Number, asterisked or otherwise, is
achieved, the already retreated units are immediately eliminated
and do not count towards fulfilling the Loss Number.
11.4.6	 Units with a movement factor of 0 are eliminated if they
are forced to retreat.
11.4.7	 Attacking units never retreat.

11.5	 ADVANCE
11.5.1	 Any remaining attacking units may advance into the
defending hex, regardless of enemy ZOCs, if the defending units
retreat or are completely eliminated, provided the following
restrictions are followed:
•	 Stacking limits are obeyed.
•	 The attacking units do not advance into a hex from which they
cannot trace a line of supply.
11.5.2	 If the Attacker advances a Soviet Tank or Guard SCU or
a German Panzer Corps SCU, he may place a Blitz marker in the
hex provided this is not prohibited by the type of terrain in that
hex (see 12.1.4 and Terrain Effects Chart). In this case the attacker
may advance units without regard to stacking limits, since stacking will not be checked here until exploitation is complete (see
9.1.4). The Attacker must do so before executing the next attack
or the opportunity to place the Blitz marker is lost. Exception:
The Axis player may place only one Blitz marker in a hex east of
the Paulus Line per Action Round during Turns 1-3 (June 1941
through Fall 1941). (Note that Axis exploitation is prohibited in
Winter 1942, due to the special effects of that winter turn (see
15.1.2), and in the Caucasus (see 12.1.3).) Note that no Blitz
markers may be placed in a 0 OPS round.

•	 May not end their retreat adjacent to the original defending
hex if retreating two hexes.
•	 May not end their retreat over-stacked, but may retreat through
a hex in violation of the stacking limits. In cases where
the Defender has no other route, they would choose which
retreating units would be able to stack within limits and which
will be eliminated.
© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

15

12.2.3	 During Turns 1-4 (June 1941 through Winter 1942), all
German Panzer Corps that begin their exploitation in a hex east
of the Paulus Line will have a movement allowance of 4, due
to rule 10.1.5; as such, their maximum Exploitation movement
will be two hexes. (Note that placement of an Axis Blitz marker
is prohibited during Winter 1942 anyway, due to the effects of
the Russian Winter – see 15.1.2)
12.2.4	 Exploiting units may ignore enemy ZOC.
12.2.5	 Exploiting units must halt upon entering a swamp,
forest, rough, desert or mountain hex. Exploiting units must
also stop if they cross the Kerch Strait. Exception: Non-swamp
terrain has no effect on Axis units Exploiting during Turn 1 (see
4.4.6). Events may cancel terrain effects for Exploitation. Note
that units adjacent to a Blitz marker are free to exploit regardless
of the terrain type of the hex they initially occupy.

12.0	 EXPLOITATION
12.1	 ELIGIBILITY
12.1.1	 Soviet Tank, Guard Tank and Guard Cavalry units (but
not Mechanized units) and German Panzer Corps SCUs are the
only units which may Exploit. Soviet Mech units may exploit
after playing the Operation Uranus Event.
12.1.2	 A unit must be in Full Supply to Exploit (although it
may move to an out of supply position during exploitation).
12.1.3	 Axis units in the Caucasus Zone may not Exploit. Neither may Axis units Exploit into the Causasus Zone. Reminder:
Soviet units may not exploit on turns in which no Lend Lease
Banked OPS were received.
Design Note: The Axis logistical capacity was stretched to its
limits in the vast, relatively undeveloped landmass of the Soviet
Union. Even after the Germans had improved their logistical
infrastructure for operations east of the Dnepr after Barbarossa,
they still lacked the capacity to operate at full effectiveness in
the Caucasus.

12.1.4	 A unit must occupy, or be adjacent to a hex with a Blitz
marker in order to Exploit. It need not have been involved in the
combat that led to the placement of the Blitz marker, nor is it
required to enter the Blitz-marked hex. It may not have already
exploited in that round (i.e., only 1 exploitation is allowed per
unit, per round).

12.2	 PROCEDURE
12.2.1	 Exploitation takes place after all combats, advances and
retreats for that Action Round have been completed.

13.0	 SUPPLY
13.1	 GENERAL RULES
13.1.1	 Units must be in supply to perform most actions. Supply
is determined at the following times only:
•	 For the active player: at the beginning of each Action Round
and during the Attrition Phase.
•	 For the non-active player: at the instant of combat. (Supply is
only checked for those units that are involved in a combat.)
13.1.2	 Supply Status is measured by the distance a unit is from
a friendly supply source. To be in full supply, units must trace
a supply path of four hexes or less to a friendly supply source
hex, or to a rail line and then along the rail line to a friendly
supply source hex. Alternately units may trace up to four hexes
to a friendly port, provided the player controls at least one other
port on that Sea (Baltic or Black Sea/Sea of Azov only) and a
line of supply can be traced from that other port (as if it were
itself a unit). Only one such port-to-port link may be included
in a supply path for any given unit.
13.1.3	 Units may never trace supply through enemy units,
enemy-controlled Fortresses, Festungs, Trenches, Cities, Oil
hexes or Victory Point hexes, or Active enemy Partisans, unnegated enemy ZOCs, or across impassable hexsides.
13.1.4	 Note that units using the Soviet Black Sea, Black Death
Event are always in supply in a coastal hex as long as the Soviets
control one port on the Black Sea (see 7.5.4).

12.2.2	 Exploiting units may move up to half their Movement
Allowance in hexes (not Movement Points), rounding up. For
example, a unit with a MA of 5 would be able to exploit up
to three hexes.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

16

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

13.2	 SUPPLY SOURCES
13.2.1	 The supply sources for German units and for the Vlassov
unit are the West map edge rail hexes and the USIR (Upper Silesian Industrial Region, marked on the map). The West map edge
starts at 1316 and runs along the west edge of the board to hex
1431 (inclusive). Romanian units must trace supply to Bucharest.
Hungarian and Italian units must trace supply to Buda.
13.2.2	 The supply sources for Soviet units are the East map
edge rail hexes.
13.2.3	 Soviet units may also use Baku as a full supply source
if at least one other Caspian Sea port is also Soviet controlled
and can itself trace a line of supply. If no other Caspian Sea port
satisfies these conditions, Baku provides supply for the purpose
of defense and attrition only (this also means that other Sovietcontrolled ports, cities, etc. that can trace a supply path to Baku
will not change control during the Attrition Phase).

14.0	 REPLACEMENTS
14.1	 GENERAL RULES
14.1.1	 During the Replacement Phase, each nation
can spend the number of Replacement Points (RPs)
recorded on the General Records Track by the nation’s
RP marker (see 7.4).

13.2.4	 Fortresses/festungs provide fortress supply,
i.e., supply for purposes of defense and attrition
(only), to units in the same hex.

13.3	 OUT OF SUPPLY (OOS)
PENALTIES
13.3.1	 OOS units have their Movement Allowance
reduced to 2 (if it was 3 or more).
13.3.2	 OOS units may not use Strategic Movement (by rail
or sea).
13.3.3	 OOS units may not entrench but they do receive the
benefits of existing trenches in their hex.
13.3.4	 If all units of one player involved in a combat are
OOS, those units may not receive the benefit of any Combat
Event Cards.
13.3.5	 If any units involved in a combat are OOS, units belonging to that side have their fire shifted one column to the left
when attacking or defending.
13.3.6	 OOS units have no Zone of Control.
13.3.7	 OOS units may not Exploit.
13.3.8	 Units which are OOS during their side’s Attrition Phase
are eliminated. Both player’s SCUs and Soviet LCUs that are
eliminated are placed in the Eliminated Units box and are available to be replaced immediately. Axis LCUs that are eliminated
are placed on the Turn Record Track three turns later. When the
Turn marker advances into a space that contains Axis LCUs, they
are placed in the Eliminated Units box and may now be replaced.
13.3.9	 During the Attrition Phase, any friendly controlled
City, Port, Oil, or Victory Point hex which does not contain an
undestroyed friendly Fortress or Festung, and which if it were
a friendly combat unit would be eliminated for being OOS,
becomes enemy controlled.

14.1.2	 RPs can be spent to replace steps for on-map units that
are not marked OOS, or they may be used to recreate units in
the Eliminated Units box. The Axis player may also spend RPs
to replace units currently in the Other Fronts box.
14.1.3	 It costs 1/2 RP to replace or recreate an SCU step. It
costs 1 RP to replace or recreate an LCU step.
14.1.4	 Recreated LCUs and SCUs may be placed in their home
country as if they were Reinforcements (see 7.5.2).
14.1.5	 RPs not spent during a Replacement Phase are lost.
They may not be saved for use in a future turn.
14.1.6	 Combat unit steps marked with an asterisk on the left
side of the counter may not be replaced; e.g., German Armies
may be replaced from 2-3 to 3-3, or 3-3 to 4-3 (in which case the
unit is replaced by its stronger counter), but may not be replaced
back to Full strength (i.e., 5-3) since this final step is marked as
non-replaceable.
14.1.7	 Axis cards award three types of RP points. “GE”, “PZ”
and “AX”. GE RPs are used to replace non-PZ GE units (only).
PZ RPs are used to replace GE PZ units (only). AX RPs are used
to replace non-German Axis units (only).

14.2	 SPECIAL RULES
14.2.1	 The Soviet Southwest Front initial unit is replaced by the
weaker SW Front in the Eliminated Units box when eliminated.
14.2.2	 The Axis player may not replace German Panzer SCU
steps if the Upper Silesian Industrial Region (USIR) hex is under
Soviet control.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

17

16.0	 SPECIAL UNITS
16.1	 PARTISANS
16.1.1	 Only the Soviet player may place Partisan
markers. Partisans may only be placed in the Soviet
Union, (Exception: the Warsaw Uprising Event) and
may only be placed after the Partisan Formation Event
has been played. Partisans may not be placed in the Baltic States.

15.0	 WEATHER
15.1	 GENERAL RULES
15.1.1	 Rasputitsa. Players may not play cards for OPS, or
take a 0 OPS round in which units are moved and/or combat is
conducted, during the first round of Fall turns and the first two
rounds of Spring Turns. Neither do they receive any OPS that
they would ordinarily receive from Events, nor may they conduct
combat if the effects of a card Event would normally allow it
(i.e., the Soviet Zhukov event). However, players may take a 0
OPS round in which they discard a card and draw a replacement
for it, but note that in this instance the Consecutive OPS marker
is not reset, contrary to the usual rule (see 7.2.6). This means
that the Consecutive OPS count is never reset during Rasputitsa
rounds (it remains where it was when Rasputitsa started).
Design Note: Rasputitsa, or “quagmire season”, occurs biannually as the roads become flooded due to melting snow in
Spring (the more severe season), and rain in Fall.

15.1.2	 Winter 1942. Unless the Winter Uniforms Event is in
effect, all Axis units shift 1 column to the left when firing on attack or defense, and receive no terrain benefits on defense apart
from trenches. No Axis Blitz markers may be placed. In addition
any Soviet attacks involving Soviet Shock Armies (SCUs) get a
1 column shift to the right. Note: The Soviet player may still not
place blitz markers in hexes that would ordinarily be considered
non-blitz terrain.

16.1.2	 Partisan placement costs 1 OPS. Spending 1 OPS allows the Soviet player to place two Partisan markers. Only 1
OPS may be used for Partisan placement per game turn. There
may never be more than six Partisan markers on the board at one
time, regardless of their Active or Inactive status (see 16.1.6).
16.1.3	 Partisans may only be placed in forest or swamp hexes.
The hex either must be one that would be OOS if a Soviet unit
were currently occupying it, OR the hex must be closer to an Axis
unit than to a Soviet unit (counting by number of hexes rather than
movement cost, but without crossing impassable hexsides). The
hex may not contain an Axis unit. Partisan counters are randomly
drawn and placed Inactive side up so that neither player initially
knows their strength.
16.1.4	 Inactive Partisans affect Axis rail movement (see 10.2.2),
and retreats (see 11.4). Axis units may stack in a hex with Inactive
Partisans, ignoring them. Inactive Partisans may not be attacked.
16.1.5	 Once placed, Inactive Partisans are removed in the following ways:
•	 By playing the Partisan Sweep Event
•	 If the Soviets have a supplied unit in the hex
•	 If the Soviet player chooses to remove them during the End
of Turn Phase.
16.1.6	 Inactive Partisan units become Active by playing certain
Events. Partisans may not be activated in a hex containing a
German or Axis unit. Active Partisan units are always In Supply, and act as normal Soviet combat units except that they may
not stack with other Soviet units nor participate in any attack or
defense with other Soviet units. If they are stacked with Soviet
units that retreat after combat, and Axis units advance into the
defender’s hex, the Partisans are eliminated. Once eliminated,
Active Partisans are permanently eliminated and are removed
from play (unlike Inactive Partisans, which may freely recycle).

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

18

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

16.2	 FORTRESSES
16.2.1	 Fortresses may be used only by the player
who owned them at the beginning of the game.

17.0	 OIL
17.1	 GENERAL RULES
17.1.1	 Control of Oil resource hexes affects the hand capacity
of both the Axis and Soviet players.

16.2.2	 If an enemy unit enters a hex with a Fortress
symbol, the Fortress is destroyed. Place a Fortress
Destroyed marker in the hex should this occur. The
hex is now treated as a City. Destroyed Fortresses
may not be replaced.

17.1.2	 There are four Oil resource hexes: 1428, 2433, 2835,
3138.

16.2.3	 The Soviet player may build one fortress during the
game by playing the Event The Volga Has Only One Bank. It
cannot be placed in a hex that is OOS.

17.1.4	 If the Axis controls no Oil hexes, the Axis player’s hand
size is reduced by one.

16.3	 FESTUNGS
16.3.1	 The Axis player may build Festungs after
playing the Festung Event. A player cannot have
more Festungs in play than are provided in the
counter mix.
16.3.2	 Festungs are built at a cost of 1 OPS per Festung. When
building a Festung place it in any non-enemy-controlled, insupply town or city hex which does not already contain a Festung.
16.3.3	 Once placed a Festung cannot be moved. A Festung is
eliminated when a Soviet unit enters the hex; return the Festung
marker to the counter mix for use in future turns.
16.3.4	 Units that start in or enter a Festung hex may never
leave the hex unless eliminated.
16.3.5	 Festungs provide supply for Defense and Attrition
purposes and cancel all retreats.

16.4	 STALIN
16.4.1	 Stalin is a normal SCU combat unit with no
attack or movement factor, or ZOC.
16.4.2	 Stalin must always be the last step eliminated in combat.

17.1.3	 In order to count as controlled for affecting hand size,
an Oil hex must be able to trace a supply line as if it were a unit.

17.1.5	 If the Axis player controls three or more Oil hexes, the
Axis player’s hand size is increased by one.
17.1.6	 If the Soviets control only 1 Oil hex, the Soviet player’s
hand size is decreased by one.
17.1.7	 If the Soviets control no Oil hexes, the Soviet player’s
hand size is decreased by two.

18.0	 BANKED OPS
18.1	 GENERAL RULES
18.1.1	 Banked OPS are Operation Points that a player may
hold and spend at some point during that turn. Specifically, they
may be spent in any action round in which the player has played
a card for OPS, played an event that grants OPS, or has elected
to take an automatic 0 OPS round in which units may move and/
or conduct combat.
18.1.2	 Banked OPS may not be saved from one turn to the
next. Any Banked OPS not spent by the the End of Turn Phase
are lost.
18.1.3	 Banked OPS, once recorded (use the Banked OPS
marker), are not lost until spent or until the end of the current
Turn.

16.4.3	 Stalin never retreats due to combat. Defending units
stacked with him do still retreat if on the losing side, but in such
a case Stalin must remain in place and Axis units may advance
into the hex and eliminate Stalin, thereby permanently removing
the Stalin counter from the game.

18.1.4	 A player may not Bank OPS except as noted below. A
player cannot choose to bank unspent OPS from the play of an
Operations Card.

16.4.4	 Stalin does not count for stacking purposes.

18.2.1	 Starting on Turn 2, the Axis player receives 1 Banked
OPS at the beginning of his first Action Round of each turn.

16.4.5	 Stalin may only be moved out of Moscow by rail Strategic Movement at the usual cost of 1 OPS. Stalin may be moved
back to a friendly controlled Moscow only by rail Strategic
Movement at a cost of 1 OPS.

18.2	 AXIS BANKED OPS

18.2.2	 The Axis stops receiving Banked OPS after the Hitler
Takes Command Event is played.

16.4.6	 Stalin may move only twice during the game; once out
of Moscow, and once back into Moscow.
16.4.7	 The Soviet player may receive Banked OPS (see 18.0)
only if Stalin is currently in Moscow.
© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

19

18.3	 SOVIET BANKED OPS
18.3.1	 The Soviet player may receive Banked OPS only if
Stalin is currently in Moscow.
18.3.2	 The Soviet player begins receiving Banked OPS on the
turn following play of the Lend-Lease Event.
18.3.3	 Once the precondition (Lend-Lease) is met, at the beginning of every turn, the Soviet player receives 2 Banked OPS
if Archangel is Soviet-controlled and/or 1 Banked OPS if he
Astrakhan is Soviet-controlled. Note: The Convoy PQ-17 Event
will temporarily nullify the Banked OPS received via Archangel.
18.3.4	 When the Stavka Event is played, the Soviet player immediately receives 3 Banked OPS, regardless of the requirements
in 18.3.2 and 18.3.3.

20.0	GERMAN MOBILE DEFENSE
20.1.1	 In any combat during non-Winter Turns from Game
Turn 1 (June 1941) to Game Turn 9 (Spring 1943) (inclusive),
whenever a German Army LCU unit is defending with one or
more Panzer SCUs in the hex, the Soviets shift one column to
the left and the Germans shift one column to the right when
resolving that combat.

21.0	 BIDDING

19.0	 NATIONAL RESTRICTIONS
19.1	 ROMANIAN UNITS
19.1.1	 Romanian units may never enter a hex in Hungary. If
forced to violate this rule, they are eliminated. No single combat
may involve both Romanian and Hungarian units.

19.2	 HUNGARIAN UNITS

Players who find the game unbalanced, or who are playing in a
tournament environment, may elect to bid for the right to play the
side of their preference. Bids will made in terms of a one-time
addition of automatic RPs to be spent from Turn 2 onwards by
the other side (players may receive at most 3 automatic RPs per
turn). Recall that the standard game includes 3 automatic RPs
for the Soviets, to be spent on Turns 2 and 3, so automatic RPs
received from bidding are applied cumulative with that. For
example, a bid of 2 to play the Axis would result in the Soviets
receiving their usual 3 RPs on Turns 2 and 3, followed by 2 more
on Turn 4. Whereas a bid of 8 to play the Soviets would result
in the Soviets receiving no automatic RPs and the Axis player
receiving 2 automatic RPs on Turn 2.

19.2.1	 Hungarian units may never enter a hex in Romania. If
forced to violate this rule, they are eliminated. No single combat
may involve both Hungarian and Romanian units.

19.3	 SURRENDER
19.3.1	 Axis minor countries (i.e., Romania and Hungary) surrender if their capital is enemy-occupied at the end of any Turn.
In such a case remove all units of that minor permanently from
the game (whether currently in play or not).

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

20

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

23.0	OPTIONAL RULES
23.1.1	 On Turn 1 (only), before cards are drawn, each player
may elect to give up 1 VP in order to take any one card of their
choice from the Blitz deck and place it in their hand. (i.e., if the
Axis player elects to do this the VP count is lowered by 1, whereas
if the Soviet player takes this option the VP count is raised by
1.) The player then shuffles the Blitz deck and draws five other
cards from that deck as normal in order to complete their hand
for Turn 1. The Axis player decides first.
Design Note: Players can use this rule if they would like to
add a degree of control over the strategic objectives of the
initial Barbarossa attack.

23.1.2	 Players who prefer to let fate decide the rate at which
Soviet reinforcements arrive in the early part of the war may
ignore rule 4.3.1 and instead shuffle the Soviet Blitz reinforcment
cards (card numbers 1-6) into the Blitz deck before drawing their
initial hand.
Design Note: Our experience is that the Soviet position will
be very poor unless two Reinforcement cards are played on
turn 2, so players should use this optional rule at their peril. It
is fun for players who like a wild ride, however!

22.0	TOURNAMENT SCENARIO
If players wish to play a shorter version of the game, the following tournament scenario is provided. The tournament scenario
begins on Turn 1 (June 1941) and ends at the completion of Turn
8 (Winter 1943), and is a good way to learn the game. Set-up is
identical to the Campaign game (see 25.0). All Automatic Victory
conditions apply (see 5.1.2 and 5.1.3). In the absence of an Automatic Victory, players count the number of Axis-controlled VP
spaces in the Soviet Union at the end of Turn 8: the Axis player
wins if they control 9 or more VP spaces; the Soviet player wins
if 8 or less VP spaces are controlled by the Axis. If the Soviet
Union has not played Industrial Evacuation as an event by the
end of this scenario, adjust the count of VP spaces 2 in favor of
the Axis. If the Axis have not played Hitler Takes Command as
an event by the end of this scenario, adjust the VP space count
2 in favor of the Soviets.

23.1.3	 Players who would like a little more control
over getting key trenches built may try the following
rule: a trench can be built in the usual way or, at the
cost of an additional OPS, the player may subtract
3 from a trench die-roll. No more than one additional OPS per
trench attempt.
23.1.4	 Some playtesters felt that it would be more realistic
to allow the Phasing player to check the supply status of OOS
units at the end of each of the player’s rounds, thereby allowing
those units to be placed back in supply if appropriate. Players
who agree with this view can choose to add a supply check for
OOS units only, for units belonging to the phasing player at the
end of their part of the Action Round

Design Note: This represents a substantially better than
historical performance by the Axis. It reflects our belief that
the Axis player can exceed historical performance given the
knowledge that the ‘game’ will end at the end of 1942.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

21

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

25.0	UNIT SET-UP
24.0	EASILY FORGOTTEN RULES

25.1	 SOVIETS

This section contains a reminder of rules that we found were
most easily forgotten during playtesting.

Southwest Front* [1724] * Stronger 5-3 unit
16M Corps [1625]	
West Front [1721]
28R Corps [1722]	
4M Corps [1723]
8M Corps [1624]	
South Front [1726]
6M Corps [1821]	
5R Corps [1823]
15M Corps [1824]	
5M Corps [1826]
18M Corps [1827]	
Maritime Army [1829]
12M Corps [1918]	
Northwest Front [2118]
3M Corps [1920]	
22M Corps [1924]
13R Army [2022]	
Central Front [2123]
21R Army [2123]	
22R Army [2320]
Leningrad Front [2517]	
10M Corps [2517]
Trans-Caucasus Front [2532]	
Reserve Front [2722]
7M Corps [2722]	
20R Army [2722]
Stalin [2722]

•	 Rasputitsa occurs on first round of Fall Turns and first two
rounds of Spring turns. Consecutive OPS count is never reset
during Rasputitsa rounds (see 15.1.1).
•	 All Axis units units have –1 MP East of the Paulus Line during
Turns 1-4 (see 10.1.5), as well as a 1 column shift left when
attacking if fully supplied, and only 1 exploitation is allowed
(which can be at most 2 hexes long) (see 11.2.1).
•	 No Blitzing is allowed in a 0 OPS round (see 11.5.2).
•	 Soviet units may not blitz if no Lend Lease received that turn
(see 11.2.1).
•	 First loss on offense must be taken by mechanized unit (see
11.3.3).
•	 If three or more Panzers are stacked together and participating
in the same combat, they automatically fire on the LCU column
(see 11.2.1).
•	 If all of a player’s units in a combat are OOS, that player may
not play a CC in that combat (see 13.3.4).
•	 German Mobile Defense (see 20.0) applies up to Spring 1943
inclusive, but does not apply during Winter turns.
•	 Only one LCU may be involved in each combat for each player
(see 11.1.3).
•	 VPs are decreased by one at the end of each Spring and Summer
turn if the Axis event Hitler Takes Command has not been
played (see text of that card).
•	 Axis can play two replacement cards in Spring 1942 and 1943
only (see 7.4.3).
•	 Soviet units may not operate in Hungary or Romania in June
1941 (see 4.4.3 and 4.4.4).
•	 The Axis player may not replace German Panzer SCU steps
if the USIR is under Soviet control (see 14.2.2).

25.2	 AXIS
German Units
49 Mtn Corps [1424]	
17th Army [1523]	
46 Pz Corps [1622]	
47 Pz Corps [1622]	
6th Army [1623]	
3Pz Corps [1623]	
9th Army [1720]	
57 Pz Corps [1720].	
16th Army [1820]	
41 Pz Corps [1820]

11th Army [1527]
4th Army [1621]
24 Pz Corps [1622]
43 Corps [1622]
48 Pz Corps [1623]
14 Pz Corps [1623]
39 Pz Corps [1720]
18th Army [1819]
56 Pz Corps [1820]

Hungarian Units
3rd Army [1025]
Romanian Units
3rd Army [1627]	

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

4th Army [1629]

22

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

INDEX
0

E

0 Ops round. 7.2.6

Easily Forgotten Rules. 24.0
Events. 7.5

A

Exploitation. 12.0

Action phase. 7.2

	 Barbarossa effects. 4.4.6

Action round. 7.2.1

	 OOS restrictions. 13.3.7

Advance. 11.5

	 Procedure. 12.2

Attrition

	 Winter 1942 restrictions. 15.1.2

	 OOS effects. 13.3.8

F

Automatic victory. 5.1.2, 5.1.3

Festungs. 11.4.1, 16.3

B

	 Movement effects. 16.3.4

Baku

	 Supply effects. 16.3.5

	 Supply. 13.2.3

Fortress supply. 13.2.4

Banked OPS. 18.0

Fortified Zone. 8.2, 9.1.3

	 Hitler Takes Command effects. 18.2.2

Fortresses. 16.2

	 Lend Lease effects. 18.3.2

Full supply. 13.1.2

	 Stalin effects. 18.3.1

G

	 Stavka. 18.3.4
Barbarossa. 4.4

Game markers. 2.2.2

Bidding. 21.0

German mobile defense. 20.0

Blitz. 11.2.1 (step 9), 11.5.2, 12.1.4 (also see Exploitation)

C

H
Hand size. 7.6

Caucasus Zone. 12.1.3

	 Oil effects. 17.0

Combat. 11.0

Hex control. 3.0, 13.3.9

	 Combined attacks. 11.1.3

Hungarian units. 19.2

	 Geographic restrictions. 11.1.9
	 Losses. 11.3
	 Resolution. 11.2
	 Winter 1942 effects. 15.1.2
Combat Cards (CCs). 7.5.5
	 OOS restrictions. 13.3.4
Combat markers. 7.3.5
Combat resolution
	 OOS effects. 13.3.5
Consecutive OPS. 7.3.2

D
Discards. 7.6.2

I
Initial hand size. 4.3
Invasions. 7.5.4

L
Lend Lease. 18.3.2
	 Effects on blitz. 11.2.1 (step 9)

M
Map zones. 2.1
Move markers. 7.3.4
Movement. 10.0
	 Nationality restrictions. 19.0
	 OPS cost. 7.3.3

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

N

S

National restrictions. 19.0

Sea movement

Naval evacuation. 10.2.7

	 Soviet. 10.2.6

No retreat option. 11.4.3

Southwest Front. 11.3.6, 14.2.1

O
Oil. 17.0
Operations (OPS). 7.3
Ops
	 0 Ops round. 7.2.6
	 Banked. 18.0
	 Consecutive. 7.3.2
	 Other Fronts box. 3.0
Out of Supply (OOS) penalties. 13.3

P
Partisans. 10.1.6, 11.1.7, 16.1
	 Activating. 16.1.6
	 Elimination. 16.1.6
	 Removal. 16.1.5
Paulus Logistical Line
	 Combat effects. 11.2.1 (step 4)
	 Exploitation effects. 11.5.2, 12.2.3
	 Movement effects. 10.1.5

R
Rail movement. 10.2.2, 10.2.4
	 Partisan effects. 10.2.2
Rasputitsa. 15.1.1
Reinforcements. 7.5.2
Replacement
	 Eliminated units. 11.3.6
Replacement points (RPs). 7.4

Soviet attack restrictions. 4.4.7, 4.4.8
Soviet Mobilization. 4.5
Spring Thaw. See Rasputitsa
Stacking. 9.0
Stalin. 16.4
Stavka. 18.3.4
Strategic movement. 10.2
	 OOS restrictions. 13.3.2
	 Stalin. 16.4.5
Strategy cards. 2.3, 7.0
Supply. 13.0
	 Path. 13.1.2, 13.1.3
	 Wources. 13.2
	 When to determine. 13.1.1

T
Total War. 7.6.4
Tournament scenario. 22.0
Trenches. 10.3
	 OOS restrictions. 13.3.3

U
Units
	 LCU. 2.2.1
	 Non-replaceable. 2.2.1
	 SCU. 2.2.1
Upper Silesean Industrial Region (USIR). 14.2.2

V

Replacements. 14.0

Victory determination. 5.0

	 German Spring 1942 and 1943. 7.4.3

Volga crossing restrictions. 11.1.10

	 Special rules. 14.2
Retreat. 11.4
	 Failure to retreat. 11.4.4
	 Length of. 11.4.2
	 No retreat option. 11.4.3
	 Retreat path. 11.4.4
Romanian units. 19.1

W
Weather. 15.0
Winter 1942. 15.1.2

Z
Zones of Control (ZOC). 8.0

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

23

24

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

Card Clarifications
Soviet Cards:

Axis Cards:

#3 Soviet Reinforcements: This card refers
to the 1G, 2G and 3G Cavalry Corps. These
units have the following IDs: 1GC, 2GC and
3GC.

#9 Guderian: This affects any units that exploit
as a result of that combat, not just those that
actually attacked. (i.e., other adjacent exploitcapable units may also benefit from the effects
of the card.)

#9 Zhukov: This card can be used in the
round in which it is played, and every subsequent OPS round that turn. It allows you
to activate two adjacent hexes for a single
attack (subject to taking one extra step loss
each time).
#10 Black Sea, Black Death: The port restriction applies only to ports in the Black Sea
and Sea of Azov (i.e., not the Baltic).
#24 Katukov’s Tanks: The unit that takes the
loss is determined by the Soviet player.
#20 Airborne Corps: The placement of the
partisan does not have to obey the normal
partisan placement requirements. (e.g., the
unit can be placed outside the Soviet Union).
Errata: Furthermore, this partisan unit must
be placed in a clear hex.
#48 Maskirovka: The units may leave an enemy ZOC without paying an OPS (since this
is not happening in a movement phase). The
units may not end up over-stacked.

#11 Kampfgruppe: The last SCU step in the
hex has to be eliminated by the attack for the
effects of the card to take place.
#13 Dora: Playing Dora does not make it possible for the Axis to place a Blitz-marker in the
defending hex. If there is also a trench in the
hex, the Axis still get the benefits of that trench.
#19 Winter Uniforms: This card does not
negate the Soviet shock troop right shift when
attacking during Winter 1942.
#54 Naval Evacuation: Yes, the ports do have
to be on the same sea.
#26 German Reinforcements: The ABT. is not
a separate unit (i.e., there are three reinforcing
units in total). There should be no comma following “ABT”.
#33 Backhand Blow: The Axis player must
attack at least one of the Soviet units that advanced that round (i.e., he does not have too
attack all of them).
#50 Sleighride: After Axis units retreat, since
the attack is canceled, the attackers may not
advance.

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

25

Stalin’s War Living Rules Manual

Sequence of Play (6.0)
A. ACTION PHASE

D. DRAW STRATEGY CARD PHASE

Each Action Phase is divided into five identical Action
Rounds. Each Action Round consists of an Axis Action
Round followed by a Soviet Action Round. The Axis
Action Round allows the Axis player to take one action;
The Soviet Action Round allows the Soviet player to
take one action.

Players may discard any Strategy Cards remaining in
their hand (see 7.6.2). The Soviet player decides first.
Each player then draws cards from their Draw Pile to
bring their hand to their current hand size (see 7.1.3).
Each player begins with a hand size of 6 cards. Changes
in control of Oil hexes and the effects of certain Event
Cards may change a player’s hand size.

B. ATTRITION PHASE

E. END OF TURN PHASE

The Axis Attrition Segment takes place immediately
upon the conclusion of the 5th Axis Action Round. The
Soviet Attrition Segment takes place immediately upon
the conclusion of the 5th Soviet Action Round. During
the Attrition segments OOS units belonging to the active player are eliminated and OOS friendly-controlled
Cities, Ports, Oil, and Victory Point hexes become
controlled by the enemy (see 13.3.9).

•	 The Axis player may remove friendly Trench markers
from the map
•	 The Soviet player may remove friendly Trench
markers from the map
•	 Any remaining Banked OPS are lost (set the markers
for both players to zero).
If the war has not ended due to Automatic Victory or
reaching Turn 18 (Summer 1945), advance the Turn
marker to the next space on the Turn Record Track and
begin the Sequence of Play again with the first Axis
Action Round.

C. REPLACEMENT PHASE
SOVIET SEGMENT: The Soviet player spends any
Replacement Points (RPs) accumulated through play of
RP Cards this turn (see 7.4). Any RPs not spent are lost.
AXIS SEGMENT: The Axis player spends any Replacement Points accumulated through play of Cards
for RPs this turn (see 7.4). Any RPs not spent are lost.

Unit Counter Symbology

	
	

Corps	
XXX	

Size:
Army	
XXXX	

Front
XXXXX

	

	

	
	 CSIR	
	

Type:
Infantry	
Mech	

Armor	

	

© 2010 GMT Games, LLC

	

	

Shock Inf.	 Maritime	
	

Cavalry

	

Partisan	
	

Mountain

</rulebook>
			
						                           
						               													<description>From Ted Raicer the award-winning designer of Paths of Glory and World War II: Barbarossa to Berlin comes a fresh new look at the most titanic and brutal land campaign ever waged, the war between Hitler's Germany and Stalin's Soviet Union.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Stalin's War is a unique card-driven, hex-based game, a combination that allows players to experience a broad range of strategic and tactical options as they maneuver their forces across a large hex map that stretches from Berlin to the Urals.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Stalin's War allows player to recreate WWII's greatest battles of encirclement as Axis Armies and Panzer Corps clash with Soviet Fronts and Armies on a front a thousand miles wide. Simple but effective rules allow you to use your mechanized forces to blitz the enemy's front line and exploit deep into your opponent's rear. Can you as the Soviets survive the slashing Panzer attacks of Operation Barbarossa and Case Blue in 1941 and 1942? Can you as the Axis player stand against the crushing Soviet Deep Battle operations that destroyed Army Group Center in 1944? Stalin's War will test both player's operational skills to the limit.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;But there is more to Stalin's War than directing your forces on the map. Both sides have their own deck of 55 cards, needed to launch offensive operations, mobilize their forces, replace losses, introduce new weapons, and deal with the larger strategic context of a World at War. Card Events include combat leaders, weapons (from German Tiger Tanks to patriotic Soviet mice nibbling the electrical wiring of the panzers), the 1944 Warsaw Uprising, Manstein's Backhand Blow, Stalin's and Hitler's meddling, the Battle of the Bulge, and much more.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Stalin's War allows players to combine the best of WWII operational play with the strategic depth and tactical chrome of a card driven design. A genuine new look the the most important theater of WWII, this is a game you want to play again and again.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;(Taken from rear of the game box)&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Scenarios &amp;#10;In addition to the full campaign game, a shorter tournament scenario is included that comprises 8 game turns and covers the time period of June 1941 through to Winter 1943.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2010" />
						               				<minplayers value="2" />
						               				<maxplayers value="2" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="7">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="4" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="2" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="7" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="3" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="240" />
						               				<minplaytime value="240" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="240" />
						               				<minage value="12" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="5">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="4">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="1" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="3" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1019" value="Wargame" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1049" value="World War II" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2018" value="Campaign / Battle Card Driven" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2072" value="Dice Rolling" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2676" value="Grid Movement" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2040" value="Hand Management" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2026" value="Hexagon Grid" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2070" value="Simulation" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="18581" value="Country: Soviet Union" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="61979" value="Players: Two Player Only Games" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="484" value="Ted Raicer" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="71" value="Rodger B. MacGowan" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="140" value="Mark Simonitch" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="52" value="GMT Games" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="321" />
			<average value="6.82012" />
			<bayesaverage value="5.69364" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="5226" bayesaverage="5.69364" />
																				<rank type="family" id="4664" name="wargames" friendlyname="War Game Rank" value="759" bayesaverage="6.25562" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.57277" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="930" />
			<trading value="57" />
			<wanting value="20" />
			<wishing value="83" />
			<numcomments value="164" />
			<numweights value="49" />
			<averageweight value="3.1429" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>