<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="125153">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/ie1GSt1XV04sXQXt-3O1UQ__thumb/img/O0H84AvXp139U865gRLGiAo9-gA=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic2503200.png</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/ie1GSt1XV04sXQXt-3O1UQ__original/img/59dZRZePEgtcupkRSA2zohZuHpM=/0x0/filters:format(png)/pic2503200.png</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="5" value="The Gallerist" />
			
						                               				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="ギャラリスト" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="藝廊經紀人" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="갤러리스트" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="더 갤러리스트" />
				<rulebook>THE GALLERIST
A GAME BY VITAL LACERDA

1 to 4 Players

The age of Art and capitalism has created a need for a new occupation The Gallerist. Combining the elements of an Art dealer, museum curator,
and Artists’ manager, you are about to take on that job! You will promote
and nurture Artists; buy, display, and sell their Art; and build and exert
your international Influence. As a result, you will achieve the respect

30 MIN per Player

needed to draw visitors to your Gallery from all over the world. There’s
a lot of work to be done, but don’t worry, you can hire assistants to help
you. There’s a long queue of unemployed Art aficionados lined up, hoping
to work with someone of your stature. Build your fortune by running the
most lucrative Gallery ever.

Game Components

Table of contents
Game Components	

1

The Gallerist Setup	

2-3

Overview of the Game	

4

•	 A brief explanation of the four Locations
1x Game board

4x Art Gallery (Player boards)

Starting Player marker
and 4x Influence markers

4x Gallerist pawns

•	 Visitors, Galleries, Plaza and Lobbies
•	 Fame, Influence, Money
Gameplay	5
End of Game
Location Actions
Executive Actions
•	 Moving Visitors by offering tickets

32x Work of Art tiles

16× Artist tiles

16x Signature tokens

10x Artist bonus tiles

•	 Using a bonus from a contract card
Kicked-Out Actions	

6

Artists Colony	7
•	 Discover an Artist
•	 Buy &amp; exhibit a Work of Art
14x

Sales Office	

12x

14x
60x Tickets

9

•	 Sign a contract

40x Visitors

1x Visitors bag

40x Assistants in Player colors

•	 Sell a Work of Art
Media Center	

11

•	 Hire Assistants
•	 Promote Artist
International Market	12
•	 Take a Reputation tile
3x Easels

•	 Make an offer for Art of International Renown

8x Fame markers
and 8x Celebrity tiles

20x Reputation tiles

20x Promotion tokens

Influence	13
Tickets, Fame and Celebrity Status	

4x Art Dealer cards

4x Curator cards

20x Contract cards

Intermediate Scoring	
End Game Scoring	
Solitaire Play	

front

back

front

back

front

back

15x, 15x, 12x, 10x, 8x, 4x

Example of play	
Money (1,2,5,10,50,100)

14
14
15-16
16
17-18

Artist Participation	

19

Reputation tiles &amp; Credits	

20

1

THE GALLERIST SETUP

4-Player GAME

Endgame Scoring track

3
Yellow’s Gallery

Purple’s Gallery

4
12

7

10
13

14

5
8

11

6
Blue’s Gallery

Orange’s Gallery

2
9

14

1
d

a

c

e

With the exception of money, all other components are limited. If they run out, you cannot take any more.
2

b

SETUP
•	Place the Game board in the middle of the table.
•	Place the Player boards around the Game board
nearest to the Gallery of the appropriate color.
Place Visitors in the cloth bag: For 4-Players,
use all Visitors. For 3-Players, remove 2 of each
type and place them in the box. For 2-Players and
Solitaire games, remove 4 of each type.

Set up the game board:
1.	 Place each Player’s Influence marker (disc) on
the “10” space of the Influence Track.

Place the first drawn blue Artist tile face-up, and
mark its initial Fame with a white cube. Initial
Fame value is printed on both sides of the tile.
5.	 All other Artists begin the game face-down.
Shuffle the Artist bonus tiles and place one at
random on each Artist. Return any remaining
Artist bonus tiles back to the box. Place one
white Visitor (Collector) from the bag on each
red Artist tile.

12.	Place 4 random Visitors from the bag in the Plaza
and 1 random Visitor in each Player’s Lobby.

12

6.	 Place both of the Artist’s Signature tokens next
to all the corresponding Artist tiles.

6

5

2.	 In the box office, place a number of tickets of
each color depending on the number of Players.
20 tickets for a 4-Player game, 15 for 3-Players,
and 10 for 2-Players and Solitaire Games. Place
any remaining tickets back in the game box.

The Lobby is between a Player’s Gallery and the Plaza.
Bonus tiles, Visitors and Signature tokens

Sales office:
3.	 Shuffle the contract cards, and place them
face-down on the leftmost space. Draw the top
4 cards and place them face-up on the four
contract display spaces.

7.	 For each Art form, shuffle the respective Works
of Art, and place each stack face-up on the
space next to the appropriate studio. Take the
top tile from each of the stacks and set them
aside for now.

Artist Colony:

8.	 Place a number of random Visitors from the
bag on each topmost Work of Art equal to the
number of tickets depicted on the tile.

4.	 Shuffle all 16 Artist tiles and place them one
at a time onto the spaces on the board which
match the color and Art form of the Artist.

easels beside the board. Use three easels for
a 4-Player game, two easels for 3-Players and
one easel in the 2-Player and Solitaire game.
These are Works of International renown.
Put any remaining easels back in the box
along with the remaining Work(s) of Art.

8

13.	Randomly choose 4 of the remaining
Reputation tiles and place one of them at
random face-up next to each Location on the
game board.
14.	Choose a start Player at random and give
him the Starting Player marker. In reverse
Player order, each Player chooses one of the
Locations, places his Gallerist there and takes
the Reputation tile from that Location. Place
remaining tiles back in the box.
•	Place everything else near the game board.

Each Player chooses a color and sets up his
Gallery as follows:
a.	 Place 8 Assistants on the spaces of the
unemployment queue.

4
Each Art form has 1 blue Artist and 1 red Artist

If you draw an Artist whose space is already
occupied, return it to the game box. Repeat the
process until all spaces are filled and then return
any remaining Artists to the game box. There must
be one blue and one red Artist for each Art form.

4

The brown space is the initial Fame value - mark it

The color of the tickets doesn’t matter - only the number

Media:
9.	 Stack each of the Promotion tokens on the
corresponding numbered spaces.

International Market:
10.	Randomly choose 12 Reputation tiles and
place one face up on each space of the upper
4 rows of the international Market. In the
Solitaire or 2-Player games, choose only 8 tiles
and only cover the upper 4 rows of the 1st and
the 3rd columns.
11.	Shuffle the 4 Works of Art you previously set
aside and place one at random on each of the

b.	 Place the remaining 2 Assistants at desks in
the office.
c.	 Place the Reputation tile taken earlier on the
3rd Art space of his Player board.
d.	 Take 10 money from the bank.
e.	 Shuffle the Art Dealer cards and deal one at
random to each Player. Do the same with the
Curator cards. These cards are kept secret
from other players.

a

b

c

Player board setup

3

Overview of the Game
In The Gallerist, each Player tries to gain as
much money as possible, and thus win the game.
Over the course of the game, Players will discover
Artists, commission them to create a Work of Art,
and invest in them to make them more famous.
They will buy Works of Art, exhibit them in their
Gallery, and possibly sell them. They will hire
Assistants and use them in the International
Market to increase Reputation and bid for
auctioned Art. At the end of the game, Players
also score additional money for completing the
goals of their Curator and Art Dealer cards.

Sales Office
International Market

Artists Colony

Media Center

Players take turns in clockwise order. On a
Player’s turn, they choose one of the four
Locations on the game board and then choose
one of the two available actions at that Location.
There are also Executive Actions and Kicked-Out
Actions that are explained later.
The four Locations in the game

A brief explanation of the four Locations:
Artists Colony: Players can either
discover a new Artist, or buy a Work
of Art from an already discovered
Artist. Each Artist may only have two
unsold Works of Art at any time, represented by
their Signature tokens. The cost of a Work of Art is
based on how famous the Artist is (tracked on the
Artist tile by the Fame cube), and once bought,
the Work of Art is displayed in the Player’s Gallery.

Sales Office: A Player can take a
contract card from the available
display or, if he already has the correct
contract, sell one of his Works of Art.
The sales value of the work is based on the Fame
level of the Artist who created it.
Media Center: A Player can hire extra
Assistants at this Location, or promote
an Artist in the media, which will
increase their Fame as well as reward
the Player an additional bonus.

Visitors, Galleries, Plaza and Lobbies
An important part of the game are Visitors, which
come in 3 different types representing Investors
(brown), VIPs (pink) and Collectors (white).
A Player may move these Visitors on the board
by spending tickets of the appropriate color, with
Galleries

Plaza

Lobbies

The Plaza, Lobbies and Galleries

4

International Market: At this Location,
a Player may send one of their
Assistants onto one of the spaces of
the International Market table and
gain Influence depending upon which column they
are placed. The upper part of the table increases
the Player’s Reputation and gives them an end
game goal tile; the bottom part of the table is
where the Players make an offer on the auctioned
Works of Art (displayed on the easels). This
auction happens at the end of the game.

Influence

the aim of getting Visitors into his Gallery. Once
there, these Visitors may earn a Player money and
Influence, and help to increase an Artist’s Fame.

Fame
Each discovered Artist (face-up) has
a marker to represent their current
Fame. This determines the sale
price of any Work of Art they create, so it is a good
idea to buy a Work of Art from them when they
have just been discovered, and sell it for a profit
when they are more famous! The Fame of an Artist
is increased when they create a Work of Art, and
when they are promoted in the media.

Each Player marks their current
Influence on the track on the game
board. Influence is spent when
promoting an Artist, taking a Location action as
part of a Kicked-Out Action, and to gain additional
money or Fame. Influence is gained whenever a
Player takes an action with this icon, and executing
a Location action at the International Market.

Money
Money is a vital resource in the
game, and is used for buying Works
of Art, hiring Assistants and bidding
on auctions in the International Market. Money
is gained whenever a Player sells a Work of Art or
takes an action with this icon.

Gameplay

Location Actions

The game is played over a series of rounds, beginning
with the Start Player. On a Player’s turn, they move
their Gallerist to one of the four Locations on the
game board, and perform one of the two actions at
that Location. Additionally, a Player may also take
one of two ‘Executive Actions’ on their turn, either
before or after performing their Location action.

On a Player’s turn, if the Player is at a Location
(has not been Kicked-Out), they MUST MOVE their
Gallerist pawn to a different Location.
Additionally, if a Player moves from one Location
to another, he may leave behind one of his
Assistants on the space the Gallerist pawn is

If a Player moves his Gallerist to a Location where
another Player is present, that Player is Kicked-Out
and will get to perform a special ‘Kicked-Out Action’
after the current Player has finished their turn.

Yellow was Kicked-Out

Because of the ’Kicked-Out Action’, Players may
take extra moves outside of their normal turn.
Remember that the next Player to take their turn
is always the Player to the left of the Player who
performed the last Location action.
This dynamic element of the game really sets it
apart, and keeps everyone thinking.

Once at the new Location, the Player MUST select
one of the two Location actions possible (see p. 7).
Example:
Orange is taking his turn. His Gallerist is currently
at the International Market. He chooses to move to
the Media Center. He decides to leave an Assistant
behind at the International Market, so he picks
up one Assistant from his office and places it on
the International Market Location. If he had an
Assistant in another Location, he could have moved
that one instead. Finally, he performs one of the
two possible actions at the Media Center.

Location Space

Kicked-Out Space

moving from. This Assistant may come from either
an office desk, or another Location. By leaving an
Assistant behind, the Player will gain a Kicked-Out
action if their Assistant is displaced.

Leaving one Assistant behind

Executive Actions
On a Player’s turn, in addition to taking a Location Action, he may also take an Executive Action. If he
does so, this action is performed either before or after the Location Action, at the choice of the Player.

There are 2 possible Executive Actions
•	 Moving Visitors by offering tickets.

•	 Using a bonus from a contract card.

•	 Moving Visitors by offering tickets

End of Game
The sequence of play continues until at least two
of the following conditions are met:
•	 The box office is empty of tickets.
•	 Two or more Artists have become Celebrities.
•	 The bag is empty of Visitors.

As soon as two or more of these conditions occur,
the round continues until the last player finishes
his turn. Then, beginning with the Starting Player,
in turn order, each player gets one more turn
as normal with the exception that if a Player is
Kicked-Out, he simply sends his Gallerist home
and does not perform a Kicked-Out action.
Final scoring then takes place (see p. 15) and the
Player with the most money wins the game.

End Game conditions - 2 out of 3

Gallerists offer tickets to bring important Visitors into their galleries

A Player may discard any number of tickets. Each
ticket discarded allows the Player to move one
Visitor of the same color one space on the board
TOWARDS his own Gallery.
A single Visitor may be moved more than once as
part of the same action.
Discarded tickets are placed on a discard pile to
the side of the game board (not returned to the
box office).

A Visitor at the Plaza or in any Lobby may be
moved by any Player, but once a Visitor enters
a Gallery, it cannot be moved out by discarding
tickets.
Example:
Move a Visitor from the Plaza to his Lobby (not vice
versa), move from his Lobby to his Gallery (not vice
versa), or even move from another Player’s Lobby to
the Plaza.

Collectors Rule:
A Player is limited on the
number of Collectors he can
have in his Gallery at any
one time. This is equal to
1 more than the number of
Works of Art the Player has
sold.
Look for this symbol in each player’s Gallery on the
game board.

Moving Visitors with an Executive Action

5

•	 Using a bonus from a contract card
Having contracts has many advantages

During the game, Players may take contract cards,
which are placed on their Player board. The bonus
shown on the card can be used by the Player
taking an Executive Action to place one of his
Assistants (from either his office or a Location)
onto the card. This bonus may only be taken once,
and the Assistant used remains on the card to
represent this.
Later in the game, if the contract card is used to
sell a Work of Art, the Assistant is returned to the
Player’s office and the contract card is flipped
over, depicting a new bonus that may be taken
by performing another Executive Action. See
description of the bonuses on the Player aid.

Example:
Blue has a contract card on his Player board.
He may use an Executive Action to place one of
his Assistants onto the card to receive the bonus
shown. (The image to the right shows the bonus of
drawing a new contract card).
The Player immediately takes the bonus printed on the card

Example:
Blue completes the contract card in the previous
example and the Assistant returns to his office. He
may then use an Executive Action later in the game
to place one of his Assistants back onto the card,
but this time receiving the top bonus on the back of
the card.

The Player immediately gets the Influence bonus

Kicked-Out Actions
If a Player moves their Gallerist pawn to a Location where there is already another Gallerist pawn or
Assistant, that piece is ‘Kicked-Out’ and moved to the black space in front of the Location space. After
the active Player finishes their turn, the Player who was Kicked-Out may take a special ‘Kicked-Out
Action’, and then the Gallerist pawn / Assistant returns home (see Going Home - bellow).
Kick out your own Assistant:
It is possible for a Player to kick out his own Assistant. In this case, the Assistant returns home, but the Player
does not get to perform a Kicked-Out Action.

The possible Kicked-Out Actions are:
•	 Reducing Influence back to the previous Fame
icon to perform one of the Location’s Actions.

Kicked-Out Space

Location Space
Yellow’s Assistant was Kicked-Out

•	 Take an Executive Action (see above).

Taking a Kicked-Out Action is optional, but the Gallerist pawn or Assistant still goes home even if no
action is performed.

Going Home
Whenever a Gallerist pawn is sent
home after being Kicked-Out from
a Location, it is returned back to
his Gallery on the game board.
Whenever an Assistant returns home, it is placed
on an empty desk in the Player’s
office. If all four desks are occupied,
the Assistant is removed from the
game and returned to the box.
6

Example:
Example: It is Purple’s turn. She moves to the
Sales Office, where the Yellow Player has an
Assistant. Yellow’s Assistant is moved to the black
space in front of the Location space.

Yellow reduces her Influence to take a Location action

After Purple has performed her Location Action,
Yellow may use her Kicked-Out Action to also
perform the Location Action (moving her Influence
marker back to the previous Fame icon).
The Assistant returns home.

Yellow’s Assistant returns home

Locations

Artists Colony
Action: Discover an Artist
After finding a new Artist, you commission him to create a Work of Art.

There are 8 Artists in each game, but only one of them (the face-up one) is available to create Works of
Art when the game begins. The other Artists must first be discovered by a Player taking this action and
following these steps:
1.	Chooses any one undiscovered Artist (a facedown Artist tile).
2.	Gains the bonus shown on the Artist bonus tile
and then discards the bonus tile to the game box.
3.	Red Artists only: Moves the Collector (White
Visitor) from the Artist tile to the Plaza.

4.	Flips the Artist tile face-up.
5.	Places a Fame marker on the brown space of
the Fame track on the Artist tile.

Commission space:
A Player may only have
one commission at any
time; if he already has a
Signature token on his commission space, he may
not discover another Artist and cannot have another
Signature token from the same Artist.

4

1
2

6.	Moves one Signature token from that Artist onto
the Commission Space at the bottom of the Art
value track on the Player’s board.

3

5

6

Discovering an Artist

Action: Buy & exhibit
a Work of Art
Something for your public to look at!

This action allows a Player to purchase a Work of
Art and display it in his Gallery. The cost of the
work is equal to the current Fame of the Artist
unless the Player has a commission for discovering
that Artist (see above). In that case, the cost of the
work is equal to the Artist’s initial Fame.

Artists only have enough
inspiration to have two
works on the Market
at the same time. This
is represented by the
Signature tokens. Once
both of these tokens have been removed from an
Artist, that Artist cannot produce another Work of
Art (except for one already commissioned) until
one of the previous works is sold.

Remember about commissions:
A Player who discovers an
Artist and has a Signature
token representing the
commission may not buy
another Work of Art from that
Artist until they have bought
the commissioned work.
A Player may have two Works of Art from the same
Artist.

To buy a Work of Art, a Player follows these steps:
Cost at current price = $14

Commission price = $10

Cost of Works of Art: Actual price = $14, Commission = $10

1.	 Chooses an Artist with either an available
Signature token, or one which he already has
a commission for. The topmost tile of the
corresponding Work of Art stack will be the
work they create.

1

2

2.	 Moves all Visitors on the Work of Art to the
Plaza.
Important reminder:
The Signature tokens are a crucial part of the game,
and a Player’s timing on when they are taken is
important for him to succeed.

Choosing Work of Art and moving Visitors to the Plaza

7

3.	 Pays money to the bank as follows:
i.	 If this is a commission, the price is the
Artist’s initial Fame;
ii.	Otherwise, the price is the Artist’s current Fame.
•	 Influence may be used to get money - see p.13.
4.	 Increases the Artist’s Fame by the amount
depicted on the work, plus an additional 1 for
each Collector in the Player’s Gallery.
•	 Influence may be used to gain Fame - see p.13.
•	 See p. 14 for more details on Fame.

5.	 Gains the tickets depicted on the Work of Art.
6.	 Moves the Work of Art to the leftmost empty
slot in the Player’s Gallery and turns it face
down (display side). If the Player has no
available slot, a Work of Art cannot be bought.

7.	 Moves the Signature token from the Artist tile
(or for commissioned works, the commission
space) to the right of the Player’s Art value
track, matching the Artist’s current star rating
(star rating is found under or before the Fame
marker position).

4th Art Gallery slot:
The 4th slot in a Player’s Gallery
is only available if the Player is
currently exhibiting a Masterpiece
(see p. 14)

7

6
Tracking the sales value of a Work of Art

4

5

Getting rewards from a Work of Art

Displaying a Work of Art

8.	 Place a number of random
Visitors from the bag on
the newly uncovered Work
of Art equal to the number
of tickets depicted on the
work. If the bag runs out,
place as many as you can.

If a Reputation tile was on the slot, the Player places it over the displayed Work of Art until he finishes his turn. At the end of his turn, he places the tile
onto one of the empty Reputation spaces on his Player board, receiving the bonus printed on that space (not the tile itself). He must then move one Visitor
from his Lobby back to the Plaza (if he has any). Because a Player only has 1 Reputation tile on his 3rd slot, each player can do this only once per game.
Note: If the Player has no empty Reputation spaces on his Player board, discard the Reputation tile back into the game box.

Example:
Yellow wants to buy a Work of Art from the Artist
shown below. The Artist’s current Fame is 9, so the
cost is 9 money. The Artist’s Fame increases by 3
in total (2 because of the Work of Art itself, and an
additional 1 because Yellow has 1 Collector in her
Gallery).
Increase in Artist’s Fame from the Work of Art itself = 2

Total Increase of Artist’s Fame = 3

Cost of the Work of Art - 9 money

8

Increase in Artist’s Fame from Collectors in Gallery = 1

Final Fame of Artist: 12 - Art Value: 1 Gold Star

Sales Office
Action: Sign a contract
You need to have contracts to sell your Works of Art.

This action allows a Player to take one of the face-up contract cards available in the display and place
it onto their own Player board.
Before performing this action, the Player may draw
4 new contracts from the deck and place them,
left to right, on top of the four current contracts.
The older contracts are not removed; instead they
are covered over with the new cards.
If a Player reveals new contracts, he may then
choose not to take one of them, although this is
not advisable.

Optionally, you may cover all cards with 4 new ones

The contract card taken is then placed on the
Player’s board; on an empty contract space or over
a previously fulfilled (face-down) contract.
If a contract is placed onto an empty slot, the
Player receives the ticket depicted on the slot,
taken from the box office.

Placing a contract on the pink ticket space

If the slot contained a previously fulfilled contract,
put the card face up on a discard pile next to the
contract deck, and place the new contract on the
space. However, the Player does not receive the
ticket printed on the space a second time.
If there was an Assistant on the flipped order card,
it is sent home (Going Home - see p. 6).

Take the ticket from the Box Office onto your Player board

After completing the action, if there is an empty
space in the contracts display, draw a replacement
from the deck and place it face-up onto the empty
space.

Example:
Orange moves his pawn to the Sales Office and
chooses to take a contract. He doesn’t like any of
the current contracts in the display, and so draws 4
new cards to place over the existing contracts. He
sees one that he likes, and places it onto his Player
board. There is still one empty space on the Player
board, so he decided to place the contract here and
receives a Pink ticket from the box office.

Empty contract deck - If the draw pile is empty
when a card is needed (either refilling an empty
space, or when needing 4 new cards), reshuffle the
discards together with any contracts in the display,
make a new deck, draw 4 new contracts and place
them in the display.

Attention:
If a player has three unfulfilled (face-up) contract
cards on his Player board, he may not sign a new
contract (i.e. Take a new contract card).

Placing a new contract over a fulfilled contract space

Refill only if there is an empty space in the display

9

Action: Sell a Work of Art
Remember the Collectors
Rule? (see p. 5)
After a sale you can have one
more Collector in your Gallery.

While working as an Art dealer, time to make real money.

Once a Player has a face-up contract card on his Player board and a Work of Art of the matching form in
his Gallery, he may perform this action to sell that Work of Art.

Look for this symbol in your
Gallery on the game board.

To sell a Work of Art, a Player completes the following steps:
1.	 Receives money according to the position of
the Signature token on the Art Value track.

4.	Returns the Signature token to the space next
to the appropriate Artist tile.

2.	 Removes a Work of Art of the matching art
form from his Gallery and places it next to his
Player board.

5.	Moves any one Visitor from his Gallery to the
Plaza (if any).

3.	 Moves any other Work of Art in the Gallery to
the left to fill any gaps.

6.	Flips the contract card face-down.
•	If the order card had an Assistant on it, the
Assistant returns home (Going Home - see p. 6).

•	 When flipping the card, the Player orients it
so that the top half matches the type of Visitor
that was moved in step 5 (Influence for a VIP, or
Investment for an Investor). If the Player moved
a Collector, or there was no Visitor to move, he
may choose either orientation.
•	 Note the Player does not receive this bonus
immediately, he must take an Executive Action
later on to take it.

Find a Work of Art with a matching contract on your board

Move the Work of Art out, and slide the rest to the left

Take the indicated amount of money

Return the Signature token to the Artist

Move a Visitor to the Plaza. Note the reminder on the Player board

Orientation of the flipped contract must match the Visitor moved

Example:
Orange has a Work of Art in his Gallery that has the
same Art form as one of his contracts. He places his
Gallerist on the Sales Office Location and chooses
to sell it.

He receives 14 money from the bank because of the
position of the Signature token next to his Player
board; the token is then placed back onto the Artist
tile. He has 5 Visitors in his Gallery, and chooses to
move one of the VIP’s back to the Plaza.

The contract card is flipped face-down, and he
rotates it so that the Influence bonus is on top. If
he had chosen to move the Collector back to his
Plaza, he could have chosen either orientation of
the face-down contract card.

If a Player’s Gallery has two Works of the same art form by different artists, it does not matter which Work of Art he chooses when he sells.
Optionally, for thematic reasons, a Player may use the red and blue tiles provided, to track the works created by each artist.

10

Media Center
Action: Hire Assistants
The help you need is just around the corner.

By taking this action, a Player may hire as many Assistants as he can fit in his office (there are
only 4 desks). The cost of hiring each Assistant is shown on the Player board and increases as the
unemployment queue decreases. To hire Assistants, a Player follows these steps:
1.	Moves up to 4 Assistants from the top of the
Player’s unemployment queue to empty desks
in his office.
2.	Pays the cost for each Assistant as depicted
next to their space.
•	 Influence may be used to get money - see p.13.
3.	Gains any hiring bonus depicted next to their
space (tickets, Influence or money).

Example:
Yellow wants to hire more Assistants. She currently
has one in her office and can therefore hire up to
three more. She decides to hire two new Assistants
paying a total cost of 3 money and receives a brown
ticket (as shown next to the 2nd space on the
unemployment queue).

Hiring 2 new Assistants - pay 3 money, get brown ticket

Action: Promote Artist
Arrange for media promotion for an Artist, making them more famous.

The top right of an Artist’s tile shows the current level of media promotion
that Artist has. With this action, a Player can increase this by 1 level by
following these steps in order:
1.	Spends Influence equal to the new level of
Promotion token.
2.	Returns the current Promotion token, if any, to
the appropriate space on the game board.
3.	Places the next level of Promotion token onto
the Artist.
If there are no Promotion tokens of the new level
available, the action cannot be taken.

Current Promotion Level of the Artist

Example:
Orange is currently exhibiting a painting from the
Artist shown below. He is planning to sell the Work
of Art later in the game and wants to make the
Artist more famous, thereby increasing the value of
his work. To do this, he needs to pay Influence.

4.	Earns the bonus depicted above the Promotion
token space on the board for the Promotion
token just placed (any 1 Ticket, Influence, 2
different Tickets, Investment or Visitor).

The media promotion of the Artist is currently level
2, so Orange spends 3 Influence, returns the level
2 token, takes a level 3 marker from the board and
places it on the Artist tile.

5.	Increases the Artist’s Fame by 1 plus an
additional 1 for each Collector in the Player’s
Gallery.

He receives the tickets bonus shown on the board,
and the Artists Fame increases by 2 spaces (1, plus
another 1 because Orange has one Collector in his
Gallery).

•	 Influence may be used to gain Fame - see p.13.

Pay Influence, return previous token and Promote the Artist

Get the bonus, and then increase the Fame of the Artist

11

International Market
Send your Assistants to increase your Reputation with foreign Visitors or make an offer in an auction.

This Location has a table of spaces, 3 columns
wide and split into an upper (4-row) and lower (3row) section. The two actions that are performed
here use a different section of the table. However,
the following rule applies to both actions:

To have access to a column, a Player must meet
the requirement shown at the top of the table with
Visitors in his Lobby. Visitors in his Gallery do not
count.
1st column - 1 Visitor (of any color)
2nd column - 1 Investor and 1 VIP
3rd column - 1 Collector and also 1 Investor
	
or 1 VIP

Upper section - Reputation, lower section - Auction

Therefore, if you have one of each type of Visitor
in your Lobby, you have access to all columns.

Requirement to access international Market columns

Action: Take a Reputation tile
Rub elbows with foreign dignitaries in the international Art scene.

This action is taken in the upper 4 rows of the International Market table. The Player chooses one of the available Reputation tiles from a column and row
that he has access to.
To gain access to a row, a Player must have acquired (either exhibited or sold) a
corresponding Work of Art (depicted to the left of the row).
After checking he has the correct access to the column and row, the Player performs the
following steps:
1.	 Earns the Influence shown above the respective
column (3, 2, 1).
2.	 Takes the Reputation tile from the chosen
space and place it on any empty Reputation
space of his Player board, immediately
receiving the benefit of the covered space (not
the tile itself).

1

Earning Influence

12

3.	 Moves any one Visitor from the Player’s Lobby
to the Plaza (if any). Note the
reminder on Player board.
4.	 Places one of his Assistants onto the nowempty Reputation space on the table, taken
from either the Player’s office or a Location.
•	Only one Assistant is allowed per space.

2

Taking a Reputation tile and gaining the bonus.

A Player who has not yet acquired a Work of Art
during the game may not choose this action.

If a Player has no empty Reputation spaces on his
Player board, he may not perform this action.

Assistants placed in the International Market stay
there all game and are important during the end of
game scoring.

3

4

Moving a Visitor from the Lobby and placing an Assistant

Action: Make an offer for Art of International Renown
Participate in an international Art auction for a very valuable Work of Art.

This action is taken in the lower 3 rows of the International Market table. After checking he has the
correct access to the column, the Player performs the following steps:

Assistants placed on the lower 3 rows of the table
are important during end of game scoring, not only
for majorities, but also to determine which Players
receives the renowned Works of Art. (see p. 15)

1.	 Gains the Influence shown above the
respective column (3, 2 or 1).
2.	 Chooses a row and pays the offer value of 1, 3
or 6 money (indicated to the left of the row).
3.	 Takes the bonus shown on the space.
4.	 Places one of his Assistants onto the space,
from either the Player’s office or a Location.
The bonuses are explained on the Player aid.

He pays the offer of 3 money for this row

Receives the bonus of the space (Gain Influence)

Influence
A Player earns Influence from having VIP’s and Collectors in his Gallery and for taking
Location actions in the International Market. A Player’s position on the Influence track
also earns a Player extra money at the end of the game. Influence may be spent during
the game in the following situations:
•	 A Player takes a Location Action during a Kicked-Out Action. (see p. 6)
•	 A Player takes the Promotion Action from Media Center. (see p. 11)

•	 A Player uses money to buy a Work of Art, hire Assistants or make an
offer in the International Market;
•	 A Player performs an action which increases the Fame of an Artist.

The first two situations have been covered already in the rules. The other two situations are explained here.

Gaining money
When a Player needs to spend money he may move his Influence disc back on the Influence
track to the previous space that shows the money icon. This gives the Player 1 money. He
may continue moving his Influence disc back, gaining an additional 1 money for each money icon space
moved to. Note that moving an Influence disc from space 35 to space 34 only generates 1 money.
Example
Blue has 13 Influence and wants to buy a Work of
Art that will cost 5. He only has 3 money. He moves
his Influence disc back to space 8 and gains the 2
money he needs.

The number inside the money icon on the Influence
track is only used for endgame scoring.
A Player may use the Influence track to gain all the
money he needs at the time, even if he has money
in hand.
In the example, the Blue Player could have moved
his Influence disc back to the start, gain an
additional 2 money, spent the 5 he needed, and
kept 2 of his original money in hand.

Using Influence to get money

If the marker reaches the end of the Influence
track, any additional Influence gained is lost.

It is not allowed to use the Influence track to gain
money which is not then spent immediately.

Gaining Fame
When a Player takes an action which
increases the Fame of an Artist, he may
move his Influence disc back on the track to the
previous space with the Fame icon. This adds an
additional 1 Fame to the Artist. He may continue
to move his Influence disc back, granting an
additional 1 Fame to the Artist for each Fame Icon
space he moved to.
Example:
Orange has 12 Influence and buys a Work of Art.
The Artist would gain 2 Fame from this action, but
Orange chooses to move his Influence disc back to
space 10 (the previous Fame icon), and the Artist
gains 1 additional Fame. If he moved the disc to
space 5, the artist would gain 2 additional Fame.

Using Influence to get additional Fame

13

Tickets
Whenever a Player gains tickets, they are taken from the appropriate stack in the box office
on the game board. The color of ticket taken must match the ticket icon on the board /
component. If the printed ticket has a triple-color, a Player may take a ticket of any color.
Tickets are used for moving Visitors as an Executive Action (see p. 5).
If a Player gains a ticket of a color and there are
no more of that type of ticket in the box office,
the Player instead removes one of any other type
of ticket from the box office (if any), places it in
the discard pile, and then takes one ticket of the
correct color from the discard pile.

Once the box office is empty of all tickets, Players
take any tickets gained from the discard pile.

Intermediate Scoring
At the end of the turn in which the last ticket of
one color is taken from the box office, each Player
earns Influence and money.
Intermediate scoring only happens once during the
game, when the first stack of tickets runs out.

Example:
Purple buys a Work of Art that gives 2 tickets of any
color. She wants one white ticket and one brown
ticket, but there are only 2 brown tickets in the box
office. So, she takes one brown ticket as normal,
and then discards another brown ticket from the box
office and takes a white ticket from the discard pile.

•	 2 Influence per VIP and 1 Influence per Collector
in his Gallery.
•	 2 money per Investor and 1 money per Collector
in his Gallery.

No tickets of the correct color? Exchange with the discards

Fame and Celebrity Status
An Artist’s Fame determines the sales value of their Works of Art. This is both
the cost to buy them, and also the amount of money a Player receives for selling
them. Therefore, it is a good idea to buy a Work of Art from an Artist when he is
mostly unknown, and then sell it when he is more famous.
There are two ways to increase an Artist’s Fame.
•	Buying a Work of Art from them, or
•	Promoting them in the industry via the media.

Intermediate scoring symbol

Important Rule:
You can never take 2 tickets of the
same color at the same time.

When a Player buys a Work of Art, they track the
Sales Value of it by placing the corresponding
Signature token next to the Art value track of his
Player board. Whenever the Fame of an Artist
increases to the next Fame symbol, any Works
of Art increase in value, and Players adjust the
Signature tokens accordingly (see p. 8).
If an Artist’s Fame reaches 19, the Artist becomes
a Celebrity and retires.

A Player who takes an action that causes this to
happen performs the following steps:
1.	Place a Celebrity tile over the Artist and gain 5
money.
2.	Any exhibited Works of Art by the Artist
who has just become a Celebrity becomes a
Masterpiece.
•	Players with at least one Masterpiece in their
Gallery are allowed to use the 4th slot. This
additional slot is only available as long as the
Player still has a Masterpiece in his Gallery.
•	No more Works of Art can be bought from the
Artist except for a commission (see p. 7).

This happens immediately after the active Player
finishes his turn and before the next Player starts
their next turn.

Artist becomes a Celebrity and his works: Masterpieces

Intermediate Scoring caused by brown tickets running out

14

Player earns 5 money, 4th space in Gallery becomes available

Example:
Blue buys a Work of Art from an Artist who currently has 16 Fame. Thankfully, because this was a commission,
Blue only pays 10 (the original Fame of the Artist). After the purchase, the Fame of the Artist increases by 4
(2 because of the Work of Art, and another 2 because Blue has 2 Collectors in his Gallery). This pushes the
Artist’s Fame to 19 (the additional Fame is lost) and he becomes a Celebrity. Blue places a Celebrity tile on the
Artist and earns 5 money. Since the Work of Art he just bought is now considered a Masterpiece, his Gallery
may now contain 4 Works of Art, instead of 3.

Endgame Scoring
Use the spots in the upper right of the game board
to track the Endgame Scoring steps.

International Market Majorities:
Each column of the International Market
is scored separately. The Player with
the most Assistants in the first column
(including those involved in the auction) receives
6 money. The Player with the second most
Assistants receives 3 money, and the Player with
the third most receives 1 money. In case of a tie,
add all tied positions together and split the result
between the Players (rounded down). A Player with
no Assistants in a column receives no money.
•	Repeat the process for the second and third
columns, with the money awarded shown
below the table.
Example:
In the image below, the scoring is as follows:
Left column: 6 money to Yellow, 2 money to Orange
and Purple.
Middle column: 8 money to Blue and Purple, 1
money to Orange and Yellow.
Right column: 15 money to Orange, 10 money to
Blue, 3 money to Yellow and Purple.

Example 2: Auction resolution
Total value of exhibition = 42

Auction Renowned Works of Art:
The Works of Art on the easels are
auctioned off. Add up each Player’s
total offer based on the Assistants they
have on the bottom 3 rows of the International
Market. Each Assistant is worth 1, 3 or 6,
depending on the row they are on.
The Player with the highest total offer chooses one
of the renowned Works of Art and places it either
in his Gallery (even if there are no spaces), or next
to his Player board (along with any previously sold
works).

When a Player takes a Renowned Work of Art
(whether he puts it in his Gallery, or next to his
Player board), he receives money equal to the sales
value of that work, as if it was created by the most
famous discovered Artist of the chosen Art form.
Example:
The photograph is worth 1 Gold Star because,
out of the two Photographers, the blue one is the
most famous, and the sales value for a Work of Art
created by him is 14.

If multiple Players are tied for the highest total
offer, the Player with the higher offer in the 3rd
column wins. If there are no offers in the 3rd
column, look at the 2nd column, and so on.
The Player with the second highest offer then
takes one of the remaining Works of Art. This
process repeats until all works have been taken.
Each Player may only take one renowned work.
Example 1:
Blue and Orange both have a total offer of 6.
Orange wins, because he has the higher offer in the
right hand column.

Scoring Auction Work of Art

Score Curator cards:
Each Player earns money for completed
collections of Art (currently exhibited in
their Gallery) as shown on their Curator
card. A Player may have at most five exhibited
Works of Art (including at least one Masterpiece
and one Auctioned Work of Art). A single Work of
Art may be part of two collections and can be used
to fulfill more than one goal.
Example:
Blue gains 10 money for having completed one of
the collections on his Curator card.

Majorities scoring

Score Reputation tiles:
Each Player earns money and/or
Influence for each Reputation tile they
have on their Player board (see last page
for descriptions).

Score Exhibition:
For each Work of Art currently exhibited
in a Player’s Gallery, that Player receives
money equal to its sales value.

Example 1: Auction resolution

Example 2:
Blue has the highest total (6) and takes one of the
Works of Art. There is a tie for 2nd place between
Orange and Yellow, each having a total offer of 4.
There are no Assistants in the 3rd column, but in
the 2nd column, Orange has a higher offer than
Yellow, and so takes the second Work of Art.

Curator card scoring

15

Score Art Dealer cards:
Each Player earns money for completed
sets of sold Works of Art as shown on
their Art Dealer card.
Example:
Gains 15 money for having completed two of the
sets on his Art Dealer card.

Score Influence:
Each Player receives money based on
their position on the Influence track.

Example:
Blue gains 12 money, Yellow gains 9 and Purple
gains 8.

The Player with the most money wins the game.
In the case of a tie, follow these tiebreakers, in
order:
Tie-breaker 1:
The Player with most Works of Art acquired
(exhibited and sold)
Tie-breaker 2:
The Player with most Visitors in his Gallery
Tie-breaker 3:
The Player with most Assistants in play
If there is still a tie, all tied Players win.

Art Dealer card Goals

Solitaire Play

Influence at end of game earns money

Setup

If you Kicked-Out Lacerda’s Gallerist, he also
discards one ticket, and he will simply continue
moving clockwise in his turn; i.e. you can’t disrupt
Lacerda’s clockwise movement.

Follow the normal game setup, with the following
exceptions:

International Market

Choose a Player color to represent the dummy
Player (Lacerda). Place Lacerda’s Gallerist pawn
and all his Assistants near the game board.
Place 10 tickets of each color in the box office.
Place 8 random Reputation tiles in the 1st and
3rd columns of the top part of the International
Market. The middle column is not used.

Every time Lacerda moves to the International
Market, or he or any of his Assistants is KickedOut from there by you, place one of Lacerda’s
Assistants onto the table in the first available
empty space, starting in the top left, moving right,
and then to the next row. The first of Lacerda’s
Assistants is placed in the top part (Reputation
tile). The second is placed in the bottom part

Take 4 Visitors of each type and put them back in
the box.

If you Kicked-Out any of Lacerda’s Assistants,
place the Assistant back in his supply by the side
of the game board and discard one ticket from
the stack with the most tickets; in case of a tie,
discard from any tied stack.
16

End of Solitaire Game
The solo game ends at the end of the round in
which the last ticket is taken from the box office.
Then, you take one more action (at a different
location to the one you are currently at).

Apprentice
1. Achieve at least one of each of your Curator and
Art Dealer goals; 2. Acquire at least 4 Reputation
tiles; 3. Acquire at least 1 Masterpiece; 4. Have at
least 160 money.

You play first. After your first turn, place Lacerda’s
pawn on the opposite Location of the game
board. After each of your subsequent turns,
Lacerda moves clockwise one Location, leaving an
Assistant behind at each place.

Lacerda does not take any Location or Executive
Actions except at the International Market.

When one of Lacerda’s Assistants is placed on a
space with a Reputation tile, that tile is discarded.

Goals to win the Solitaire Game:

Gameplay

As usual, if he kicks you or your Assistant out of a
Location, you can take a Kicked-Out Action.

(Auction). This sequence is repeated during the
game, so the 3rd, 5th, etc., Assistants are placed in
the top part, and the 2nd, 4th, etc., are placed in the
bottom part. If any part of the table is filled, the
Assistants are placed on the unfilled part until the
table is completed.

The Assistant is placed at 1st empty space nearest the top left

Example:
Lacerda moves to the International Market. He
already has 2 Assistants in the Reputation part of
the table, and also 2 in the auction part. So this
will be the 5th of Lacerda’s Assistants placed in the
table, and it is therefore placed in the top part. The
Assistant is placed on the first empty space nearest
the top left and the Reputation tile is discarded.

Experienced
1. Achieve the highest goal of the Curator card and
one goal of the Art dealer card; 2. Acquire at least 5
Reputation tiles; 3. Acquire at least 2 Masterpieces;
4. Have at least 180 money.
The Master Gallerist
1. Get at least 35 money in total from Curator and
Art Dealer goals; 2. Acquire at least 5 Reputation
tiles; 3. Acquire at least 3 Masterpieces.

Example of Play
Round One
The game begins, Blue goes first:
He moves away from the International Market
to the Artist Colony, leaving an Assistant
behind. This kicks Orange out of the Location, and
Orange’s pawn is moved to the black circle next to the
Location. Blue decides to buy a Work of Art.

He flips the blue photographer Artist tile and receives
the bonus shown on the bonus tile (2 tickets in this
case; he takes white and pink). He also places a Fame
cube to mark the Artist’s initial Fame of 4.

To pay for it, she would need to move her Influence
marker back to the previous space with the Fame icon.
This will cost her 5 Influence, which she thinks is too
expensive, so she chooses not to do so.

One of the Artist’s Signature tokens is placed on his
commission space of his Player board.

Instead, Purple moves her Gallerist pawn to her Gallery
on the game board.

Orange now has a commission, and the price of the first
Work of Art that he buys from this Artist will always be
at the initial Fame value (4).
Orange’s Gallerist is then moved to his Gallery.

He can only buy from the blue painter, as this is the
only available Artist.
He pays 3 money for the Work of Art (the current Fame
of the Artist) and moves the two Visitors on the Work of
Art to the Plaza.
Since he does not have any Collectors in his Gallery, the
Fame of the Artist only increases by the value depicted
on the Work of Art, in this case, just 1.
He gains the tickets shown on the Work of Art. He must
take 1 brown ticket and then his choice of either pink or
white. He chooses pink, and places both tickets in his
office.
Blue places the Artwork in his Gallery face down in the
leftmost space and takes one of the Signature tokens for
the Artist and places it on the right of his Player board
next to the 1 Green Star icon. This marks the sales
value of the Work of Art.
He then places one Visitor randomly from the bag onto
the newly revealed Work of Art (because there is only 1
ticket printed on the new Work).
Before he finishes his turn, Blue chooses to take an
Executive Action:
He discards the pink ticket to move the VIP in his Lobby
(from game setup) one space into his Gallery. He also
spends the brown ticket to bring an Investor to his lobby.

Orange’s Kicked-Out Action - Discovering an Artist

Yellow is up next, she is currently at the
Sales Office. Before she leaves, she places an
Assistant in her present Location, and then
moves to the Media Center, kicking the Purple Player
out. Then she takes an action to Hire Assistants.
She hires two Assistants from her unemployment queue,
receiving the brown ticket (printed next to the second
Assistant’s space) and moves the Assistants to empty
desks in her office.

Yellow decides to pay 2 money from her own supply and
use Influence to pay for the other 1.
To pay this 1 money with Influence, she moves her
Influence disc two spaces back (to the space with the
money icon).

She offers the brown ticket to move one Investor from
the Plaza to her Lobby.

Blue’s turn - Buying a Work of Art

In order to take one of the two Location
Actions, Orange needs to spend Influence,
moving his Influence marker back to the
previous space with the Fame icon. This will cost him 5
Influence, which he decides to do.
Orange takes the action to discover an Artist and
chooses the blue photographer.

Having been Kicked-Out of her previous
Location, she may now choose to move to any
Location. She moves her Gallerist pawn to the Sales Office
which kicks-out Yellow´s Assistant. She wants to take a
contract card, but none of the contracts in the display are
to her liking, so she chooses to draw 4 new contracts and
places them over the current ones in the display.
Then, she takes one of these new contract cards and
places it on the third space in her office (she could have
chosen any space). She takes a ticket of any color, as
shown on the covered space; she chooses white.
Before Purple finishes her turn, she may take an
Executive Action:
She could use the ticket she just gained to move a
Visitor, or she could use the bonus of her contract card
by placing an Assistant on it; she chooses to do neither.
Yellow chooses not to take a Kicked-Out Action and
sends her Assistant home.

She must pay a total of 3 money for this (1 for the first
Assistant and 2 for the second).

Before finishing her turn, Yellow chooses to take an
Executive Action:

Before the turn passes to Yellow however, Orange is
waiting outside the Location, having been Kicked-Out.
Orange may now take a ‘Kicked-Out Action’:

It is now Purple’s own turn:

Yellow’s turn - Hiring Assistants

Having been Kicked-Out, Purple’s Gallerist is waiting
outside the Media Center. Purple now has the option of
taking a ‘Kicked-Out Action’ before her turn begins:
She does not have any tickets or contracts, so she
cannot take an Executive Action, but she could spend
Influence to take one of the two Location Actions.

Purple’s turn - Getting a contract

Orange is up next and moves his Gallerist to
the Media Center. This kicks-out Yellow.
Before Orange takes his Location Action however, he
uses his Executive Action to spend a white ticket and
move a Collector from his Lobby to his Gallery.
Then, as his Location Action, he chooses to Promote the
blue photographer that he discovered on the previous
Kicked-Out Action during Blue’s turn.
The Artist’s current Promotion level is 1, so Orange
spends 2 Influence, and places a level 2 token onto
the Artist. Orange receives the bonus shown above the
Promotion token space (Gain Influence). This gives him
1 Influence (for the Collector in his Gallery).
Then, the Artist’s Fame increases by 2 in total: 1 for the
Promotion, and an additional 1 because Orange has 1
Collector in his Gallery. The Fame marker is moved to
space 6, which has the 2 Green Stars icon. This means
that any existing Work of Art is increased in value.
However, the Signature token that Orange has next to
his Player board is still a commission only; it has not yet
been bought, so it stays on the commission space.

17

onto the space in the table. This earns Yellow a new
Assistant and a pink ticket.
For her Executive Action, Yellow spends the pink ticket
and moves the VIP in her Lobby to her Gallery.

A couple of rounds later:

Orange’s turn - Promoting an Artist

Blue is the next Player, and he decides that
he wants to sell his Work of Art.

After Orange’s turn is over, Yellow may take a Kicked-Out
Action, but chooses not to, and returns to her Gallery.

Round Two
Now it is Blue’s turn again:
He moves one of his Assistants to the
Location he is at, and then decides to
visit the International Market to increase
his Reputation. With this move he kicks out his
own Assistant. The Assistant returns home without
performing an action and Blue continues his turn.
He only has 1 Investor in his Lobby, and so only has
access to the first column of the table. He also only has
a painting, so there is only one space in the top part of
the table he can choose.
He gains the 3 Influence, takes the Reputation tile from
the space and places it on his Player board, over the
space that allows him to move any Visitor from the Plaza
to his Gallery. He chooses to move a VIP.
Blue moves the Investor in his Lobby back to the Plaza
because his job is done, and finally, places an Assistant
from his office onto the space in the International
Market where the tile was taken from.
Blue does not have any tickets or contracts, so cannot
take an Executive Action.

Yellow’s turn - Making an offer

Blue then gets to take a Kicked-Out Action and would
have liked to spend 3 Influence to take a Location
Action. However, he no longer has any Visitors in his
Lobby, so cannot access the International Market. His
Gallerist is moved back to his Gallery.
Purple’s Turn:
Purple visits the Artists Colony, kicking out
the Blue Assistant. She wants to buy a Work
of Art to fulfill the contract she took on her
last turn, but before taking the Location Action, she
uses her Executive Action to move an Assistant onto her
contract card. The bonus allows her to choose a Visitor
from the bag and place it directly into her Gallery, and
she chooses a Collector.
She then uses her Location Action to buy the last
available painting. (The blue painter now has no
Signature tokens left).

Yellow’s turn:
Yellow moves from her Gallery to the
International Market. Blue is already at the
International Market, and so is Kicked-Out.
Yellow has one VIP and one Investor in her Lobby so she
can choose to access either the 1st or 2nd column of
the table.
She decides to make an offer (the lower part of the
table), and chooses the “1 money” row of the second
column. She gains 2 Influence for choosing the 2nd
column, and then uses her Influence to get the 1 money
she needs for the offer, moving back her disc to space
8 of the track, and places one Assistant from her office

18

He moves from his Gallery to the Sales Office
and chooses to sell his only painting. The Artwork is
worth 8 money (the position of the Signature token),
so he removes the painting from his Gallery and places
it next to his Player board, receives 8 money from the
bank, and returns the Signature token to the Artist.
After the sale, Blue must move one Visitor from his
Gallery to the Plaza. Since he only has one VIP inside,
he must send that one away.
His Assistant, which is on the contract card, is returned
to the office and the contract card is flipped.
Since the Visitor that was sent away was a VIP, the
contract card is oriented with the Influence icon on the
top. If he had no Visitors inside his Gallery before the
sale or he had moved a Collector, he could have chosen
the orientation of the card.
For his Executive Action, he could move one of his
Assistants onto the just-flipped contract card. But
since he no longer has any VIPs inside his Gallery he
will get no influence for this, so he decides to skip the
Executive Action.

She places the Signature token to the right of her Player
board, next to the space with 1 Green Star (based on
the current Fame of the Artist).
Purple pays 4 money for the work (current Fame of
the Artist), using 3 of her own money, and 1 from the
Influence track by moving her Influence marker back 2
spaces.

Blue’s turn - Getting a Reputation tile

Blue has an Assistant waiting outside the Location, so he
can now do a Kicked-Out Action; he decides to use his
Influence and discover a new Artist. After performing his
Kicked-Out Action, Blue moves his Assistant to his office.

She then increases the Fame of the Artist who she
bought the Work of Art from by 1 (as shown on the
Work of Art card) and an additional 1 because she has
1 Collector in her Gallery. She wants to increase the
value of the painting even more, and decides to use her
Influence to get the Artist 1 additional Fame. Purple
spends 3 Influence (back to the previous Fame icon on
the Influence track).
The Artist’s Fame is now 2 Green Stars, so the Signature
tokens owned by Blue and Purple are moved up to the
2 Green Stars space. The sales value of these Works is
now 8.

Purple’s turn - Buying a Work of Art

Blue’s Turn - Selling a Work of Art

Artist Participation
Photography

Artist

Description

2. USA

•	 Craig Maher

Paint, 2011

4. USA

•	 Alexander E.B. Zatarain

Ode to R. Mutt, 2014, This piece attempts to lift the object out of its context so that its qualities are felt
while its identity is obscured. Once the viewer realizes what the object in the photograph actually is, my
hope is that he will discover new meanings in the reality of commonplace things.

5. Australia

•	 Robert Masters

Dichroic Glass, 2014, Macro Photo of dichroic glass, bracelets. Part of Google+ weekly photo Project 2014

6. Portugal

•	 Vital Lacerda

Dancing Girl, 2008, Introspection. Part of a blog project.

7. Portugal

•	 Bruno Valério

Square Budha, 2013, Aveiro

8. USA

•	 Tim Barnes

2010, Interior of a covered bridge at Southford Falls State Park in Southford, Connecticut. Is a “High
Dynamic Range” (HDR) photograph, which is a combination of several shots.

1 and 3 were created by the game Artist - Ian O’Toole - Australi and

Painting

Artist

Description

9. Australia

•	 Alicia Smith

The Deep Rainforest, 1997, detail. Water Color, pen/ink. Unicorns, Dragons, Manticores, Phoenixes,
Basilisks/Cockatrices, Perytons, Gryphons/Griffins, Couatls.

10. India

•	 Amit Kalla

Landscape (abstract), 2014-2015, Oil on paper, 23x23 Inches

11. USA

•	 Craig Maher

The screamer, 2005, Oil over Canvas

12. Brazil

•	 Janete C. Cunha Claro

Coffee Series, 2002-2015. Part of a series of paintings that highlights one of the riches of Brazil, coffee,
which is an eternal reflection of the sensitivity and taste of the Brazilian culture and its people.

13. USA

•	 Amy Shamanssky

Harold’s World, 2010, Acrylic and Charcoal on canvas, 16x20 Inches

14. Mexico

•	 Pablo de Leon Nava

Esperando, 2015.

15. Hong-Kong

•	 Francis G Alexsandero W

Psalms of the heart, 2014, detail. Marker on Canvas, People are always in darkness and goodness, to
restrain the mind will be able to write a beautiful poem.

16. USA

•	 Pablo Peña

The Last Sunset, 2012-2014.

Digital Art

Artist

Description

27. Portugal

•	 Vital Lacerda

Organic Glass, 2006, Distortions, macro. Seeing life melting through glass.

29. USA

•	 Raef Payne

Syzygy, 2011, Illustration. Syzygy is about the aligning of planets in the universe and the creation of new
possibilities and new worlds.

30. Hong-Kong

•	 Francis G Alexsandero W

7 Horses Gallop - Seven of life Outline, 2014, Illustration. Chinese Ink on Rice Paper. Truth, morality,
benevolence, righteousness, prosperity, wisdom and trust.

32. Belgium

•	 Rafaël Theunis

Sunset in Winter, 2004, I made a series of photographic collages using blueprinting techniques to
visualize a diary I kept whilst studying in Boston, MA. The work symbolizes my visual and internal
impressions of a cold but beautiful winter.

25, 26, 28 and 31, were created by the game Artist - Ian O’Toole - Australia
All 3D Sculpture Works 17 to 24 were created by the game Artist Ian O’Toole - Australia
All the Works of Art described above were kindly contributed by the Artists themselves. For them, and all the others who sent their work, a huge thank you. Without you,
this game would not be possible.

19

Reputation tiles:
Gain 1 money per 3 Influence you have (round down).
Resolve this tile before any others.

Gain 2 money per Work of Art you acquired during the game
(exhibited and sold).

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money per Collector in your Gallery.

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money per Work of Art you sold.

Gain 1 Influence and 2 money per VIP in your Gallery.

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money per Work of Art you are exhibiting.

Gain 1 Influence and 2 money per Investor in your Gallery.

Gain 1 Influence and 2 money for each different Art form you
acquired during the game.

Gain 1 money per Visitor in your Gallery.

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money per photograph you acquired
during the game (exhibited and sold).

Gain 4 money for each set of 3 different Visitors in your Gallery.

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money per painting you acquired during
the game (exhibited and sold).

Gain 1 Influence and 2 money per Reputation tile you have
(including this one).

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money per digital Art you acquired during
the game (exhibited and sold).

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money for each of your Assistants in the
Auction part of the International Market.

Gain 1 Influence and 3 money per sculpture you acquired during
the game (exhibited and sold).

Gain 1 Influence and 1 money for each of your Assistants in play
(not unemployed).

Gain 2 money for each Artist with a Fame of 15 or higher.

Gain 2 money for each Artist who has a Promotion level of 4 or
more.

Gain 2 Influence and 4 money per Masterpiece you are
exhibiting.

Many thanks to all playtesters: Alexandre Garcia, Álvaro Santos, António Lobo Ramos, António Vale, Becca Morse,
Bruno Valério, Carolina Valença, Catarina Lacerda, Carlos Paiva, Chris Zinsli, Cristina Antunes, Christopher Incao,
Dan Wiseman, Daniel Gunther, David Dagoma, Duarte Conceição, Elhannan Keller, Elsa Romão, Emanuel Santos,
Firmino Martinez, Garry Rice, Gil Hova, Gonçalo Moura, Hélio Andrade, Ian O´Toole ,Inês Lacerda, João Madeira,
João Monteiro, João Silva, Larry Rice, Luís Evangelista, Marco Chiappa, Mike Minutillo, Nuno Silva, Nuno Cordeiro,
Oliver Brooks, Paul Grogan, Paulo Duque, Paulo Renato, Pedro Freitas, Pedro Sampaio, Pete King, Rafael Duarte,
Rafael Pires, Ricardo Gama, Ricardo Moita, Rhiannon Ochs, Robert Canner, Robert Forrest, Ruben Rodrigues, Rui
Malhado, Sandra Sarmento, Sandrina Fernandes, Sérgio Martins, Sofia Passinhas, Suzanne Zinsli, Tiago Duarte,
Vasco Chita, Vitor Pires and Grupos de Lisboa, Leiria, Aveiro, Porto, the Columbus Area Boardgaming Society, and
Arcádia Lusitana.
A huge thank you to: Hugo Elias, Jorge Graça, Nathan Morse, Paulo Lacerda, Pedro Almeida, Pedro Branco, Ricardo
Almeida, Sérgio Neves, these guys played all versions of this game undetermined times.
Special thanks to Paul M. Incao for all his commitment and time spent developing The Gallerist, Ian O’Toole for the
amazing Art, Paul Grogan for the exquisite editing of English rules, all of the BGG community for their suggestions
and support, and Rick Soued for believing in me and the game. Without all of these people this game would not
have been possible.
All my love to my beautiful daughters Catarina and Inês and to my muse and greatest friend, my wife Sandra for all
their ideas, patience, support, and inspiration and many, many hours of playtesting.

20

Credits:
Game Design: Vital Lacerda
Game Development: Paul M. Incao
Illustrations: Ian O´Toole
Graphic Design &amp; 3D illustrations: Ian O´Toole
Rulebook &amp; 3D illustrations: Vital Lacerda
English Rules Editing: Paul Grogan, Gaming Rules!
Proofread: Adam Allet, Ori Avtalion, Travis D. Hill, Victoria Strickland
Project Manager: Rick Soued
If you have any questions, please email us at: info@eagle-gryphon.net
LIKE us on Facebook: www.facebook.com/Eagle-Gryphon-Games
FOLLOW us on Twitter: @EagleGames
© 2015 Eagle-Gryphon Games,
801 Commerce Drive, building #5.
Leitchfield, KY 42754, All Rights Reserved.
www.eagle-gryphon.com

</rulebook>
			
						               													<description>This age of art and capitalism has created a need for a new occupation - The Gallerist.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Combining the elements of an Art dealer, museum curator, and Artists&amp;rsquo; manager, you are about to take on that job! You will promote and nurture Artists; buy, display, and sell their Art; and build and exert your international reputation. As a result, you will achieve the respect needed to draw visitors to your Gallery from all over the world.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;There's a lot of work to be done, but don't worry, you can hire assistants to help you achieve your goals. Build your fortune by running the most lucrative Gallery and secure your reputation as a world-class Gallerist!&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Maximize your money and thus win the game by: &amp;#10;&amp;#10;     having visitors in your gallery; &amp;#10;     exhibiting and selling works of art;&amp;#10;     investing in artists&amp;rsquo; promotion to increase art value;&amp;#10;     achieving trends and reputation as well as curator and dealer goals.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2015" />
						               				<minplayers value="1" />
						               				<maxplayers value="4" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="255">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="100" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="47" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="33" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="139" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="29" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="104" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="96" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="4" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="108" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="80" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="17" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="90" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="150" />
						               				<minplaytime value="60" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="150" />
						               				<minage value="13" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="45">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="16" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="24" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="3" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="26">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="25" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="1" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1021" value="Economic" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2013" value="Commodity Speculation" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2910" value="Investment" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2004" value="Set Collection" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2819" value="Solo / Solitaire Game" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2082" value="Worker Placement" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="25292" value="Crowdfunding: Giochistarter" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="8374" value="Crowdfunding: Kickstarter" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="22135" value="Crowdfunding: Spieleschmiede" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="70948" value="Digital Implementations: Tabletopia" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="57508" value="Game: The Gallerist" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="5666" value="Players: Games with Solitaire Rules" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="56419" value="Theme: Art" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="75406" value="Theme: Fine Art and Art Museums" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="39521" value="Theme: Painting / Paintings" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="193148" value="The Gallerist: KS Stretch Goal Pack #2" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="256676" value="The Gallerist: Scoring Expansion" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="12396" value="Vital Lacerda" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="64844" value="Ian O'Toole" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="597" value="Eagle-Gryphon Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="38809" value="Angry Lion Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30213" value="Fire on Board Jogos" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="50643" value="Fruhling-Honpo" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="7251" value="Giochix.it" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30677" value="Maldito Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="39249" value="sternenschimmermeer" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="11740" />
			<average value="8.04808" />
			<bayesaverage value="7.68414" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="61" bayesaverage="7.68414" />
																				<rank type="family" id="5497" name="strategygames" friendlyname="Strategy Game Rank" value="47" bayesaverage="7.76228" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.35082" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="16215" />
			<trading value="154" />
			<wanting value="1221" />
			<wishing value="5749" />
			<numcomments value="2053" />
			<numweights value="797" />
			<averageweight value="4.2647" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>