<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="22604">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/q5c_53j2tPIJiAATwl4xIw__thumb/img/4NXDVPwaMaPEpQbmtLqWTiZzPQE=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic453474.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/q5c_53j2tPIJiAATwl4xIw__original/img/Wp0xj33A8ZFaWunOO2qezXE4L5Y=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic453474.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="5" value="The Halls of Montezuma" />
				<rulebook>The Halls of Montezuma

Rules of Play
Contents
1.0	
2.0	
3.0	
4.0	
5.0	
6.0	
7.0	
8.0	
9.0	
10.0	
11.0	
12.0	

Introduction.........................................................................2
13.0	 Placement Actions, Fortifications, and Fortresses................12
Components.........................................................................2
14.0	 Naval Movement, Squadrons, Port Seizure, and Blockade...13
Game Concepts....................................................................4
15.0	 Armies................................................................................14
Set Up and Sequence of Play................................................5
16.0	 Raids and Guerillas.............................................................14
Political Will and Victory.....................................................6
17.0	 Discarding and Holding Cards...........................................14
Supply and Control..............................................................6
18.0	 Governmental Status/ End Turn Phase, War Declaration, and .
Random Events Phase and Action Cards..............................7
	
Revolts................................................................................15
© 2008 GMT Games, LLC
Deal Cards Phase and Strategy Cards....................................7
19.0	 Comprehensive Example of Play.........................................16
© 2008 GMT Games,
Action Phase.........................................................................8
	 LLC
Credits ..............................................................................19
Activation Action, Reaction, and Movement into Battle.......9
20.0	 Designers' Notes.................................................................20
Battle..................................................................................10
21.0 Card Histories ....................................................................21
Events.................................................................................12
22.0	 Rules Index .......................................................................24

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC
© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

1

The Halls of Montezuma

The game begins during the period of diplomatic crisis over the
southern border of Texas. During this time, both players may move
and engage in combat, but will have limited flexibility in what can be
accomplished. At some point, the US will declare War, giving both
players more cards to use and more options.
The rules are organized largely according to the Sequence of Play, found
in section 4.0. Major game concepts are found in the rules section where
they are most prominent. The victory conditions are presented first so
players know their goals, although victory is checked at the end of the
Turn. The rules are focused on what you, the players, may do. If what
you want to do is not stated, then you may not do it. Concentrate on
what the rules allow.
The Halls of Montezuma includes:
•	 One 22” x 34” map
•	 Two counter sheets
•	 Three player reference cards
•	 80 Strategy and 30 Action cards
•	 2 ten-sided dice
•	 This Rulebook
If there are any components damaged or missing, please contact us at:
GMT Games
P.O. Box 1308
Hanford, CA 93232-1308
If you have any questions about the rules, we’ll be glad to answer them
if you send them to the address above with a self-addressed, stamped
envelope. For faster response, contact the developer at stratdeveloper@
nac.net, or see us online at talk.consimworld.com. We're in the "PostNapoleonic" folder of the "Individual Games" discussion forum.
References to other rules are noted in parentheses. For example, a
reference to the rule for seizing a port is noted thus:

2.0 	COMPONENTS
2.1	 The Map. The game map represents the theater of war; Units move
from Space to Space (or Zone) as they campaign. Spaces are marked
for terrain and for other game purposes, as noted below and on the
map Legend.
a.		 Map features. Features of note on the map are:	
•	 Spaces cost 1 or more Movement Points (MP) to enter, taken
from a moving Unit’s/Force’s Movement Allowance (MA), as
the Unit/Force enters the Space (10.2). Each Space’s terrain
is as indicated on the Map Legend.
•	 For rules purposes, “in Mexico” means anywhere on the map
except for the Zones and Texas Spaces.
•	 Spaces marked with the Indian symbol are the points of origin
for Raids.
•	 Spaces can be controlled; every Space is under control of one
player or the other at all times during the game (6.7 and Set
Up card).

b.		 Fortresses. The game’s two fortresses, Mejico and Vera Cruz, are
marked on the map; each has an inherent artillery Unit (13.3).
c.		 Connections. Connections allow movement from Space to Space
at the MP cost listed on the Terrain Effects Chart.
d.		 Zones and Movement Arrows. Zones represent larger areas of
land than normal Spaces. They function identically to Spaces,
except as noted. Entry into and exit from Zones are by Movement Arrows. Units are able to move in either direction across
such Arrows.
e.		 Holding Boxes. Each Leader has a command Box. Place all Units
and Subordinate Leaders under a Leader in his Command Box.
Place Guerillas not presently in play in the Guerillas Holding
box.
f.		 Charts and Tables. Charts and tables necessary to play the game
are printed around the edges of the Map and on the player aid
cards.
g.		 Information Track. Mexican Political Will (PW) is the key to
victory (5.1). The track of boxes numbered 0 to 35 is used to
mark the current PW, as well as the US Blockade and Bellicosity
levels. Use the Firepower (FP) markers on this track to calculate
FP in Battle.
h.		 Battle Diagrams. Each player has a Battle diagram facing his
side of the map. Use these to determine total Firepower in Battle
(11.2.f ). Place Units in the appropriate boxes per the Battle
Sequence.
j.		 Mexican States. Mexico is made up of a number of States, separated by the darker boundaries. Each Space in a State contains
the State’s abbreviation, and is faintly color-coded. Each State
also has a corresponding status box, which contains the State’s
name, the State control number (6.9), and boxes for the State
control and Civic State markers. The States of Queretaro and
Guanajuato share a status box owing to space limitations. Place
the markers for both states in the box; both have a State control
number of ‘2’.
2.2	 Units and markers. The game includes two 8 ½” by 11” countersheets. These two sheets contain all the Units and other markers to be
placed on the Map. The play aid card includes a visual representation
and explanation of the Units.
a.		 Combat Units. Combat Units (“Units”) are of three types, Infantry, Cavalry, and Artillery. All combat Units except Guerillas
have two steps. To indicate that the Unit has lost a step, flip it
to its one-step side, or eliminate a Unit already on its one-step
side. The single-step side of the Unit has the white band under
the unit’s strength.

Reduced
Strength bar

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

Commitment
Symbol

Unit
Firepower

Artillery

The Halls of Montezuma is a two-player game based on the MexicanAmerican War—a war that began as a struggle for Texas but soon
changed into two nations battling for empire. One player is the United
States and the other is Mexico. The game attempts to recreate the
War from the point of view of the policy makers of both nations in
the conflict, without too much complexity. Thus, we have abstracted
certain real world factors to make the game playable in about two to
three hours, while retaining what we deemed to be essential features
of the historical situation.

•	 Transit Spaces count for all purposes as normal Spaces except
when specifically noted in the Rules. Transit Spaces are never
controlled for any purpose.
•	 Transit Spaces can cause attrition (10.2.d).
•	 If three or more Spaces and/or Transit Spaces are part of a
triple connection, all are adjacent to each other.

Cavalry

1.0 	 Introduction

Infantry

2

Unit
Identifier

The Halls of Montezuma

a

a

a

d

d
d

3

a

j
j

d
a

d

a

a

d

a

a

a

a

a

c

a

c

j

c

h
e
j

j
j

j

j
g

j

j

j

j

h

c

b
d

b

a

j

e

j

j

j

d
j

1.	 I	 nfantry Units are regiments of foot soldiers, between 300
and 1000 troops. Each strength point represents about 300
to 500 men. Infantry Units include:
•	 Regulars: Professional, trained infantry.
•	 Activa Militia (Mexico) and Volunteers (USA): Regiments
raised by Mexican and American States, less experienced and
not well trained. Generally, may not be committed in Battle.
•	 Zapadores (Mexican sappers): These troops give an advantage in Battle involving fortifications (11.2.f and the
Battle Results Table).
•	 Guerrillas: Irregular troops skilled in hit-and-run tactics.
•	 Marines: Marines generally function as normal Infantry
Units. In addition, US Marines have special rules for Amphibious Landings (14.2.c).

State
Volunteers

Infantry /
Artillery

Guerrilas

Marines

Design Note: The minimal difference in FP between Units at full
and reduced strength reflects the use of Unit reserves, discipline,
and cohesion. The step loss represents more a loss of cohesion rather
than a loss of men. Being returned to Regroup does not mean all
the soldiers have been killed, but that the Unit has lost its cohesion
and needs to be reorganized.

Regulars

Play Note: The Combat strength for many Units is the same on
both their full and reduced strength sides. If a player has one of each
type in a Battle, add 1 to the Force’s FP.

Zapadores

The small boxed letters on the map correspond to the features described on p. 2

Play Note: US Units marked with a red band at the top of the
Counter (US Regulars & State Militias) enter play only after the
US has declared War on Mexico.
2.	 Cavalry Units represent regiments of 100 to 1000 mounted
troops, 200 to 300 mounted men per strength point. Cavalry
may withdraw before Battle per 11.2.b. Cavalry receives
benefits per the play of Strategy cards.
3.	 Artillery Units represent 20 to 25 guns per strength point.
The US 1st through 4th Artillery Units are considered both
Artillery and Infantry.
b.		 Leaders. Leaders command Units. Leader counters carry stars
and ratings. The stars are used for combat commitment, replacement attempts, and other functions. The reverse of most Leader
counters is marked “REPL”; this side is used in case a Leader

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

4

OPS Value

dies in Battle (11.3). Santa Anna’s replacement is Valencia, who
has a separate counter. Each Leader is rated for:
•	 Strategy—How easy it is to Activate a Leader and get him
moving (1 = easiest, 4=most difficult).
•	 Command—The number of Units he can command for
movement (3.5). This rating also denotes rank—subordinate
Leaders must have the same or lower command rating as the
Force Commander.
•	 Tactics—His ability in Battle and troop management.

Blue=US Event
Green=Mex Event
Blue/Green=Either

Game Period
Indicator
Headline
and Text

Strategy
Command
Tactics

Leaders may be left alone in a Space; Leaders alone may NOT
enter a Space with enemy Units. If an enemy Unit/Force enters
a Space with a Leader alone, and that Space does not contain
a fortress (13.3), that Leader must be placed with a friendly
Unit/Force within 5 Spaces. If no such Unit/Force exists, the
Leader is eliminated and his replacement becomes available in
the Leader Pool (3.2).
Design Note: Valencia was the military and political rival to Santa
Anna. In the Event of the latter’s demise, Valencia would have been
the obvious new political choice of the Army and people of Mexico.
In our view, Santa Anna was not spectacular in battle—hence his
rating of ‘1’.
2.3	 Markers. Markers are included for fortifications, control of Spaces,
raided Spaces, game record tracks and the effects of various Events.
Their use is explained in the applicable rules or on Event cards. The
markers included are an absolute limit except for the Space control
markers. Key markers are:
a.		 Fortifications. The game includes three types of fortifications,
two of which are on markers—fieldworks and forts. Place fieldworks and forts with their “?” side up—although the owning
player may look at the marker’s face at any time. Fortresses are
printed on the map at Mejico and Vera Cruz.

Forts

Fieldworks

b.		 State Control/Civic State. These markers determine whether
a Mexican State is under US or Mexican control (6.9) and is
“Calm” or in “Revolt” (18.4).
c.		 Space control. These indicate which side controls a Space (6.7).
2.4 The Die. A ten-sided die is used to resolve combat and a number
of other game mechanics. Read the ‘0’ as zero, not ten.
2.5 Player Aid Cards. The Player Aid Cards contain the charts and
tables to play the game. The Turn Record track allows players to track
the game Turn. This track also includes each Turn’s mandatory Events
(7.1.a), the War die roll modifier (18.3.a), the declaration of War Political Will cost (18.3.b), and the end game die roll (18.7) for each Turn.
2.6 The cards. The 110 playing cards are divided into two smaller
decks. The 30 Action cards cause random Events and determine
movement/attrition of active Units /Forces. The Strategy deck has two
sets of cards—Crisis and War, distinguished by the red “Crisis” band
across the top of the cards for use during the Crisis Period. Add the
War strategy cards to the deck after the US declaration of War (18.3).
When in conflict, the card’s text prevails over the rules.

Movement Chart
Response
Card
Indicator

Supply Event
Indicator

Remove
Indicator

Naval
Capability
Indicator

3.0	 GAME CONCEPTS
3.1	 Key Terms. The following terms are crucial to play of the game—
the rules reference indicates the location of their main explanation.
They are capitalized throughout.
•	 Space—one of the locations on the map into which Units can
move (2.1).
•	 Unit—one of the playing pieces representing the troops which
fought during the War (2.2.a).
•	 Leader—any of the generals available to move Units around
(2.2.b).
•	 Regroup—where Units not in play are placed—a coffee mug
would work perfectly (3.2).
•	 Commander—a Leader in command of a Force (3.5) or Army
(15.0).
•	 Force—one or more Units (and Leaders) under a Commander;
may be an Army (3.5).
•	 Event—the actions described on the face of a card (7.1b and 12.0);
Event titles are printed in Italics.
•	 Battle—combat between Units and Forces, occurring during
activation and movement (11.0).
•	 Army—a Force with an Army marker placed by card play (15.0).
•	 War—the game begins during the period of Crisis over the border
of Texas; during the game the US declares War in one of a variety
of ways (18.3).
3.2	Regroup/Leader Pool. Each side should have a container (a mug)
as its Regroup box. Place Units available but not in play in Regroup;
place Units eliminated during play back into Regroup. Place Leaders
available but not yet in play at any convenient location on the table.
Do not place Scott or Santa Anna in these Leader Pools. Draw Units
from Regroup and Leaders from the Leader Pool randomly, unless
specifically stated (e.g., the Scott Invades Event requires a Marine Unit).
3.3	 Stacking. No more than 15 Units, plus any number of Leaders
and markers, may end an Action or Phase in one Space. If more are
present, the owning player must eliminate Units in excess of 15. Players
may always inspect the contents of enemy stacks. The Baggage Train
does not count towards stacking. 	Zones have no stacking limit.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma
3.4	Reinforcements. Players receive reinforcements during the course
of the game; most arrive by card play, but some arrive by mandated
Event. Place reinforcement Units at full strength, drawing them from
Regroup. The player must take the number of Units indicated, unless
Regroup is empty. In this case, the reinforcements are lost. Except for
Scott and Santa Anna, randomly draw reinforcement Leaders from
the Leader Pool. Unless stated on the card, place reinforcements as
follows:
•	 US reinforcements—New Orleans or any friendly, in supply
Texas Spaces.
•	 Mexican reinforcements—any friendly, in supply Political Will
Cities.
3.5	 The Force. A “Force” is any group of Units and Leaders subordinate to a particular Leader (the “Commander”). An “Army” is a Force
with an Army marker. Unless otherwise specified, the term “Force”
applies to Forces and Armies. The number of Units allowed in a Force
is the “Force activation limit”. A Force need not include all the Units
in a Space.
a.		 Designation. Designate a Force at the moment of activation,
interception or avoiding battle. A Force contains a Commander,
no more than one subordinate Leader, and a number of Units up
to the Commander’s command rating. An Army is a Force with
an Army marker, and contains a Commander, any number of
subordinate Leaders, and Units up to the total of the combined
command ratings of the Commander and one subordinate. The
Baggage Train does not count towards stacking.
b.		 Timing. Forces need not be designated except as described in
3.5.a. At all other times, any number of Leaders and Units can
coexist in a Space (up to the stacking limit of 15 Units).
3.6	 Santa Anna. At start, place the Santa Anna Leader counter in the
“In Exile” box. Santa Anna is governed by the following:
a.		 Initial Placement. Santa Anna comes out of Exile and enters
play on the first of the following to occur:
•	 Action card Event: Santa Anna Returns from Exile is played
during the Random Events Phase (7.0).
•	 Strategy card Event: Santa Anna Elected President is played
during the Action Phase (9.0).
•	 Declaration of War: Place Santa Anna with 4 Units in Mejico
fortress at the beginning of the Turn following the US declaration of War—immediately if the US player declares War at
the beginning of a Turn (18.3.b).
b.		 Return to play. After removal by Santa Anna in Exile, place him
back in the "Exiled" box. Roll the die during the Random Events
Phase. On a 5 or higher, place Santa Anna in Mejico fortress. If
the roll was 4 or lower, roll again next turn. Santa Anna Elected
President also returns him to play if in exile.
c.		 Normal leader. In all other respects, Santa Anna is a normal
Leader.
3.7	 Initiative. From the beginning of the game until the nations are
at War, Mexico has the initiative. From the moment the US declares
War until the end of the game, the US has the initiative.

4.0	 SET-UP AND SEQUENCE OF PLAY
4.1	 Game Set-up. Refer to the Set Up card to prepare for play.
4.2	Turn Sequence of Play. Each game Turn consists of a series of
Phases; complete all Phases and their Segments in the order stated.
A.	 	Random Event Phase (7.0).
•	 Implement all Events noted on the Turn Record track, in the
order stated.

5

•	 The players alternate drawing and executing four action cards
each, initiative player first. Execute each Event immediately
(7.1.b).
•	 Roll for Santa Anna’s return (3.6.b).
•	 The US player may declare War, paying the Turn’s PW penalty
(18.3.b). From Turn 4 on, reactivate an inactive squadron
(14.3).
B.	 	Deal Cards Phase (8.0).
•	 Deal each player the appropriate number of Strategy cards
(8.1).
•	 Beginning with the initiative player, each player may draw
one extra card, moving the PW marker 1 in the other player’s
favor.	
C.	 Action Phase (9.0).
•	 The players alternate playing Strategy cards, the initiative
player determining who plays first (7.1.b).
•	 Each card play allows the player to engage in one action at
the player’s discretion:
1.	 Activate Leaders, Units, and Forces to move (10.0), suppress revolts (10.3), establish control of a Zone (10.4),
resolve a siege (10.5) and engage in Battle (11.0).
2.	 Execute the Event on the card (12.0).
3.	 Place control markers (13.1), fortifications (13.2), replacements (13.4), or the Baggage Train (13.5).
4.	 Make a Naval Move (14.1), conduct an Amphibious
Landing (14.2), Activate a squadron (14.3), or Seize a
Port (14.4).
5.	 Organize an Army (15.0).
6.	 Raid Spaces (16.1) or Hide/Reveal a Guerilla (Mexican
player only—16.5).
7.	 Discard or Hold a card (17.0).
•	 Execute the Supply Event (9.2) on play of Logistics or a Strategy
card with the Supply Wagon icon. The Supply Event automatically happens on play of the Logistics card. If another card with
the Supply Wagon card is played, roll the die—if the roll is
less than or equal to the OPS value of the card, the Supply
Event takes place. Each Turn does not have to have a Supply
Event; the Turn may have a maximum of one.
•	 The Action Phase ends per 9.0.
D.	 Governmental Status/End Turn Phase (18.0).
•	 Spaces may change control because of the presence of enemy
Units/Forces (18.1).
•	 Remove isolated control markers and determine which Mexican States are under US control (18.1.a–b).
•	 The Mexican player determines if the Mexican government
collapses (18.2).
•	 If the US is NOT at War, the US player rolls on the Declaration of War Table (18.3.a).
•	 Both players determine if any active revolts spread (18.4.a).
•	 Change PW for raids, State control, and revolts; remove Raid
markers (18.5).
•	 Check for victory (5.2).
•	 On turns so noted on the Turn Record track, roll to see if the
game ends; if the game ends, check victory (18.7).
•	 Shuffle all Action cards and move the Turn marker to the
next Turn.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

6

5.0	 POLITICAL WILL AND VICTORY
5.1	 Mexican Political Will. The Mexican Political Will track is a
quantitative measure of Mexico’s willingness to fight the US. Various
Events throughout the game add and subtract points from
Political Will, as noted on the PW Chart. When a PW award
benefits Mexico, move the marker up the track; when the
award benefits the US, move the marker down.
a.		 Raids (16.0). Each raid is worth ½ PW (16.4.a).
b.		 Political Will Cities. Whenever a PW city changes control, PW
will change. Roll the die; add the PW modifiers from the PW
city’s marker and from the map, subtract one if Santa Anna is
President, and refer to the City Conquest Table to determine
the PW effect.
c.		 Battle. Battle affects PW per the PW Chart; all effects are cumulative.
d.		 States in revolt or under US control. The Mexican player loses
PW each Turn for each State in revolt and/or controlled by the
US player (18.5.b).
5.2	 Victory. Determine victory during the Government Status/End
Turn Phase. Check to see if one of the two situations below applies:
a.		 Sudden Death. A player fulfills his nation’s Sudden Death Victory conditions by occupying Spaces. Occupying a Space means
that the Space is in supply, has at least one friendly Unit in the
Space, and is under friendly control. If a Zone is involved, enemy
Units may also be present.
•	 The US wins if the US simultaneously occupies Vera Cruz,
Mexico City, Saltillo, Alta California, and Monterrey, and has
more Units in the Disputed Zone.
•	 Mexico wins if Mexico occupies five or more Texas Spaces
and has at least one Leader and two more Units than the US
in the Disputed Zone.
b.		 PW Victory. If the game ends at the end of a Turn per 18.7, the
Mexican player wins unless one of the following two conditions
applies:
•	 Mexican Government Collapse. If the Mexican Political Will
is 10 or less, the US wins (18.2). 	
•	 No Government Collapse. If the Mexican Political Will is 1
or less, the US wins.
5.3	Tournament Bidding. In tournaments, or if both players want
to play the same side, each player should write down a bid of at least
0 Political Will points. The higher bidder plays the favored side, unless
the losing player wishes then to bid higher than the current high bid.
Bidding may proceed with the players alternating, until one player
concedes the bid. The winner plays the favored side; change the Political Will by an amount equal to the bid in favor of the bid’s loser.

6.0	 SUPPLY AND CONTROL
Design Note: We have modeled the logistics in the game with some randomness to capture varied factors in an abstract sense, such as weather, local
road conditions, low level raiding, and, simply put, bad management of
the supply lines and bases. Like any good strategist, you are always going to
be concerned with your supply lines, but the “supply line test” in the game
happens in an uncertain way to generate sufficient tension without making
the game-play so calculating. You can push your Forces further from the
base of operations, perhaps to exploit an enemy weakness, but in this game
you can’t rely on a specified timing of the Supply Event. Instead, a player
could see a Force sitting beyond its limit or recently cut off and play a card
to attempt to trigger the Supply Event—this makes the strategy card with

a high OPS number a valuable card to play when the conditions are right.
In this game, as Mexico retreats to interior lines and difficult terrain, the
Americans could get tempted to do too much without safeguarding their
supply line.	
Success in the game revolves around supply and control. Supply allows Units and Forces to function at full effect. Control of Spaces and
States allows tracing supply, affects PW, and other aspects of the game.
Because supply and control issues affect many activities in many phases,
they are presented here. The Supply Event, when the supply status is
checked for all Units and Forces, is executed per 9.2.
6.1	 Supply Status. Supply requires tracing a supply line from a Space
to a supply source. If a Space is in supply, all Units and Forces in the
Space are in supply. Check supply during the Action Phase on execution of the Supply Event (9.2). A Space must also be in supply at other
times noted in the rules, including, for example, building fortifications,
taking replacements, establishing control over Spaces, and engaging in
Battle.
6.2	 Supply Lines. A supply line is an unbroken chain of up to five
eligible Spaces from the Space being checked to a supply source. The
Space being checked does not count towards the length of the supply
line, but the supply source Space does. A Rough connection costs
two towards the length of the supply line. Supply lines may be traced
through Spaces and Transit Spaces. Each Space must be friendly; no
Space may contain an enemy Unit. In addition, each Space must be
•	 either clear terrain or non-clear terrain containing a friendly fortification or Baggage Train,
•	 free of a Raid marker, unless a friendly Unit or Baggage Train is
in the Space, and
•	 not in a State in revolt, unless the Baggage Train is in the Space.
6.3	 Supply Sources. A given supply source may supply any number
of Units. Trace supply to the following sources:
•	 United States—a friendly Texas Space, a port (6.4.a), a Zone (6.4.b
and 6.4.c), the beachhead or the U.S. Baggage Train marker (6.5).
•	 Mexico—a friendly PW City, a Zone (6.4.b & 6.4.c), Sonora State
(6.4.d), or the Mexican Baggage Train (6.5).
6.4	 Supply source details. Apply the following as appropriate:
a.		 Ports. One port per coast may serve as a supply source for one
US Force (but NOT an Army). Supply must be traced
to it normally. The Beachhead marker allows a second
port to serve as a supply source for any number of
Forces (including Armies). Supply through a port
requires the appropriate squadron to be active. If the squadron is
seizing a port (14.4), it is considered active for supply purposes.
b.		 The Disputed Zone. Up to three Units of each side are automatically in supply in the Disputed Zone. A player with at least as
many Units therein as the other player may trace a supply line
through the Disputed Zone, which counts as three Spaces.
c.		 Alta and Baja California. One Unit from each side is automatically in supply in each of Alta California and Baja California. A
player controlling Alta California may use it as a supply source
for one Force outside the Zone, including by sea per 6.4.a. The
Force supplied from Alta California may be a different Force
for each supply check.
Example: During a Supply Event early in the Action Phase, a Force
in Space X is supplied from Alta California. During the next card
play, another Force moves from Space Y—in supply from a Texas
Space—and engages in combat in Space Z, which can trace supply
to Alta California. The Force suffers neither movement attrition nor
the adverse Battle effect of being out-of-supply.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma
d.		 Sonora. During the Supply Event only, three Mexican Units are
automatically in supply in Sonora State. All other Units trace
normally.
e.		 Raid markers. A raid marker in a supply source Space prevents
use of the Space as a supply source, unless a friendly Unit or the
Baggage Train is in the Space.
6.5	 The Baggage Train. Each player has one Baggage Train, which is
used as follows:
a.		 Supply Source. The Baggage Train is a supply source in any
type of Space or Transit Space. Trace a supply line into and out
of the Baggage Train’s Space regardless of terrain. The friendly
Baggage Train must itself trace a valid supply line to another
friendly supply source (the US Baggage Train may trace to the
Beachhead marker, and vice versa). Even if out of supply, the
Baggage Train may be eliminated during the Supply Event to
supply all Units /Forces which can trace to it.
b.		 Movement and Capture. The Baggage Train moves only as
part of a Force, at the Force’s MA. The Baggage Train does not
count against the Force activation limit. A Baggage Train may
be left alone in a Space; if one or more enemy Units enter that
Space, the Baggage Train is immediately captured. Move the PW
marker 1 Space in favor of the capturing player. The Baggage
Train reenters on play of a Strategy card (13.5).
c.		 Beachhead. The US Beachhead functions as an immobile Baggage Train in the port Space.

6.6	Out-of-supply Effects. During the Supply Event (9.2), the owning player eliminates one-half (rounded up) of all steps in each out-ofsupply Space. If present, at least one Cavalry step must be eliminated.
If any connection to the Space is a River Connection, eliminate one
less step. In addition, at the moment of certain game activities, check
the supply status of the Unit/Force involved. An out-of-supply Unit/
Force
•	 May not build forts/fieldworks, take replacements, or establish
control over Spaces.
•	 Takes movement attrition if it moves.
•	 Suffers a FP penalty in Battle.
6.7	 Space control. All Spaces are controlled by one side or the other
at all times during the game. "Friendly" refers to anything belonging
to your side, "enemy" to anything beloning to the other player. Use
the control markers primarily in the other player's country. Use them
within your own country for clarity. Removal
of an enemy control marker in your own
country is the equivalent for all purposes to
placing one of your own.	
a.		 Spaces. Control of Spaces changes through (a) winning a Battle
(11.2.j), (b) the Place control marker action (13.1), or (c) occupying the Space at the end of the Turn (18.1).
b.		 Transit Spaces. Transit Spaces cannot be controlled; trace supply lines through them normally. Transit Spaces may be raided;
Raid markers block supply lines for both sides. Moving into or
from one or more transit Spaces results in a movement attrition
check (10.2.d).
c.		 Isolated control markers. During the Governmental Status
Phase, isolated control markers are removed (18.1.a).

7

Play Note: A player need only place control markers in the player’s own
country for purposes of clarity. Friendly Spaces in a player’s own country
can never be isolated.
6.8	 Zone control. At start, Mexico controls Baja and Alta California
as well as Yucatan. The US controls New Orleans. The Disputed Zone
is never controlled, but both sides may use it as if it were friendly.
Change control of a Zone per 13.1.
6.9	 State control. All Mexican States, including Yucatan, Baja
California, and Alta California Zones, begin the game under Mexican
control. Each State has a State control number in its State Status Box.
If the US controls Spaces in the State greater than or equal
to this number, the US controls the State. The US controls
a Zone when the US has the only Units in the Zone. State
control affects PW and Mexican Government collapse.

7.0	RANDOM EVENTS PHASE AND
ACTION CARDS
7.1	 The Random Events Phase. The Random Events Phase includes
both mandated Events (printed on the Turn Record track) and Action
card Events. Conduct the Phase as follows:
a.		 Mandated Events. First, execute all Events on the Turn Record
track in the order stated; some may not apply in particular situations.
b.		 Action cards. Next, the players alternate drawing two Action
cards each, beginning with the initiative player. Execute each
Event immediately, regardless of beneficiary.
•	 The player of the card receives friendly reinforcements when
a card has reinforcements for both players.
•	 Each player receives reinforcements from a maximum of
one card per Random Events Phase. On drawing a second,
continue drawing until a non-reinforcement card is drawn.
Returns from Exile counts as a Mexican reinforcement card.
c.		 Santa Anna’s return. If Santa Anna was exiled during play, roll
to see if he returns (3.6.b).
d.		 War. The US player may declare War (18.3.b).
7.2	 Action cards. In addition to Random Events, Action cards also
determine the Movement Allowances (MA) for moving Units and
Forces. Reshuffle the Action deck at the beginning of each Turn. In
addition, if the Action deck is exhausted during the Action Phase, the
deck should be reshuffled. To reshuffle the Action deck, combine both
undrawn cards and played cards and shuffle.

8.0	DEAL CARDS PHASE AND
STRATEGY CARDS
The Strategy cards drive play of The Halls of Montezuma. The players
move, fight, build forts, execute Events and do virtually everything
else through the play of cards. The information included on the face
of each Strategy card indicates the Operations Level of the card (OPS),
an Event, the ability to naval move a Force, and the possibility of a
Supply Event. The American player may play the Event on the card if
the Event symbol is in Blue or in both colors; the Mexican player may
play the Event if the symbol is in Green or both colors.
8.1	Deal cards. Each player receives a hand of cards in the Deal cards
Phase. A held card (17.2) counts towards the hand. Determine hand
size as follows:

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

8
Crisis Period

The number indicated on the Turn Record
track, Tejas! forming part of Mexico's hand
on Turn 1

War before Mexican
government collapse

Both players: 9 cards

War after collapse

Mexican player: 7 cards
US player: 9 cards

8.2	 Strategy card deck. At the beginning of the game separate the
thirty Crisis Strategy cards from the fifty War cards (2.5). Set the War
cards aside, and shuffle the Crisis cards to form the Draw pile. Use
only the Crisis Strategy cards until the US declares War. When the US
declares War, add the rest (18.3.e).
8.3	 Strategy card play. Place each card played into a discard pile,
unless the card is removed. Players may always check the number of
cards left in the deck or in the other player’s hand, and examine the
discarded or removed cards. A card may be played for ONE Action
per Action Phase.
a.		 Removal. Remove the cards marked “Remove” from play when
played for their Event.
b.		 Reshuffle. To reshuffle, take the discard pile and combine it with
any undealt cards, and shuffle. If the deck is reshuffled during
the Deal cards Phase, resume dealing at the point at which the
deck was exhausted. Use the Reshuffle marker as a reminder.
The deck is reshuffled in three situations:
•	 Deck Exhaustion—the draw pile runs out of cards when
more are needed for the deal.
•	 “Reshuffle” card—at the end of any Turn in which a card
marked “Reshuffle” is played for an Event.
•	 Declaration of War—When the US declares War, reshuffle
the new, combined deck.
c.		 Response cards. Some Events respond to the actions of the other
player as described on the card. When a response card is played
as an Event, do not check for the Supply Event.
d.		 Supply Event check. Check for the Supply Event each time a
card with the Supply Wagon icon is played (9.2). The Supply
Event does not occur when a card is played in response.

9.0	 ACTION PHASE
During the Action Phase, players alternate playing Strategy cards. The
player with the initiative determines the first player. Each card allows
one action to take place. The Action Phase ends when one of the following occurs: (a) both players have played all their cards (including
holding the last one) or (b) one player has held the last card, and the
other has played them all.
9.1	 Actions. Each card play allows the player to execute one of the
following actions, as detailed in 9.3–9.9:
•	 Activate Leaders, Units, and Forces to move, engage in Battle,
suppress revolts, or place a control marker in a Zone.
•	 Execute the Event on the card.
•	 Place/Remove control markers, fortifications, replacements, or
the Baggage Train.
•	 Make a Naval Move with a Force, Activate a squadron, or Seize
a Port.
•	 Organize an Army.
•	 Raid Spaces or Hide/Reveal a Guerilla (Mexican player only).
•	 Discard or Hold a card.

9.2	 The Supply Event. Play of Logistics automatically dictates the
execution of the Supply Event. On play of any other card bearing the
Supply Wagon icon, roll a die. If the roll is less than or equal to the
OPS value of the card, execute the Supply Event. Subtract 1 from the
die in all Heat Turns. No more than one Supply Event takes place per
Turn. During the Supply Event:
•	 Check supply for each Space containing a Unit or Force,
•	 Eliminate one-half (rounded up) of all steps in each out-of-supply
Space, including at least one cavalry step if present. Reduce the total
step loss by one if the Space has at least one Rio Grande connection to it (this does not prevent the cavalry step loss required), and
•	 Check for the effect of the Blockade—roll a die; if the roll is less
than or equal to the Blockade level, draw one Mexican Unit from
Regroup and remove it from the game.
9.3	 Activation. Either player may use a card for OPS to activate
Leaders alone, or a Unit/Force in a Space. Active Forces may move
(10.0), suppress revolts (10.3), establish control over a Zone (10.4),
resolve a siege (10.5), and engage in Battle (11.0). Draw an Action
card to determine the movement allowance (MA) for individual Units
or Forces (10.1). An out of supply Unit/Force may be activated.	
•	 Leaders alone. Each Leader activated costs 1 OPS.
•	 Individual Units. Activate one combat Unit with the play of any
OPS value card. The Unit activated may be anywhere on the Map.
•	 Force. Activate a Force using a Strategy card with an OPS value
greater than or equal to the Force Commander’s Strategy rating.
Play and Design Note: Lower rated (that is, better) Leaders tend to move
greater distances than higher rated Leaders; all Leaders can fail to move,
but higher rated ones are more likely to. The Action cards account for the
probabilities associated with command, aggressiveness, and command
failure. Note that an Army is always guaranteed to move at least one Space.
9.4	 Events (12.0). A player plays a card for its Event when the Event
symbol is in the player’s color or in both colors. Events may be played
freely within the conditions on the card.
9.5	 Placement (13.0). The placement action allows players to establish
control over Spaces, build fieldworks or forts, place replacements in a
Force, or return the Baggage Train to play.
9.6	Naval activation/Movement (14.0). Play of any OPS value card
allows a Leader or Unit alone to move from friendly port to friendly
port. Play of a 2, 3, or 4 OPS card allows the US player to activate a
squadron. Play of a 4 OPS card allows either player to move a Force
from port-to-port or the US player to conduct an Amphibious Landing.
9.7	Organize (15.0). Play of a 2, 3, or 4 OPS value card allows a
player to organize an Army.
9.8	Raid (16.0). Play of any card allows a player to conduct Indian
and Guerilla raids up to the card’s OPS value ­­­(16.2). In addition, the
Mexican player may hide or reveal a Guerilla Unit (16.5).
9.9	Discard/Hold (17.0). Discarding a card counts as the player’s
Strategy card play. A player may hold a card if only one card remains
in hand. The card may be held for play later in the current Action
Phase, or until the next Turn.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

10.0	 ACTIVATION ACTION,
REACTION, AND MOVEMENT INTO
BATTLE
Units/Forces move when activated per 9.3. Units move with the Movement Allowances (MA) determined by 10.1. A Leader, Unit, or Force
is active until it has spent all its MP or stops for some other reason.
Determine the MA and engage in the activites outlined in 10.2–10.5.
Reaction may occur per 10.6–10.8.
10.1 Movement Allowances. Leaders moving alone have an MA of
10 Movement Points (MP). For Units and Forces, draw an Action
card to determine the MA. Refer to the Movement Chart, and find
the Commander’s Strategy Rating. The number below it is the MA.
Units moving alone have a Strategy Rating of 4. An underlined MA
causes attrition. An Army (15.0) always has a minimum of 1 MP, even
if the Action card lists an MA of ‘0’. Subtract 1 from listed MA for all
Armies, to the minimum of 1.
10.2 Movement. Leaders/Units/Forces move from Space to Space,
spending MP per the Terrain Effects Chart to use connections and enter
Spaces. The MA may never be exceeded in a given activation, and MP
may not carry over from activation to activation. Reaction­—interception (10.6) and avoiding Battle (10.7)—occurs during movement.
Battle costs an activated Force MP to determine Battle Type (11.2.a).
a.		 Special cases. Apply the following as appropriate:
•	 Movement into a Zone costs all remaining MP.
•	 Movement out of a Zone costs 1 MP plus the cost to enter
the Space.
•	 After play of Topographic Engineers, American Units and Forces
may move through a Rough or Jungle Space but must then stop
in the next Space entered; they always stop in Rough/Jungle.
•	 Units may be dropped off but not picked up during activation
and movement.
•	 A moving Unit/Force may freely move into or through enemyControlled Spaces.
•	 An Army may spend an extra MP in an enemy Space to make
it friendly.
b.		 Enemy occupied Spaces. Enemy-occupied Spaces contain either
enemy Unit(s) or unoccupied fortifications. Apply the following
as appropriate:
•	 Units and Leaders moving alone may not enter enemyoccupied Spaces.
•	 Leaders alone in a Space (except for a fortress—see 13.3)
do not hinder enemy movement; retreat or eliminate such
Leaders (2.2.b).
•	 The moving Force must attack any enemy Unit(s) in the
Space (11.0).
•	 A Force enters a Space containing an enemy fort or fieldworks
(but no Units) by paying the normal MP cost.
•	 A Force leaves a Space containing an enemy fort or fieldworks
by paying 1 MP; see 13.3 for fortresses.
•	 Units /Forces enter Zones freely regardless of the presence of
enemy Units.
•	 Mexican units may never enter New Orleans.
c.		 Movement Attrition. Movement attrition causes an active Unit/
Force to lose 1 step. Units suffer movement attrition in six ways.
Attrition is cumulative, but never eliminates the last step in the
moving Unit/Force. Units suffer movement attrition only if they
expend 1 or more MP. Determine attrition in the last Space of
movement, before paying MP for Battle (if enemy-occupied).

9

A moving Unit/Force must take attrition when it moves
•	 during a Heat Turn.
•	 using an underlined MA on the Action card (10.1).
•	 after play of some Strategy cards.
•	 when activated in an out-of-supply Space (6.6).
•	 in a State in revolt (18.4).
•	 in one or more Transit Spaces and fails the Transit Space roll
(10.2.d).
d.		 Transit Space attrition. Transit Spaces may cause attrition. Roll
a die at the end of movement. If the roll is less than or equal to
the number of transit Spaces moved from, through, or into, the
activated Unit/Force takes movement attrition.
e.		 Movement into Battle. Battle occurs when an active Force enters a Space containing one or more enemy Unit(s). The enemy
unit(s) may already be in the Space, or they may intercept into
it.
f.		 Movement into and out of Zones. Battle is never required in
a Zone; both players may have Units/Forces in the same Zone.
Activate a Unit/Force normally in a Zone.
g.	 	 Guerilla Units. Guerrillas alone move as Units alone, except
they may enter Spaces containing enemy Units. Only Canales
may lead Guerillas as a Force (and never as an Army). Canales
may be subordinate to another Leader. On entry, place Guerilla
Units in Rough Spaces. Guerrillas may be in a Force with other
Units.
Design Note: Guerilla Units are a potential Mexican asset; there is, however, no framework of central control over their operations. The Guerillas
are always there, so to speak, but only have an impact when the Mexican
player expends resources in a manner that exerts control. In effect, any card
becomes a “Guerillas Attack” response card.
10.3 Revolt Suppression. Either player may suppress revolts during
the Action Phase. Activate a Force normally. The Force may move
before suppressing the revolt, but suffers movement attrition. Once
the Force has stopped in a Space in the State in revolt, determine its
remaining MA (which can be ‘0’). Then, roll a die. Subtract the Force
Commander’s Tactics rating. If the net die roll is equal to or less than
the remaining MA, the suppression attempt succeeds. If the unmodified roll is ‘9’, then the Force loses a step. A Force receiving ‘0’ MP as
a result of the Action card may attempt to suppress with an MA of 0.
An underlined MA causes movement attrition.
10.4 Control of Zones. A Force in an enemy-controlled Zone may
place a friendly control marker in the Zone if no enemy Units are
present. Activate the Force normally. Establishing control of a Zone
costs the entire MA of the Force (even if ‘0’). An underlined MA causes
movement attrition.
10.5  Siege. Siege occurs when a US Force is activated in a fortress
Space containing no other Mexican Units (13.3). Activate the Force
and draw the Action card. As long as the MA is not ‘0’, the Force may
attack the fortress; take attrition normally. This activation may be intercepted. Resolve Battle against the fortress normally. The fortress is
destroyed if the US wins the Battle and inflicts at least two step losses
on the fortress. Place a US fieldworks marker and control marker in
the Space (if the Space is in supply).
10.6 Reaction Movement. During an activation, the opposing player
may engage in reaction movement—Interception or avoid Battle. Reaction in Zones is covered in 10.9. Each Space a moving Unit/Force
enters allows interception and avoidance, which may be made in either
order. Reaction takes place after the MP is spent to enter the Space but
before determining attrition and Battle Type. To intercept or avoid,
roll a die and add the reacting Force Commander’s Tactics rating. On
a roll of 5 or higher, the reaction move is successful.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

10

The Halls of Montezuma

10.7 Interception. Interception occurs when the active enemy
Unit/Force enters a Space adjacent to a friendly Force. Designate the
intercepting Force and roll the die. If the roll is successful, place the
intercepting Force in the Space the enemy enters; the subsequent Battle
is a Hasty Attack (11.2.a). If the attempt fails, the Force remains in its
Space; it may attempt to intercept again during the same activation.
a.		 Eligibility. Make no more than one interception attempt into
each Space a moving Unit/Force enters. An intercepting Force
need not include all Units in a Space, but it may not exceed
the Force activation limits. Otherwise, a given Unit or Leader
may be part of any number of interception attempts during an
activation or Action Phase.
b.		 Interception Details. The following provisions apply to all
interceptions:
•	 An intercepting Force receives the benefit of any friendly
fortification in the Space.
•	 Interception adds 1 to the defender’s Efficiency die roll
(11.2.g).	
•	 A Force may intercept into a friendly-occupied Space.
•	 An intercepted Guerilla Unit attacks the intercepting Force,
but must retreat after the Battle (if it survives)—the intercepting Force in this case never retreats.
•	 Leaders moving alone may not be intercepted.
10.8 Battle avoidance. When an active Force moves into Battle, one
Unit alone or one Force in the Space may attempt to avoid Battle.
An avoiding Force need not include all Units, but Units remaining
behind may not avoid Battle themselves. If the roll is successful, place
the avoiding Unit/Force in any adjacent Space which neither contains
enemy Units nor was the Space the active Force moved from.
a.		 Failure Penalty. A Unit/Force which fails its avoid Battle roll
may not commit Units in the subsequent Battle. In addition,
lower its Battle Efficiency roll by 1.
b.		 Mexican avoidance in Rough and Jungle. A Mexican Unit or
Force in a Rough, Jungle, or Rough/Jungle Space automatically
avoids Battle prior to the play of Topographic Engineers.
c.		 Avoidance from a Fort/Fortress. A Unit/Force may avoid out
of a fort/fortress normally. If the avoid roll fails, however, it is
attacked in the Space without benefit of the fortification. Ignore
Unit(s) left behind during this Battle. If the Unit/Force which
failed to avoid also loses the Battle, it retreats back “into” the fort/
fortress. The attacking Force may then attack the fort/fortress
in a Pitched Battle. If it does not so attack, place the attacking
Force in the Space it entered from. This rule allows two Battles
in the same Space.
d.		 Destination of avoiding Units. Place the Unit/Force successfully
avoiding Battle in an adjacent Space which (a) does not contain
enemy Units, and (b) was not the Space from which the active
Force entered the Space. An avoiding Unit/Force may always
avoid into an adjacent Zone.
e.		 Continued Movement. If the avoid attempt empties the Space,
the active Unit/Force may continue moving. If the active Force/
Unit again enters any enemy-occupied Space, another avoid
Battle attempt may be made. A Unit/Force may avoid Battle
any number of times during an activation, unless in a Zone. In
a Zone, if the active Force contains more cavalry, the defending
Unit/Force may avoid Battle only twice (10.9).
f.		 Avoidance Limitations. An intercepted Force may not avoid
Battle. A Force which fails an interception attempt may not
avoid Battle if the active Force moves into its Space.

10.9 Reaction and Zones. Units may intercept out of a Zone. Units
may avoid combat into a Zone. A Force in a Zone may attempt to
intercept Forces moving into the Zone. When a Force moves out of a
Zone, it may be intercepted in the Space it enters either by a Force in
the Zone or in an adjacent Space. To attack an enemy Unit/Force in
the Zone, the activated Force designates the target, spends 1 MP and
rolls to intercept. If successful, the enemy may attempt to avoid Battle,
either remaining in the Zone or moving into an adjacent Space. The
active Force may be intercepted by another enemy Force in the Zone.
If the enemy avoids Battle, the active player may repeat the attempt,
up to its MA. Battle occurs when the enemy fails to avoid Battle. If
the active Force has more Cavalry steps than the avoiding Unit/Force,
the avoiding Force may avoid Battle only twice, at which point it must
leave the Zone into any adjacent Space. The active Force may move
into that Space if it has MP remaining. The Unit may avoid normally
once outisde the Zone.

11.0	 BATTLE
Design Note: The Battle rules attempt to reflect several factors prominent
in the Mexican War. First of all, many of the Battles during the War were
not decisive tactically and resulted in low levels of casualties. The Americans
had clear advantages, reflected in certain Battle card events. The Mexican
artillery was less than effective because of bad powder and out-dated doctrine. Leadership was a major factor favoring the United States, with the
Americans getting the tactical ratings advantage and the special Officer
cards. The firepower is roughly the Force size, except that players can augment firepower with the commitment rules, and the Mexican player will
not get as much as he wants from the Activa Militia. Players will discover
that their Forces display resiliency in Battle at first, but once the step losses
mount, a Force will collapse quickly.
11.1 Initiation of Battle. Battle occurs when an active Force (“the
attacker”) moves into a Space containing enemy Units (“the defender”),
and the defender does not avoid Battle. Battle is mandatory and all
Units in the Space must participate. Cavalry and Guerillas may be
able to withdraw from combat (11.2.b). Battle may occur twice in a
Space in the Event of a failed avoidance attempt out of a Space with
a fort or fortress (10.8.c).
11.2 Battle Sequence. Place the “Battle Space” marker on the map.
Move all Leaders and Units to the Battle Diagram area on your side of
the map, and use it and the FP markers to resolve the Battle; the FP
markers will help distinguish between FP based on Units and total FP.
Each Battle follows the sequence in 11.2. Sections 11.3 – 11.9 cover
specific situations as appropriate.
a.		 Determine Battle type. The attacker determines the Battle Type
by spending movement points after entering the Battle Space.
The Battle Types, movement costs, and Firepower (FP) effects
on the attacking Force are:
Type of Battle

MP
cost

FP
effect

Column of Route

0

–5

Hasty Attack
Normal Attack

1
2

–3
–2

Pitched Battle

3

–0

Other effects
Attacker may not commit
any units
Required if intercepted
—
Add 1 to Post-Battle results
roll regardless of winner

Design Note: the time scale for an OPS card is somewhat abstracted
but covers roughly 10 to 14 days of historical time. The expenditure
of movement points for the Battle Type represents scouting activities,
maneuvers to take advantage of good ground, and other factors.
After the MP are spent, compare the best tactics rating on each
side. Change the Battle Type one in favor of the Force with the
higher Tactics Rating, or, if the Battle Type is already the best

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma
for that Force, add half a die roll (rounded up) to the Force’s
Firepower. A subordinate's Tactics Rating may be used. This
adjustment is also made in a Battle following interception.
Example: The Defender has the higher Tactics rating in a Hasty
Attack. The Attack is resolved as a Column of Route.
b.		 Withdrawal. Cavalry and/or Guerillas alone in a Space may be
able to withdraw from Battle. The activated Force may continue
moving after a Withdrawal. Withdrawal takes place after spending MP for Battle Type. Withdrawing Units are placed in any
adjacent Space not containing enemy Unit(s). Withdrawal may
be repeated if the active Force moves into a new Space.
•	 Cavalry may not withdraw in a Zone.
•	 Guerilla Units may only withdraw from a Rough Space.
•	 Units may not withdraw into the Space from which the active
Force entered.
c.		 Guerilla arrival. The Mexican player may discard a Strategy
card and add a hidden Guerilla Unit to the Space (16.5). This
play puts the attacking US Force out of supply for this Battle.
Guerillas brought in this way do not count against stacking for
the duration of the Battle. They may join a Battle in a fortification.
d.		 Battle Events. Both players may play one or more Response
Event cards. The attacker plays all desired cards first. After the
defender plays cards, the attacker may only play cards directly
responding to a defender’s card.
Example: After the attacker plays cards, the defender plays Bombardment. The attacker is holding Artillery Duel, but may not play
it for this Battle, because the attacker always plays his cards first,
and Artillery Duel is not a response to Bombardment.
e.		 Lead and Committed Units. Each side must designate a lead
Unit—only Guerillas are ineligible to be leading Units. Each
may then commit one or two Units. Only Units bearing the
commitment symbol may be committed. A one-star Force Commander may commit one unit; a two-star Force Commander
may commit two. Each committed Unit loses one step after
calculating FP; this loss does not count towards determining
victory in Battle. The attacker commits Units first.
Design Note: Units which cannot be committed are less experienced
(e.g., in the case of the Mexican Activa Militia infantry Units) or are
limited due to combat doctrine and resources (e.g., artillery Units).
f.		 Firepower total. Each player totals friendly firepower (FP) per
the Firepower section of the Battle Results Table. For purposes
of determining an attacking Force’s supply status, trace supply
from the Space from which the Battle is launched, not from the
Battle Space. The defending Unit/Force traces from the Battle
Space.
g.		 Efficiency and Leader/Artillery Loss. Each player rolls one die,
applies all applicable modifiers, and compares the modified roll
to the Efficiency Roll column of the Battle Results table. Next to
the result is a description of the troops’ performance. If a player’s
Efficiency die roll was a natural ‘2’ or ‘7’, a Friendly Leader Loss
is possible per 11.3. If the Mexican player’s Efficiency Die roll
was a natural ‘9’, Mexico loses one additional artillery step (if
present); this step does not count towards determining victory.
h.		 Casualties. Each player then cross-references the Efficiency result
with friendly FP. The result is number of step losses inflicted on
the enemy.
i.		 Victory, Post-Battle Losses, and Retreat. The winner is the side
which inflicted the higher total of losses on the Battle Results
Table. If the total is tied, the defender wins. If the winning Force
was eliminated by the Battle result, restore one step of the win-

11

ner’s choice to the Space. Conduct Post Battle Losses, and then
the loser retreats (11.5).			
j.		 Aftermath. Adjust Political Will (5.1). Guerillas must return
to the nearest Rough Space (if such Spaces are equidistant, the
Mexican player decides where to place the Units). If Canales is
in the Space, Canales may move with the Guerillas. The winner
places a friendly control marker in the Space.
11.3 Leader Loss. If a player’s Efficiency roll was a natural ‘2’ or ‘7’,
roll the die for each Friendly Leader, adding his Tactics Rating. An
Army Commander may reroll this roll once. If the modified roll is 5
or higher, roll again and consult the Leader Loss Table. Santa Anna
and Scott are treated normally for Leader Loss purposes.
11.4 Step Losses. The owner chooses which specific Units take losses.
•	 A player may not eliminate any reduced Units before reducing all
full-strength Units in the battle.
•	 Each committed Unit takes one step loss before assigning casualties.
•	 Return eliminated Units to Regroup.
•	 If all Units on a side are eliminated in a Battle, place surviving
Leaders in the Leader Pool.
11.5 Post Battle Losses and Retreat. If the difference in step losses
between the winner and loser is five or more, check for post-Battle
losses. Count all steps lost in the Battle for any reason.
a.		 Post Battle Losses. The losing player rolls one. Subtract the
losing Commander’s Tactics rating and add one if this was a
Pitched Battle. Refer to the Post Battle Results table. The losing
Force takes the noted additional losses. If the roll is a natural
‘9’, the losing Force routs as follows:
•	 Eliminate a Unit/Force with 5 or fewer steps,
•	 Eliminate one-half the steps in Forces with 6 or more steps
(rounding up), losing one step from each type if present,
•	 Check for Leader Loss again, and
•	 Place all surviving Leaders and Units in a friendly, supplied
Space within 5 Spaces of the Battle Space (if no such Space
exists, all survivors are eliminated, Leaders going to the Leader
Pool).
b.		 Retreat. The surviving losing Unit/Force retreats one Space.
Retreating Units need not remain together. Units unable to
retreat are eliminated.
c.		 Retreat priorities. The attacker must retreat to the Space from
which it moved into Battle. A retreating defender may retreat to
an adjacent Space, Transit Space, or Zone, but not into a Space
containing one or more enemy Units. Retreat to a friendly Space
over an enemy Space. Choose one closer in MP to a friendly
supply source if several eligible Spaces are available. The defender
may retreat into the Space from which the attacking Force entered only to avoid elimination.
d.		 Specific situations. The following apply to retreats as noted:
•	 Guerillas must retreat to the nearest Rough Space. Canales
may retreat with regular Units or with the Guerillas.
•	 A Force defending in (a) a fort or fortress, or (b) rough, jungle,
or rough/jungle terrain may take one additional step loss to
cancel a retreat. The attacker wins the battle, receives any PW
benefit, and returns to the Space from which it entered Battle.
•	 U.S. Units retreating from a failed Amphibious Landing must
return to the port of origin.
e.		 Surrounded retreating Force. If all Spaces adjacent to the Battle
Space contain Units from the winning side, then (a) eliminate
all retreating Artillery Units, (b) eliminate half (rounding up)
of the retreating side’s remaining steps (owner’s choice), and (c)
place the survivors in a friendly Supply Source within 5 Spaces

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

12

of the Battle Space. If no such Space exists, then place survivors
in Regroup/Leader Pool.
11.6 Overrun Battle. An attacking Force may continue movement
after Battle if (a) it suffered no losses on the BRT, (b) all enemy Units
were eliminated, and (c) no enemy fortification is in the Space.
11.7 Fortifications. Enemy fortifications are never eliminated in
Battle. See 13.2.b for moving out of a Space containing a fort or
fieldworks, and 13.3 for fortresses.

12.0	 EVENTS
12.1 Events. Each Strategy card contains an Event. Follow the card’s
text to execute the Event. The circle around the card’s OPS number is
color-coded to indicate which player may play the card for the Event:
blue for the US, green for Mexico, and both for either player. Play
each Event according to the text of the card. An Event allowing the
player a number of OPS after the Event permits use of those OPS for
any purpose allowed by the rules. Apply the following as appropriate:
a.		 Reinforcements and replacements. Place Event reinforcements
per 3.4. Some Events give the player replacement points, steps
or Units. All replacements must be placed in supply. Play of a
card granting replacements does not affect the ability to play a
card for replacements (13.4), and vice versa.
b.		 Mandatory Events. Play of either Logistics and/or Santa Anna
Elected President for the Event is mandatory. The player holding
the card may determine the timing of such play(s). These cards
may not be held until the next Turn.
c.		 Remove and Reshuffle. Remove cards marked "remove" from
play when played for the Event. When played as Events, cards
carrying the notation “Reshuffle” cause the Strategy deck to be
reshuffled at the end of the Action Phase.
Play Note: If a reshuffle card is played during the Turn in which
the At War cards are added to the deck, the Reshuffle in effect has no
effect–but make sure you add the Reshuffle card to the deck (unless
removed from play).
d.		 Response Events. Some cards have a blue “Response” bar at the
top. Play the Event as indicated by the card. Response Events
do not replace a normal card play in the Action Phase. When
played in response, these cards do not trigger the Supply Event.
e.		 Officers. The US player has four “Officer” cards. Play during
the Battle sequence (11.2.d). Play no more than one “Officer”
Event per Turn. When played, place the corresponding Officer’s
counter in the Force Commander’s Holding Box; the Officer
remains with that Force Commander until removed. Mexican
play of No Future Glory cancels one Officer card play or officer
present in a given battle—remove the counter from play. During
each Battle, including the current one, use the Officer for either
Chief of Staff or Field Command. Use no more than one Officer
in each capacity during a given Battle. Remove all Officers in
a Force if the Force loses a Battle, even if their effects were not
declared for that particular combat. The Officer effects are:
•	 Chief of Staff—Add 1 to the Efficiency Die roll.
•	 Field Command—Add the results of 1 die roll to the Force’s
FP for the current Battle.

13.0	 PLACEMENT ACTIONS,
FORTIFICATIONS, AND FORTRESSES
A card of any OPS value may be played to place control markers, build
fieldworks, take replacements, or return the Baggage Train to play.

13.1 Place control markers. Play any card to establish control over
enemy Spaces or Zones. Each OPS point on the card played allows
placement of one control marker in one Space; spending all OPS allows placement of control in a Zone (10.4). Control of a Space may
be changed if either:
•	 a friendly Force is in the Space/Zone, or
•	 the Space is adjacent to the Space and no enemy Force is presently
able to intercept into the Space (Control of Zones may not be
changed from adjacent Spaces).
Play Note: Place control markers in Spaces in your own country for clarity
only; unless an enemy marker is in the Space, you control it.
13.2 Build a fortification. Fortifications are fieldworks, forts, and
fortresses (2.3.a). No Space may contain more than one fortification,
except for forts under-construction (13.2.b) and destroyed fortresses
(10.5). Do not place fortifications in Transit Spaces. Build fortifications
in friendly supplied and occupied Spaces only.
a.		 Fieldworks and Forts. To build a fortification, randomly draw
a fortification of the appropriate type, examine it, and place it
face down in the Space. If any Leader in the Space has a Tactics
rating of either ‘1’ or ‘2’, then draw two, examine them, place
one, and return the other to the fortification pool. Flip the
fortification face up when a Battle occurs in the Space.
•	 Build a fieldworks in a Space without another fortification.
•	 Build a fort in a Space containing a friendly fieldworks. Place
an “Under Construction” marker on the Fort. On a subsequent card play, remove the marker and the fieldworks; the
fieldworks retains full capability until removal. It thus takes
two card plays to complete a fort.
b.		 Destruction. An active Force may remove enemy unoccupied
fieldworks and forts by spending 1 MP in the Space. A player
may demolish any friendly fort or fieldworks on the map whenever it is his opportunity to play a Strategy card (except in reaction). The demolished fortification is immediately available to
be built elsewhere.
13.3 Fortresses. The fortresses are Mejico and Vera Cruz. Fortresses
are printed on the map, and are destroyed only by siege (10.5). A US
Force moving into a fortress must stop. If Mexican Units are present,
Battle follows normally, adding the FP of the inherent Units (13.3.a).
Once no other Mexican Units are in the Space, the US Force, in a
subsequent activation, may resolve the siege per 10.5. When other
Mexican Units defend in a fortress, the fortress' inherent steps may
not be taken as Battle or Post Battle losses. A successful siege destroys
a fortress; after destruction, fieldworks and forts may be built in the
Space normally.
a.		 Inherent Units. Each fortress has an inherent two step artillery
Unit. Fortresses’ inherent Units may neither intercept nor avoid
Battle. The inherent FP is added at full-strength to any Mexican
defense in the Space. Neither Unit may be committed. Once the
US controls a fortress, its inherent Unit is considered eliminated
from the game.
Historical Note: The fortress at Vera Cruz had about 135 guns
installed. Mexico City had inherent artillery defenses (not as many
as Vera Cruz) but suffered from a shortage of well-trained artillerists.
b.		 US control. The US maintains control of a fortress Space provided a supplied Unit in a fieldworks or fort remains in the Space.
At the end of a successful siege, the US places a fieldworks in
the fortress space automatically (10.5).
13.4 Replacements. Any card may be played for replacements using
the card’s OPS value. No more than one replacement Action may be
undertaken by each player during a given Turn; use the friendly “No

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma
Repl./Repl. Taken” marker as a reminder. Designate one in supply
Leader to receive the replacements. The US player may NOT take
replacements until War has been declared.
a.		 Procedure. Designate the Leader to receive replacements. Roll
the die once for a one-star Leader, and twice for a two-star. Take
the higher of the two rolls and add the OPS value of the card.
The sum represents the replacement points, which can be spent
as follows:
•	 1 point for 1 infantry step.
•	 2 points for 1 cavalry or US mixed infantry/artillery step.
•	 3 points for 1 artillery step.
•	 Points equal to command value for 1 available replacement
leader. Only one REPL Leader may be taken in a given replacement action.
b.		 Placement. First, the active player may flip any reduced Units
in the Space to full strength, paying the replacement point
cost. Then, draw Units out of Regroup one at a time, and pay
replacement points to place it in the Space at either reduced or
full strength. Placement of a drawn Unit with at least one step is
mandatory, unless insufficient replacement points are available,
in which case another Unit may be drawn. Newly added Units
may bring the size of the Force above the Leader's force activation limit. Units drawn but not taken are returned to Regroup.
Example: The American player plays a 3 OPS card for replacements,
and designates Scott to receive replacements. The U.S. player rolls two
dice and gets results of 3 and 7. He takes the 7 roll, adds 3 for a total of
10, and flips two cavalry Units to full strength (cost of 4) and draws an
artillery combat Unit (placed on its reduced side at a cost of 3) as well as
two Infantry Units (one placed at full strength, one at reduced, at a cost
of 3 more replacement points).
Design Note: Replacement Units are randomly drawn because the Commander on the ground would have little control over which Units higher
authorities would send to his support.
13.5 Baggage Train. When the friendly Baggage Train has been
removed from the map, a player may return it to play via a Strategy
card (9.5). Place it in any friendly, in supply Space containing a
friendly Force.

14.0	NAVAL MOVEMENT, SQUADRONS,
PORT SEIZURE, AND BLOCKADE
14.1 Naval Movement. The game has two coasts, East and West. The
corresponding squadron must be active for all US naval movement.
Naval Movement between the coasts is never permitted. To make a
Naval Move, play a Strategy card and move the Leader/Unit/Force from
one friendly, supplied port to another, unless an Amphibious Landing
is taking place (14.2). A Leader/Unit/Force that makes a naval move
may not perform any other movement during the same activation.
Any Battle is considered a Column of Route attack.
a.		 Unit/Leader. On play of any OPS value card, one Unit or Leader
may move from port-to-port.
b.		 Force. On play of a ‘4’ OPS card, a Force (but not an Army)
may make a naval move.
c.		 Army. An Army may make a naval move only on play of Scott
Invades.
d.		 Mexican Naval capability. The Mexican player may make a
naval move only when the US squadron for the corresponding
coast is inactive (14.3) or seizing a port; from Turn 4 to the end
of the game, both are active except by card play or if seizing a
port (14.4).

13

14.2 Amphibious Landings. Amphibious Landing is available to US
Forces only. Play a 4 OPS card and move a Force from a friendly to
a Mexican port. At least one Marine Unit must be included (14.2.c).
Conduct reaction and Battle normally during a landing. If the US wins
the Battle or the port Space is empty, the US player places a control
and the Beachhead marker. The Beachhead is an immobile Baggage
Train.	
a.		 Landing Failure. A Force failing to win a Battle in the Amphibious Landing returns to its port of origin.
b.		 Scott Invades. This card allows a special Amphibious Landing
per the card’s text. The Units in the landing Force or Army can be
drawn from Regroup, New Orleans, or any in-Supply Space(s).
Units up to Scott’s command Rating may be drawn. If Scott is
in command of a previously-built Army, the Army participates
in the landing. Marines must be included.
c.		 Marines. The following provisions apply to all US Amphibious
Landings.
•	 One or more US Marine Units must be in the landing Force,
•	 At least one US Marine must be committed in any Battle in
the landing Space, and
•	 The Marine Unit included in a landing made per Scott Invades
may be drawn per 14.2.b.
Play Note: You may search Regroup for a Marine Unit for Scott Invades,
even if one is already on the map, thereby bringing two for this Event.
14.3 Activate Squadrons. Each coast has a corresponding US squadron; both begin the game inactive. A squadron becomes active on play
of a 2, 3, or 4 OPS card. Both squadrons automatically activate at the
beginning of every turn from turn 4 onward. On each squadron’s first
activation during the game, increase the Blockade Level by one. If a
coast’s squadron is either inactive or seizing a port (14.4), the Mexican
player may make naval moves along that coast.
14.4 Seizing a Port. An active squadron may seize a Mexican-controlled port on play of a Strategy card (9.6). Such a Port may be seized
if the Space contains no more than two Mexican steps and neither is
Artillery. The squadron is still active even after seizing a port, but the
Mexican player may make naval moves on that coast. A squadron
engaged in seizing a port is active for tracing supply by sea.
a.		 Effects. Apply the following effects when a port is seized:
•	 Place the squadron on the Port and raise the blockade level
by 1.
•	 Place a US control marker in the Space.
•	 Any Mexican steps remain in the space.
b.		 End seizure. When a port seizure ends, place the squadron
marker back in the squadron box. The squadron remains active
unless deactivated by Event. The blockade level increase remains
even after the seizure ends. The port seizure ends when
•	 A Mexican Artillery Unit moves into the Space,
•	 The US player activates the squadron by card play, or
•	 An Event deactivates the squadron.
14.5 The Blockade. Track the blockade of Mexico on the Information track. The blockade level modifies the die roll on the Mexican
Government Collapse Table (18.2). In addition, during each Supply
Event (9.2), roll a die against the blockade level to determine if a
Mexican Unit is removed from the game. The blockade starts at ‘0’,
and increases by one when:
•	 Each squadron activates for the first time during the game.
•	 A port is seized by a squadron.
•	 An Event increasing the blockade is played.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

14

The Halls of Montezuma

15.0	 ARMIES
Design Note: The Army markers represent an extra level of organization,
command staff, and artillery park, with attending increases in political
prominence of a Force and reductions in maneuverability. The design does
not force players to build armies. However, the Political Will
benefit and extra firepower make them attractive even if they
are a double-edged sword offering a lower movement rate and
the possibility of PW loss if you lose in battle.
15.1 Army Organization and Retention. Place and keep Army
markers on the map as follows:
•	 Organization. Play of a 2, 3 or 4 OPS card allows the organization
of an Army in a friendly, in-Supply Space provided at least one
Leader and one Unit is in the Space.
•	 Retention. Each Army needs at least one Leader and one Unit. At
all times, if the last Leader in an Army is eliminated, then the Army
marker is removed. When an Army is reduced to one Leader as a
result of Leader Loss in Battle, you may draw one Leader from the
Leader Pool and place him in the Army. Santa Anna and Scott may
not be so drawn unless in the pool because of Leader Loss. If all
Units in an Army are eliminated, remove the Army, roll for Leader
loss (again), and place surviving Leaders in the Leader Pool. An
Army marker removed for any reason may subsequently be rebuilt.
15.2 Army Movement. When activated, subtract 1 from the MA
printed on the Action card for all Armies. An Army always has a minimum of 1 MP, even if the Action card lists an MA of ‘0’. Armies activated for movement may place control markers at a cost of 1 MP each.
15.3 Armies in Battle. An in supply Army adds 3 to friendly FP in
Battle. If an Army wins a Battle, move the PW marker 1 in its side’s
favor. If an Army loses a battle, move the PW marker 1 against its side.

16.0 	RAIDS AND GUERILLAS
Design Note: The rules on raiding bring out the effects of varied Indian
and Guerilla activities that were mostly a “side-show” during the course
of the war. The action cards “deliver” Indian Units and Guerilla Units
to the players randomly, since the U.S. and Mexico did not have direct
control over such Units or attempt to organize them. The raid mechanics
here are adapted from Wilderness War, altered for the Mexican War.
16.1 Raids. The game includes five Raid markers plus one for Local
Militia Raid. Raid opportunities occur either by play of an Action or
Strategy card (16.2). Once placed, Raid markers are only removed
during the Victory Check Phase.
a.		 Where to Raid. Both players may place raid markers in enemyControlled or occupied Spaces, as well as Baja California, Alta
California, and Yucatan Zones. The Mexican player may also
raid the Disputed Zone. The target Space/Zone must be
•	 Within 10 MP of the Indian Space used for the raid, or
•	 Within 6 MP of the Guerilla Unit’s Space—the Unit moves
to the raided Space.
b.		 Other Raid Specifics. Spaces containing either fortifications or
friendly Units may not be raided. At a given raid opportunity,
trace each Indian Raid from a different Indian Space and use
each Guerilla once. Raids may take place during the Armistice
(after play of that Strategy card). No more than five Guerilla/
Indian raids occur in any one Turn; Local Militia Raid is a sixth
possible raid. Canales may join a Guerrilla raid.
16.2 Raid Particulars.	

b.		 Raiding via Strategy card. The play of a Strategy card for
Raiding allows raid attempts up to the OPS value of the card.
Each raid attempt may involve either an on-map Guerilla or an
Indian Space. After designating each target Space, follow the
Raiding procedure in 16.3.
c.		 Event. The Local Militia Raids Event allows the automatic placement of a Raid marker by the Mexican player.
16.3 Raiding Procedure. For each Strategy card raid, roll a die,
and modify as noted below; all applicable modifiers are cumulative.
If the net roll is ‘5’ or more, place the Raid marker. If an enemy Unit
is in the Space, eliminate a Guerilla Raider on an unmodified roll of
‘0’ or ‘1’. Raiding Guerrillas move to the nearest Rough Space or the
Hidden box per 16.5.
•	 +1	
•	 –1	
•	 –1	
•	 + ?	

For a Guerilla Raid, if Canales is in the Space.
If an enemy Unit is in the Space.
If the Space contains an Enemy Leader.
The OPS value of the card played to make the Raid.

16.4 Raid Effects.	
a.		 PW effect. Each successful Raid awards the Raiding player ½
PW point at the end of the turn. Add up each side’s raid total,
subtract the smaller from the larger, round fractions up, and
move PW in favor of the side with the larger total. Remove the
raid markers during the Government Status/End Turn Phase.
b.		 Other effects. A Raid marker converts the Space into a Transit
Space until removed. A Raid marker blocks a supply line for
either player unless a friendly Unit or Baggage Train is in the
Space. Spaces with Raid markers may not be raided again until
next Turn.
16.5 Guerillas. Guerillas move normally. Canales is the only Leader
who may command Guerillas in a Force. One Guerilla Unit may be
hidden either by play of a Strategy card during the Action Phase or
after a raid--place it in the box on the Turn Record Track. No more
than one Guerilla may be hidden at a time. The Unit may be returned
to the map either by a Strategy card play during the Action Phase or
during Battle (11.2.c). Bringing a Guerilla out of hiding during Battle
places the US Unit/Force out of supply. Guerillas may only enter
Spaces in Mexico.
Design Note: The raiding rules simulate the fact that the politically prominent raids were not very frequent, and that there were limited resources
and windows of opportunity for raiding especially given the abstracted time
scale for the play of an OPS card. Limiting the raids allowed to 6 total
between the two players alters the attractiveness of raid attempts as a Turn
proceeds (simulating weather problems, local command paralysis, shifting
sentiments of raiders, etc.). This also limits Raid Political Will Points to
a maximum of 3 Political Will Points if only one side raids successfully.

17.0	DISCARDING AND HOLDING
CARDS
17.1 Discards.	 Place a card in the discard pile and take no action.
Do not discard cards marked “Mandatory”. Discard of “Remove” cards
does not cause removal. No Supply Event may be triggered.
17.2 Held cards. A player with one card remaining may hold it. This
card may be played anytime later in the Action Phase, or held until
the next Turn. Once each player has one card remaining, each either
plays it normally or holds it until next Turn. A card held for the next
Turn counts against hand size.

a.		 Action card. A player drawing an Indian Raid card during the
Random Events Phase places up to the indicated number of raid
markers.
© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

18.0	 GOVERNMENTAL STATUS / END
TURN PHASE, WAR DECLARATION,
AND REVOLTS
Design Note: There are two major political features of the War built
into this design. The Mexican government was a fragile entity. The game
models this in two ways—the Mexican player has an array of presidential
personalities to handle, reflected through Events, and faces the possibility of collapse of central authority; Mexican states can also descend into
revolt. Some of the fighting pre-dated “official” declaration of War due to
antiquated communications and bureaucratic and political turmoil in
the United States. Thus, we model the level of U.S. bellicosity to account
for the effect of certain military and political events, starting the game
with the period of crisis and increasing hostility which will result in a US
declaration of War.
During the Governmental Status/End Turn Phase, execute the procedures in 18.1–18.5 in the order stated.
18.1 Determine control. Each player gains control of all enemy
Spaces now containing a friendly Unit/Force, regardless of supply.
Then, simultaneously remove all isolated friendly control markers.
Third, check each Mexican State for US control. 	
a.		 Isolated control markers. An isolated control marker is one
which is (a) in the other player’s country, (b) not in supply, and
(c) in a Space not currently occupied by a friendly Unit. Removal
is deemed simultaneous.
b.		 State control. If the number of US controlled Spaces in a State
is equal to or greater than the State control number, flip the
State control marker to the US side. If the number of Spaces
controlled by the US is less than the number, Mexico retains or
regains control of the State.
18.2 Mexican Government Collapse. If Santa Anna is President,
skip this step. If Santa Anna is not President, the Mexican player rolls
one die and modifies the result per the Collapse Table. Once Collapse
occurs, skip this step. The Table gives three possible results:
•	 Stable—If on the “Unstable” side, flip the marker to “Stable”.
•	 Unstable—Flip the PW marker to “Unstable” and add 1 to the
Collapse roll on the next turn.
•	 Collapse—Reduce PW by 5; 7 cards during each subsequent
Draw Cards Phase.
If the Mexican Government collapses during a Turn, the Mexican
player does NOT lose any Strategy cards that Turn.
Design Note: When Santa Anna was in power, the strategic will of Mexico
was, in essence, his own will, which could not collapse.
18.3 United States Declaration of War. During the Government
Status Phase, the US rolls for War on the War declaration Table. The
ways by which the US declares War are all in this section:
a.		 War Declaration Table. The US player rolls one die. Modify
the roll as indicated and apply the result. US Bellicosity changes
as follows, to a minimum of 0 and maximum of 5:
•	 The first time when more Mexican than American Units are
in the Disputed Zone; reduce bellicosity by 1.
•	 Play of Santa Anna Returns from Exile and Santa Anna Becomes
President each increases bellicosity by 1.
•	 Play of Strategy cards for the Event during the action phase,
per the card’s text.

15

b.		 Beginning of Turn. The US player declares War for the PW
penalty noted on the Turn Record track during the Random
Events Phase. War is declared automatically at the beginning
of Turn 7.
c.		 Automatic declaration of War. The US declares War immediately if Santa Anna commands a Force and enters any Texas
Space.
d.		 Strategy card. Some Events allow the US player to roll on the
War declaration Table.
e.		 Consequences of declaration of War. Add the War cards to the
Strategy deck, reshuffle the deck, and add the At War Units to US
Regroup at the beginning of the next Turn. After War is declared,
both players receive 9 cards in the Deal cards Phase, but do not
add cards in the middle of the Turn. If War is declared during
the Action Phase, the US player may play a card for replacements
later in that Action Phase. If he has not yet entered play, place
Santa Anna and four Units in Mejico fortress at the start of the
following Turn.
18.4 Revolts. Finally, check for the spread of revolts. Revolts are
suppressed during the Action Phase (10.3).
a.		 Spread. Alternating between the Mexican player and the US
player, designate a State in revolt and roll one die. The revolt
spreads on a roll of 8–9 (or 7–9 if the Mexican Government
has collapsed). The rolling player flips the Civic State marker in
any one “Calm” State adjacent to the State being checked. If no
adjacent State is “Calm”, then the revolt cannot spread. States
are adjacent if at least one connection exists between Spaces in
each State. Alta California, Baja California, and Yucatan are all
States.
Play Note: You may select a state with no adjacent “Calm” states.
b.		 Effects. When a Mexican State goes into revolt, flip the Civic
State marker from its ‘Calm’ side to its ‘In revolt’ Side. A State
may go into revolt any number of times during the game. Revolts
affect the actions of both players in each Space/Transit Space in
a State in revolt as follows::
•	 No supply line may be traced into or through the Space unless
the Baggage Train is present.
•	 It is treated as enemy-controlled for retreat purposes.
•	 No Unit may take replacements in the State.
•	 A Unit/Force expending one or more MP in the State suffers
movement attrition (10.2.c).
18.5 PW Changes. Change PW for raids, revolts, and States under
US control.
a.		 Raids. Award raid PW per 16.4.a and remove the raid markers.
b.		 State Control, Revolts and PW. Total the number of States in
revolt and/or under US control, and halve the result. If a State is
both in revolt and under US control, count it once. Round the
halving down if the Mexican Government has NOT Collapsed,
round up if it has. Reduce PW by the result.
18.6 Victory Check. Determine if Victory per 5.2 has been achieved.
18.7 End of Game Segment. At the end of Turns 6 through 9, roll
one die. The game ends if the roll is greater than or equal to the number on the Turn Record track. The game ends regardless at the end of
Turn 10. If the game continues, shuffle the Action deck, and go on
to the next Turn.
Play Note: Given the sequence during this last phase, if the game ends
per 18.7, the Mexican player will win.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

16

The Halls of Montezuma

U.S.

Mexico

19.0	COMPREHENSIVE EXAMPLE OF PLAY

It is the beginning of Turn 2. The US has yet to declare war. During
Turn 1, Kearney moved into the Disputed Zone after the play of Tejas!
and defeated the Mexican unit placed there. Thereafter, Settlers allowed
two US Units to be placed in that Zone. Meanwhile, the Mexican player
took replacements at Monterey—sending them to Arista. Kerney then
moved out out of the Disputed Zone to San Antonio. Ampudia built a
fieldworks. Finally, Taylor attempted to attack across the Rio Grande,
but was stopped when the action card gave him ‘0’ MP.

At start of Turn 2:
Mexico

Arista, 1st Light, 7th Dragoons, (1st Mtd, 1st PC, 6th Artillery) and
the Baggage Train in Presidio del Rio Grande.
Ampudia, 2nd, 4th, 6th, 10th Infantry, 9th Dragoons, Zapadores,
Army of Tejas, and +2 fieldworks in Matamoros.

US

Kearney, 1st Infantry, 1st Dragoons, Bragg and Taylor Artillery.
Taylor, 1st – 4th US Artillery, 5th and 7th Infantry, 2nd Dragoons,
Army of Observation, the Baggage Train, and a +2 fieldworks in Fort
Brown.

Random Events Phase

1.		 The US takes standard reinforcements and places Worth and the
3rd Infantry in San Antonio. Mexico receives the Guard, the 2nd
Marines, and the 3rd Artillery, as well as leaders Lombardini and
Leon. Leon and the 2nd Marines are placed in Vera Cruz to be
able to move to Yucatan to suppress the revolt. Lombardini and
the other Units are placed in Monterey.
2.		 The Mexican player draws an Action card. It is Riots (card 1), and
the die roll is a ‘5’—no effect. The US player then draws Reinforcements (17), and receives one Leader and two Units, placing

them in Encinas. Mexico then draws Reinforcements (14), and
places Canales and the 5th and 8th Dragoons in Saltillo. Finally,
the US draws Riots (29), rolls a 6, and places Cohahuila State in
Revolt.
Since there are no wounded leaders, and the US player decides not to
declare war for the +5 PW penalty, the Random Events Phase ends.

Deal Cards Phase

Each player receives five cards.
•	 Mexico’s hand includes Nicholas Trist, Operational Exhaustion, Bad Weather, Pacific Squadron, and Forced March.
•	 The US hand includes Guerillas Go Home, Malaria, Negotiations Break Down, Dysentery, and No Quarter.

Actions Phase

1.		 The Mexican player has the initiative, and decides to go first. His
first concern is the revolt in Cohahuila, which cuts the supply line
for Arista’s Force, and may make it difficult to follow through on
his planned invasion of Texas. Therefore, he plays Bad Weather for
2 OPS to activate Arista, to suppress the revolt. He draws Political Insight (21) to determine the MA. Cross-referencing Arista’s
Strategy rating of 2 with the MA row, he sees this Force has 5 MP.
He chooses not to move the Force, thus avoiding movement attrition. The suppression die roll is ‘7’—the revolt is not suppressed.
2.		 The US, wanting to lessen the threat of the advanced Mexican
Forces, plays Dystentery as an Event. It carries a Supply Wagon
(the “Chuck Wagon”) icon, this requiring a Supply Event check.
The die roll is ‘7’, greater than the card’s OPS of ‘2’—no Supply
Event occurs. The die roll for the Event is a ‘9’—Mexico must take
a step loss in two units. He chooses the 2nd Infantry in Vera Cruz,
and the Mejico Unit in Mejico fortress.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

3.		 Mexico will again attempt to suppress the revolt. After play of
Pacific Squadron, the Action card Reinforcements (13) gives
Arista 7 MP. The die roll of ‘1’ suppresses the revolt.
4.		 The US plays Guerillas Go Home, rolls a ‘5’ for the Supply
Event check—the Event doesn’t happen—and activates Kearney
and four Units, leaving Worth and the Taylor Artillery behind in
San Antonio. The Action card Heat (20) gives Kearney an MA
of ‘7’, but he must take a step loss to movement attrition for
the underlined MA. The US player moves Kearney’s Force south
across the Rio Grande to Palo Blanco for 5 MP. Lombardini does
not intercept and Kearney moves into Monterey for 1 more MP.
Canales attempts to intercept, but the die roll of ‘0’ prevents that.
The Mexican player decides to stand at Monterey, leading to a
Battle. The US player eliminates one step from the 1st Infantry for
the movement attrition. The US player then rolls a ‘5’ for Transit
Space attrition; since Kearney moved in 2 Transit Spaces, there is
no attrition.

17

The Battle of Monterey
1. The US player spends 1 MP to declare a Hasty Attack. Because
Kearney’s tactics rating is better than Lombardini’s, the Battle Type
is increased one level in the US player’s favor, to a Normal Attack.
2. 	 The Mexican force may not withdraw, and no Guerillas may be
added because none are yet in play.
Neither player has Battle Events to play.
3. The US designates the 1st Dragoons as its lead Unit (3 FP), and the
3rd Infantry as its committed Unit (4 FP). The other two Units
count 1 each for FP for 2 more FP based on Units. The US FP is
increased by 1 for combined arms, and reduced by 2 for the Normal
Attack. The US Force is in supply through the three Transit Spaces
to San Patricio, tracing from Palo Blanco. Total US firepower is 8.
4. Mexico designates the 3rd Artillery as its lead Unit (1 FP) and the
Guard as the committed Unit (8 FP). Mexico therefore has 9 FP.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

18

The Halls of Montezuma

5. Both players flip their committed Units for the required step
loss—this can be done later, but doing it now makes sure they
remember to do so.
6. The US efficiency roll is 5, while the Mexican roll is 4. The US roll
is increased by 1 for Kearney’s tactical rating. Neither roll results in
Leader/Artillery Loss. Both players’ Forces efficiency is rated ‘Poor’.
The 8 FP of the US force inflicts 1 step loss on the Mexican Force,
while the 9 FP of the Mexican force inflicts 2 step losses on the
US. Mexico flips the 3rd Artillery, while the US flips Bragg artillery
and the 1st Dragoons. The US player then plays No Quarter as a
Response event, and eliminates the 1st Infantry—PW goes down
to 29, while Bellicosity increases to 1. The card is removed from
the game. Since the difference in step losses is less than 5, no Post
Battle Results roll is made. Kearney retreats to Palo Blanco. The

Battle itself has no PW effect because neither side is an Army nor
has 5 or more Units.
7.		 Despite the temptation, the Mexican player decides to get some
replacements to Arista, and plays Operational Exhaustion. The
Supply Event roll is a ‘9’. The replacement die roll is a ‘6’, giving
Arista 8 replacement points. The Mexican player flips the two
cavalry units for 4 points, and then draws Units, pulling the 3rd
Light and placing it at full strength for 2 points and then the 4th
artillery. Because he does not have at least 3 replacement points
remaining, he may draw another unit, and pulls the 4th Light. He
is able to place it at full strength, spending the full 8 replacement
points.
8.		 The US player breathes a sigh of relief and plays Malaria to activate
Kearney. California War (5) gives Kearney 3 MP. He moves back
across the Rio Grande to the Transit Space, rolling a ‘3’ for Transit
Space attrition.
9.		 Mexico then plays Forced March to build an Army, after making
a Supply Event check. The roll of ‘2’ triggers the Supply Event—but
at this point everyone’s back in supply, so no steps are lost. The
Army of Mejico is built with Arista.
10.	The US plays Negotiations Break Down. Since the DZ contains
no Mexican Units, PW is reduced by 1 to 28.
11.	To end the Action Phase, Mexico plays Nicolas Trist to activate
Canales. The chuck wagon is ignored, because the Supply Event
has occurred this Turn. He activates Canales, and draws Rough
Seas, giving him 6 MP—Canales moves north to join Arista on
the Rio Grande.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

Governmental Status/End Turn Phase

1.		 No Spaces change control this Turn, nor are any control markers
isolated. The Mexican player rolls a 9 on the Collapse table. The
only applicable modifier is the +1 for the revolt in Yucatan—which
brings the roll to 10, resulting in a “Unstable” result—this roll
will gain an additional +1 modifier next turn. The US then rolls
3 on the War Declaration Table. This roll is modified by +1 for
bellicosity, +1 for the elimination of a US Unit in Battle, and +1
for Turn to a net roll of ‘6’. The US does not declare war.
2.		Yucatan is the only State in revolt. The Mexican player designates
that State and rolls a 1—the revolt does not spread. If any raids
had taken place, markers would be removed and PW awarded right
now. Because only 1 State is either in revolt or under US control,
and the Mexican government has not collapsed, no PW is lost this
turn (the ½ PW award is rounded down to 0). Since neither side
has achieved any victory conditions, play goes on to the next Turn.
Source map: Mapa de los Estados Unidos de Méjico : segun lo organizado
y definido por las varias actas del congreso de dicha républica y construido
por las mejores autoridades. 1847—Disturnell, John, 1801-1877.
http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.gmd/g4410.ct000127

CREDITS

19

Designer: Michael Welker and David Fox
Developer: William Cooper
Art Director: Rodger B. MacGowan
Map Art and Card Logo: Tim Schleif
Final Counter Art: Rodger B. MacGowan
Rules Layout: Neil Randall
Card and Charts Layout: Mark Simonitch
Box Cover Artist: Rodger B. MacGowan
Playtesters: Richard Simon, Chris Atkins, Greg Mourad, Rob
Bottos, John Haas, David Imparato, Chris Janiec, Jim Lawler, Ken
Schultz, Thomas Cadenhead, Joshua Meah, Pete Skaar, John Foley,
Jeff Schulte, Alan Sundberg, Steve Valone, John Christopher, David
Mattson, Harvey Mossman, Peter Stein, Ben Hull.
Proofreaders Extraordinaire: Kevin Duke, Robin Griller, Aaron
Silverman, Brad Stock, Michael Debije
Production Coordination: Tony Curtis
Special thanks go to Anton Adams for his help with many aspects of
the game. Thanks also go to Michael Fitzgerald, Ph.D. who helped
out with many broad historical issues.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

20

The Halls of Montezuma

20.0	DESIGNERS’ NOTES
A lot of wargamers like design notes—and many are scattered here
and there in this rules booklet. Others want to see some design notes
in one place. We’ve attempted to cater to both preferences, so here are
some design thoughts with a ‘big picture’ perspective (let’s call this
the Macro notes and the various in-rule comments the Micro notes).
The Halls of Montezuma has a long, involved history. The idea to do a
strategic-level game for the Mexican-American War came up sometime
in 2002. Initially, some buzz arose about a strategy game for Gringos—
something that would be similar to the interesting and innovative
mixture of battles and campaign-level game included in Risorgimento.
But David and I were pretty adamant about doing the game as a carddriven game in the tradition of We The People, For The People, and so
on. Our first game with GMT (Thirty Years War: Europe in Agony) was
a great experience, as something just came together when I morphed
from developer to codesigner. To be clear, there were some downsides
to being in that sort of a mode, as I couldn’t juggle both angles of approach to that game. Well, in any case, some six years later Thirty Years
War is out of print, so it’s about the right time for a new game, right?
The GMT principals then gave us a green light to do the game as a
standalone. In mid-2002 I had the basic ideas in place: a game nearer
the We The People level of complexity, Mexico had to be able to win
(since it wouldn’t be a solitaire game), events (at least some) not
dependent on card draws, an operational tempo and battle system
that revealed the difficulty of waging war in the region, amphibious
operations (but not overly-focused), and all the political, economic,
logistics, social, and technological factors in the events, mechanics, and
atmosphere. In particular, I wanted the players to feel like high-level
strategists with little control over local events and actions. In addition, the design had to instill frustration—enabling the players to feel
like commanders of the era, in which plans were always imperfect,
disease was around every bivouac, and the guerillas could show up at
any moment.
Wargame design is complicated. But I got great advice: design it, play
it, design it more, play it more. And remember—a game design is
never finished, only published. So, as I reflect on the overall ideas on
my agenda, there are a few issues to review (but not all of them—hey
I need some leftovers for an article somewhere!):
1. The interesting leaders from the Civil War era cut their teeth
here—so they can appear at particular moments and then fade away
from sight.
2. I also wanted a tactical system that rewarded planning but was based
on command efficiency as the major determiner of battle victory: getting more lethal firepower at the right place and time. Many of the
war’s battles were small, indecisive, low-casualty affairs. A few, however,
were larger, more deadly, and decisive. The system had to allow for
both ends of this spectrum. At first I tried an algorithm much like the
army-size methodology found in For The People. However, my initial
testing indicated that the forces were too robust in large battles, and
the ratings system did not adequately yield the feeling of lack of control
and the wider variations I needed to make every engagement feel very
risky. After about seven iterations of the combat system, I decided to
combine control and uncertainty in a simple yet effective combination. FP is dependent on planning and concentration of Force (and
can fade away with the wrong cards), while the uncertainty emerges in
the efficiency die (and Bill thought of some ‘period language’ to add
some color to the efficiency result). The end result betrays the influence of many approaches to combat systems. You’ve got a firepower
calculation that is a distant cousin to the method in Thirty Years War.
The movement to pitched battle is a mix of the ideas found in Joe

Balkoski’s Great Campaigns games as well as Kevin Zucker’s really
amazing designs. Finally, as I scan my shelf of card-driven games, I
am reminded of the master—Mark Herman—you will find that the
efficiency roll is clearly related to the combat mechanic found in his
game Empire of the Sun.
3. Action cards for the independent events (as well as several ways to
capture the chaos of Mexican politics) and the uncertainty of local
operations—these cards combined the two notions very easily and
remained in the design from early stages.
4. The crisis and the war declaration—I wanted to make sure the early
battles could happen along with a potential invasion of Tejas, all before
the U.S. showed its teeth—sharp teeth indeed once Winfield Scott
figured out the land war was likely to be a close call.
5. Mexican political will—I needed a victory system that included
sudden death and an end-game uncertainty to keep the U.S. player
on his toes—many gamers with historical hindsight would likely wade
into the game with a lot of confidence. I needed to make things risky
as well as frustrating—all in the context of a ticking clock, since my
reading is that domestic issues were likely to make Americans tired of
the war rather quickly. Originally a sliding scale similar to Wilderness
War, we realized at Origins 2004, thanks to Ken Schultz and Thomas
Cadenhead, that tracking Mexican PW only, and giving the US the
incentive to reduce it, was key to the game’s tempo of play.
6. Unpredictable supply—Supply is randomized and can catch you
sleeping—we wanted that unpredictability from the beginning. The
system is easy enough to track (especially if the non-active player is
watching the card to remind both players to check supply) and makes
the strategy cards slightly different than other games of the genre.
7. What else can I mention to fit this to seven points?? Santa Anna
(or Ana)? Revolving-door politics? Dysentery? Well, I hinted here at
a few things, but I’ll leave the controversies to the internet… see you
at Consimworld.
Now that I have mentioned Mark Herman (up there in point 2),
I should ensure the following is in print: Mark, your game designs
entertain me (us!) and challenge us—they range from the fascinating to the complex, and the latter is a sign that you believe in our
intelligence. You have trusted us to enjoy your games and see history
as you do. Your work is my major inspiration—I hope that Halls of
Montezuma might cross your game table one day, downstairs in your
war room on that well-lit table. This game is my own atypical way
of saying, “Thank you!” (And to be more specific, thank you for the
advice I mentioned above).
Before I depart so you can play the game with a buddy, I should mention something regarding the six year design and development process.
There were some hurdles. I have had two more kids since starting the
work (that makes 7 kids and 2 game designs… my plan is to make it all
even-Steven within 5 years). Also, in 2003 my van was stolen in the wee
hours of New Year’s, and (don’t ask me why) the only prototype game
was in a briefcase in the back. I had to begin from scratch; then, I was
expatriated to Austria to teach there and provide ‘touring’ services for
American students visiting Austria, Italy, and other wonderful locales.
The upside: I witnessed the 200th anniversary of the battle of Austerlitz.
The downside: I was too busy to work on the game from early 2005
to the end of 2006. Thankfully, play testing was underway. We made
it to P500, and then Bill Cooper (who developed Europe Engulfed…
so I knew we were in great hands!) fine-tuned, supervised play tests,
and even used the game in his classes.
And, thank you for being patient. I hope you enjoy the game.
MW

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma

21.0	 Card Histories
1		
Polk Addresses Congress: After learning of the Thornton
Affair, in May, 1846 President Polk called for a joint session of Congress
and requested a declaration of war against Mexico, saying, “The cup of
forbearance had been exhausted even before the recent information from the
frontier of the Del Norte [Rio Grande]. But now, after reiterated menaces,
Mexico has passed the boundary of the United States, has invaded our territory
and shed American blood upon the American soil. She has proclaimed that
hostilities have commenced, and that the two nations are now at war.”
2			No Quarter!: The brutal nature of the Mexican-American War
was made clear by the tendency of both sides to use lethal force, particularly
in the killing of prisoners of war. Santa Anna´s bloody attack on The Alamo,
giving no quarter to the surrendering Americans, gave rise to a wave of
pro-nationalism and anti-Mexican sentiment, particularly in Texas; giving
no quarter in the Mexican War was expected to be a furthering of Santa
Anna’s policy from the earlier battle.
3			
Fremont Declares Bear Flag Republic: Lieutenant Colonel
John Charles Fremont led an American force of 300 men into Alta
California in June, 1845, capturing Santa Barbara and declaring the shortlived Bear Flag Republic, with Fremont as military governor. The Bear
Flag Republic would eventually become the American state of California.
4			
Settlers: Despite the ongoing hostilities, American settlers moved
into the former Mexican territories of Nuevo Mexico and Alta California
at a steady rate.
5			
Guerillas Go Home: Mexican guerilla bands frequently
disbanded as individuals went home to tend to their crops or defend their
farms from hostile Indians.
6			Nicholas Trist, State Emissary: Nicholas Trist was named
emissary to Mexico by President Polk to negotiate the end of the war.
Both Polk and General Winfield Scott soured of Trist’s performance and
he was called home in 1848. Trist ignored the President’s instructions and
negotiated and signed the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo in January, 1848,
which would eventually be approved by both nations.
7 			
Minor Revolt in Baja/17 Baja Revolts Suppressed/19 Provincial Revolt Suppressed/28 Provincial Revolt/42 Major Revolt in Baja!
The government of Mexico was far from stable during its war with the
United States. Control over the provinces from Mexico City was almost
non-existent; the province of Yucatan had revolted in 1841 and declared
itself neutral at the outbreak of hostilities. Several other provinces, such as
Baja California and Alta Mexico, revolted against the central government,
often with covert American encouragement.
8			
Manifest Destiny: A term first used in 1845 by journalist John
L. O’Sullivan while urging American annexation of Texas, “ And that claim
is by the right of our manifest destiny to overspread and to possess the whole of
the continent which Providence has given us for the development of the great
experiment of liberty and federated self-government entrusted to us.”
9			Thornton Affair: In April, 1846, American Captain Seth
Thornton led a company of dragoons on a scouting mission near future
Brownsville, Texas. Thornton encountered a brigade of Mexicans under
Colonel Anastasio Torrejon and was captured along with several of his
officers and men. After news of this reached Washington, President Polk
called a joint session of Congress and asked for a declaration of war with
Mexico.
10		Remember the Alamo!: The Alamo was a fortified chapel in
San Antonio, Texas, defended by Texans during their revolution against
the Mexican government in 1836. The Alamo was captured and the entire
Texan garrison wiped out by a Mexican army commanded by Antonio
Lopez de Santa Anna. “Remember the Alamo!” became a rallying cry for
American troops and Texas volunteers during the Mexican-American War.

21

11		Tejas!: The Department of Tejas, formerly the Mexican State of
Coahuila y Tejas, seceded from Mexico in 1835 and soon afterward became
the independent Republic of Texas. Mexican President Jose de Herrera
sent troops into the Disputed Zone in 1845 to oppose the Republic of
Texas’ claims on Mexican land south of the Rio Grande river.
12		
Santa Anna Elected President: The mercurial Antonio Lopez de
Santa Anna was President of Mexico eleven times in 22 years between 1833
and 1855. Santa Anna declared himself President in 1847, simultaneously
running the Mexican government and Mexican army.
13		
Whigs Oppose War: American political opposition to President
Polk’s drive towards war was strong, particularly among the opposition
party Whigs, whose numbers included Illinois Representative Abraham
Lincoln. Massachusetts Senator Daniel Webster was the leader of the Whig
anti-war movement.
14		Operational Exhaustion: As American armies advanced further
into northern Mexico, their increasingly tenuous supply lines meant long
delays in pushing forward badly needed supplies and reinforcements.
15, 27.	 Local Militia: Local Mexican militia units were frequently called
up to fill in the regulars’ ranks before a battle.
16		
Indian Uprising: While the Mexican and American militaries
clashed on the battlefield, Indian tribes located in the Disputed Zone
raided American forts, waystations, and Baggage Trains.
18		
Baptism of Fire: At the start of hostilities, both the United States
and Mexico had very small national armies and rapidly built up their forces
with influxes of raw volunteers. These green troops, led by inexperienced
officers, would take heavy losses as they learned the harsh lessons of war.
20		
Bad Weather: Although he endeavored to maintain a calm
façade, the General seethed inwardly as the rain continued to pour down,
turning the road into a bog and slowing his army’s march to a crawl. And
so was lost a great opportunity, perhaps never to be regained.
21		
Low Ammo: “We are out of ammunition, General!” the Colonel
cried. The General nodded grimly and pointed his sword at the enemy.
“Very well then, we will give them the bayonet.”
22		
Light Casualties: Sensing a disadvantage, the General broke
off the battle before his force became heavily engaged, saving his army to
fight another day.
23 		Dysentery/26 Malaria/78 Yellow Fever: Disease took a heavy
toll of armies in this era, and a combination of the hot Mexican climate,
inferior hygiene, and poor camp discipline by such large numbers of
volunteers and militia troops only made the danger worse. Over 80%
of American military deaths during the war came from disease or other
non-combat causes.
24, 68	 Forced March: Under the General’s stern eye the soldiers trudged
onward, canteens empty and banners hanging limp in the blazing heat,
their route of march marked by discarded gear, fallen exhausted men, and
dead mules.
25		
Leading from the Front: “Steady, boys, steady !” the General
cried, the morning sun flashing on his sword. “Three cheers for the old
flag and follow me, one more charge and we’ll take those guns !”
29		Negotiations Break Down: Prior to the outbreak of war,
President Polk sent John Slidell to Mexico in 1845 to negotiate American
purchase of Nuevo Mexico and Alta California. The Mexican government
quickly dismissed Slidell’s offer, and attempts to resolve American demands
on Mexican territory short of war ended. During the American Civil War,
Slidell was one of the Confederate ambassadors to Europe imprisoned
by the United States in the Trent Affair that nearly led to war with Great
Britain.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

22

The Halls of Montezuma

30		
Good Ground: In a flurry of dust the scout reined his mount
to a halt. “That’s danged good ground ahead, General !” he barked, eyes
flashing. “Best ground I’ve seen all day. Get a battery of guns up on that
ridge and I reckon you can stop anyone from crossing the river.”
31		
Political Capital: Admittedly an anachronistic term, political
capital is based on a public figure’s favorable image among the populace
and among other important personalities in or out of the government.
Political capital must be spent to be useful, and will generally expire by the
end of a politician’s term in office. In addition, it can be wasted, typically
by failed attempts to promote unpopular policies which are not central to
a politician’s agenda. In the context of the Mexican War, political capital
in both nations was highly variable, and thus unpredictable.
32		Commodore Perry: Matthew C. Perry, Commodore of the
American navy’s Home squadron. Perry relieved David Connor as
commander of the Home squadron after the capture of Veracruz in 1847,
afterward taking the Mexican ports of Tuxpan and Tabasco. Perry would
later gain fame as the leader of the American squadron that sailed to Japan
in 1853 and opened up that country to outside contact.
33		Topographic Engineers: Topographical engineers were first
appointed during the War of 1812. Lack of appropriations caused the
corps to fall out of service during the Mexican War. The event card presents
a ‘what if ’ possibility, wherein the corps becomes active and produces
accurate maps for frontier campaigning in the largely unknown terrain
of Mexico.
34		Robert E. Lee: Lee needs no introduction. He began the Mexican
war as a First Lieutenant on Winfield Scott’s staff, fought in all of Scott’s
major battles, and received brevet promotions for bravery to the brevet
rank of Colonel.
35		Naval Bombardment: The American Home squadron, initially
under the command of David Connor but soon replaced by Matthew
Perry, was a significant weapon for the Americans in their campaign to
capture Mexico’s Gulf ports.
36		
Blockade Declared: After the declaration of war the American
Navy’s Home squadron under Commodore David Connor quickly
established a blockade of the Mexican Gulf coast. Facing overwhelming
American naval superiority, the Mexican Navy sold its largest two warships
to British commercial lines and offered no significant opposition.
37		
War Appropriations: The U.S. Congress passed legislation
authorizing the calling up of volunteers to support the war effort.
Financially, the war cost the US $147 million, including $73 million for
direct costs, $64 million for veterans’ benefits, and $10 million in interest
charges on war loans. A total of 101,000 American soldiers were mobilized,
including 27,000 regulars and 74,000 volunteers; the typical volunteer
served for 10 months. Deaths in battle totaled 1549; another 11,000 died
from disease and accident.
38		Texas Rangers: The official police force and militia of the
Republic of Texas, the Texas Rangers were mustered into federal service in
1846. They were invaluable as scouts and fighters against Mexican guerillas
and hostile Indians, to whom they showed little mercy.
39		
Marines: “From the Halls of Montezuma/To the shores of Tripoli
/We fight our country’s battles /In the air, on land, and sea.” Scott’s army
included elements of the United States Marines, who participated in the
capture of Veracruz and later the storming of Chapultepec Castle during
the siege of Mexico City.
40		
Flying Artillery: Thanks to the innovations of Major Samuel
Ringgold, the “Father of Modern Artillery,” American artillery batteries
were highly mobile and easily moved across the battlefield. They were
dubbed “Flying Artillery” for their speed of action.
41		
Santa Anna Exiled: After the American capture of Mexico
City in August, 1847, Mexican President Santa Anna resigned his office

and was shortly afterward removed from command of the remnant of
the Mexican army by acting President Manuel Pena y Pena. As the treaty
ending the Mexican War entered its final negotiations, Santa Anna was
exiled to Jamaica in May, 1848. He was destined to return and become
president of Mexico one final time in 1853.
43		
U.S. Grant: Hiram Ulysses Grant—known to history as Ulysses
Simpson Grant due to a clerical error while he was a cadet at the United
States Military Academy—future commander of all Union armies during
the American Civil War and President of the United States. Served on
both Zachary Taylor’s and Winfield Scott’s staffs during the Mexican
War, receiving brevets for bravery at the battles of Molino del Rey and
Chapultepec. Be sure to read Grant’s memoirs for a revealing look at the
life of a staff officer during the Mexican-American War.
44		
Thomas J. Jackson: The future “Stonewall” Jackson of American
Civil War fame. Thomas Jackson was a Second Lieutenant in the 1st
United States Artillery Regiment in 1846, with whom he fought in all
of the major battles of Winfield Scott’s campaign. He earned two brevet
promotions for bravery and finished the war as a brevet Major.
45		Commodore Connor: David Connor, Commodore of the
American Home or Atlantic squadron from 1846 to 1847. He led
American naval forces during the siege of Veracruz.
46		Oregon Treaty: Disputes between the United States and Great
Britain over the location of the northern border of American-controlled
Oregon Territory were long-standing and by 1846 some American
politicians were openly calling for war with Britain over the issue. Hence
the slogan, “Fifty-four Forty or Fight !” In 1846, President Polk agreed to
set the boundary at the 49th Parallel and signed the Oregon Treaty, freeing
up American troops who had been guarding the border to transfer south
for service against Mexico.
47		
Pierce Reinforces: General Franklin Pierce, another future
American President, landed a brigade of fresh American troops at Veracruz
in June, 1847 and marched overland to reinforce Winfield Scott’s army.
48		
Pacific Squadron: The American navy’s Pacific squadron,
commanded by Commodores John D. Sloat and Robert F. Stockton during
the Mexican War. Sloat and Stockton were instrumental in leading the
American capture of Alta California.
49		
P. G. T. Beauregard: Pierre Gustave Toutant Beauregard,
future Confederate general from Fort Sumter onwards, was an engineer
Lieutenant on Winfield Scott’s staff at the start of the Mexican War. He
fought in all of Scott’s battles, was wounded at Chapultepec, and received
brevet promotions to Major for bravery.
50		Close Action: A naval term indicating the signal for engagement
of enemy ships with the purpose of their capture or destruction.
51		
Scott Invades: Winfield Scott led American troops in every war
from the War of 1812 to the American Civil War, serving on active duty
at the rank of General longer than any other in American history. With
Zachary Taylor’s campaign in northeastern Mexico running out of steam,
in October, 1846 Winfield Scott presented a plan calling for the capture of
the Mexican port of Veracruz to use as a base for a small army of regulars
to advance on Mexico City along the same route used by Hernando Cortes
centuries earlier. Looking for a way to force a decision on the Mexican
government, President Polk allowed Scott’s plan to move forward.
52		Tejas Volunteers:  After war was declared against Mexico, there
was some confusion in Washington about how to prosecute it. General
Taylor began having significant successes against the northern Mexican
troops just across the Texas border, but there was doubt that he could
proceed all the way to Mexico City, a thousand miles away. It was therefore
decided that several strategies should be attempted. General Zachary Taylor
was to continue building the strength of his army (mainly from Texas
volunteers) and to continue marching from the north as circumstances
permitted.

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

The Halls of Montezuma
53	 Sale of Church Property: Mexico’s financial difficulties lead to
attempts to levy and sieze Church properties despite the strong opposition
of Santa Anna. Under Acting President Gomez, the Mexican congress
voted passage of a law authorizing seizure of Church property. The act led
to outright rebellion (known as the Polka Rebellion). Once Santa Anna
resumed power, the Church paid over 2 million pesos to facilitate repeal
of the act.
54	No Future Glory: Many American military careers were born in the
Mexican War; who knows what the future might have held had Robert
E. Lee been struck down by dysentery or Ulysses Grant killed by a stray
cannonball ?
55	 San Patricios: The Saint Patrick or San Patricio battalion, a Mexican
army unit made out of Catholics who had deserted the American army.
The San Patricios fought at the battles of Buena Vista, Cerro Gordo, and
Churubusco. Many of the San Patricio survivors were captured by the
American army and executed for treason.
56	Reinforcements: The new regiment marched up to the battleline,
their clean uniforms in sharp contrast to the sweaty, dirty, ragged men who
had been fighting all morning. “I’m heartily glad to see you, Colonel,” the
General said, holding out his hand. “Now let’s see about whipping those
fellows.”
57	 Gomez Presidency: Valentin Gomez Farias, acting President of
Mexico from December, 1846 to March, 1847.
58	 Foreign Aid: Seeking to head off the growth of a potentially powerful
North American power, several European governments, including Britain
and Spain, sent aid to Mexico.
59	 Anaya Presidency: Mexican General Pedro Maria Anaya was elected
President of Mexico in November, 1847, to replace acting President Pena.
Anaya began negotiations to end the Mexican-American War but was
unable to complete them before his term expired in January, 1848.
60	 Fresh Troops: Frequently, conscription would bolster a force; or,
rest and recuperation via rotation of troops allowed for enhancement of
effectiveness.
61		
Spies!: During the Mexican War, “no move was made to establish
a permanent intelligence capability,... either in the fighting or in the peace
that followed. [General Zachary] Taylor ignored intelligence almost to
the point of dereliction in his invasion of northern Mexico. General
Winfield Scott, who landed at Vera Cruz and occupied central Mexico,
displayed better intelligence sense. He organized a crude but effective
secret service known as the Mexican Spy Company under Colonel Ethan
Allen Hitchcock.” Ameringer, U.S. Foreign Intelligence, p. 48.
62	Recruits: As Winfield Scott’s army closed on Mexico City, the
Mexicans desperately recruited new units to defend the city, including
the Military Academy cadets who defended Chapultepec Castle.
63	 March Attrition: American troops were not used to the hot, humid
Mexican climate, and suffered greatly during long marches.
64	 Local Militia Raid: Mexican regional militia units attack the long,
vulnerable American supply line.
65	 Yucatan Revolt Suppressed: Yucatan revolted against the Mexican
government and declared its independence in 1841. At the outbreak of the
Mexican-American war, Yucatan remained neutral but the state’s Mayan
population rebelled against the Hispanic-led state leadership during the
Caste War in 1847. The Hispanic government asked for Mexican help
against the Mayans in exchange for rejoining Mexico; the Mayan rebellion
was defeated and Yucatan was re-admitted to the Mexican nation in 1848.
66	 Artillery Duel: The cannonball thumped off the ground and bounded
past the General’s horse. “Mighty good practice,” he said, watching the
enemy gunners scurry around their pieces. With a rumble of hooves and
a clatter of harness a battery came into position next to him. As the crew

23

rushed to unlimber their guns the General cried, “Get some fire going,
boys. Make it bloody hot for ‘em !”
67	 Scott Removed: Following the capture of Mexico City in September,
1847, infighting quickly developed between the prickly Winfield Scott and
several of his general officers. Some of these, particularly Gideon Pillow,
were quick to use political influence. President Polk, fearing the rise of
yet another Mexican War general as political rival, removed Scott from
command in January, 1848.
69	 Morale Loss: A blazing sun; tired, thirsty men who hadn’t eaten in
days; rumors of a great defeat suffered on the coast; the General knew it
would be a hard battle today.
70	 Logistics: Maintaining large armies in a pre-industrial age across the
long open spaces of Mexico and Texas with the added difficulty of desert
climate was very difficult for both nations.
71		
Armistice: After capturing Mexico City in September, 1847,
General Winfield Scott agreed to an armistice with Santa Anna’s
Mexican government to begin peace negotiations. However, Scott did
not understand Santa Anna’s weakness, nor did he anticipate that Santa
Anna would be removed from office and exiled. Negotiations would drag
on until February, 1848.
72	Dug In: Stripped to the waist, sweat pouring off them, the soldiers
dug. One private leaned on his spade and looked up. “Dangit General, are
we fighters or are we moles ?” “No soldier ever died from hard work,” the
General replied. “You’ll thank those dirt walls tomorrow when the balls
are flying.”
73	Taylor Runs for President: After the capture of Monterrey in
September, 1846, American General Zachary Taylor’s campaign in
northeastern Mexico petered out as President Polk, suspicious of Taylor’s
political ambitions, withdrew veteran troops to add them to Winfield
Scott’s army. Democratic President Polk’s distrust of Taylor was largely
driven by Taylor’s Whig sympathies and his fear that Taylor had his eyes on
the presidency. Taylor received the Whig party’s nomination for President
in 1848 and defeated Democrat Lewis Cass to win the White House.
74	Cavalry Charge: Bugles blared, sabers flashed in the sun, and with
a sudden thunder of pounding hooves the cavalry leapt into motion.
Standing in his stirrups, the General cheered his voice hoarse as they swept
towards the enemy line.
75	Deserters: Both nations had small regular armies and relied on
volunteers and local militias to fill in the ranks. Non-professional troops
such as these were unreliable and deserted in large numbers.
76	 Weak Volunteers: The General rode along the line, peering intently
into the faces of his men. A few hard, battle-tested regulars, true, but far
too many young farm boys or homeless adventurers looked back at him
with frightened eyes.
77	 Breach!: One moment the fire-ringed walls were standing stout as
ever, then with a sudden clap like thunder they were down in a cloud of dirt
and debris. A great cheer went up and the troops sprang forward, racing
for the gap. “The walls are down, boys, charge ! Charge !” the General
cried.
79	Cavalry Pursuit: The enemy line broke. Banners, packs, muskets
were tossed aside as men sought only safety, but it wasn’t to be. The cavalry
were among them now, riding them down with sabers flashing, chasing
the survivors towards the horizon.
80	 Artillery Barrage: Behind him the line of guns bucked and roared.
The General raised his telescope again to watch the bursts of dirt and debris
among the enemy’s lines and grunted in satisfaction. “We are kicking the
tarnation out of them,” he bellowed to an aide. “We’ll soon see how long
they can stand it!”

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

24

The Halls of Montezuma

22.0	RULES INDEX
Activate Unit/Force..................................................................... 9.3
Amphibious landing . ........................................................ 9.6, 14.2
Armies—building them ........................................................... 15.1
Artillery loss............................................................................11.2.g
Automatic Declaration of War.................................................18.3.c
Avoid Battle.............................................................................. 10.8
Baggage Train—placement........................................................ 13.5
Battle and Armies.............................................................5.1.c, 15.3
Battle in general........................................................................... 11
Battle procedure........................................................................ 11.2
Battle response cards......................................................8.3.c, 11.2.d
Blockade............................................................................ 9.2, 14.5
Cavalry Withdrawal............................................................... 11.2.b
Chief of staff—Officer effect...................................................12.1.e
Collapse of Mexican government............................................... 18.2
Collapse of Mexican government.............................. 5.1.d, 8.1, 18.2
Committed unit...................................................2.2.a, 11.2.d, 11.4
Control marker placement--Spaces............................................ 13.1
Control of Spaces............................................................... 6.7, 18.1
Control Space....................................................... 6.7.a, 10.2.a, 13.1
Control State......................................................... 5.1.d, 6.9, 18.5.b
Control Zone..................................................................... 6.8, 10.4
Declaration of War effects.......................................................18.3.e
Discard .................................................................................... 17.1
Efficiency roll.................................................................11.2.g, 11.3
End game—die roll................................................................... 18.7
Events—Action cards............................................................... 7.1.b
Events—Strategy cards................................................................. 12
Field command—Officer effect...............................................12.1.e
Fieldworks—building..............................................................13.2.a
Firepower total........................................................................ 11.2.f
Fortifications in Battle......................10.5, 10.8.c, 11.5.d, 11.7, 13.3
Fortresses . ................................................................................ 13.3
Forts—building.......................................................................13.2.a
Guerilla Withdrawal . ............................................................ 11.2.b
Guerillas . ................................................ 10.2.g, 1.2.b, 11.2.c,16.5,
Guerillas in Battle .........................................................11.2.c, 16.5
Hand Size .................................................................................. 8.1
Heat turns........................................................................9.2, 10.2.c
Held card........................................................................... 8.1, 17.2
Inherent units—fortress..........................................................13.3.a
Interception ............................................................................. 10.7
Isolated control markers...................................................6.1, 18.1.a
Lead unit . ..............................................................................11.2.e
Leader losses . .........................................................3.2, 11.2.g, 11.3
Mandated Events on Turn Record Track . .................................7.1.a
Mandatory Events.................................................................. 12.1.b
Mexican naval movement....................................................... 14.1.d
Movement................................................................................. 10.2

Movement Allowances ............................................................. 10.1
Movement attrition.................................................................10.2.c
Movement of Armies................................................................. 15.2
Moving into enemy-occupied spaces...................................... 10.2.b
MP cost for Battle type ..........................................................11.2.a
Naval move........................................................................ 9.6, 14.1
Officer card effects .................................................................12.1.e
Out of supply effects........................................................6.6, 10.2.c
Overrun Battle.......................................................................... 11.6
Placement Actions........................................................................ 13
Placement of Reinforcements...................................................... 3.4
Placement of replacements..................................................... 13.4.b
Port seizure......................................................................... 9.6, 14.4
Post-Battle losses.....................................................................11.5.a
PW changes.............................................................................. 18.5
Raid effects . ............................................................................. 16.4
Raid—PW effect.....................................................................18.5.a
Raids............................................................................. 16.2.b, 16.3
Raids—Action cards . .............................................................16.2.a
Reaction movement/Zones . ............................................ 10.6, 10.9
Removal of forts and fieldworks............................................. 13.2.b
Remove cards...........................................................................8.3.a.
Replacement action................................................................... 13.4
Reshuffle cards......................................................................... 8.3.b
Response cards..........................................................................8.3.c
Retreat................................................................................... 11.5.b
Revolt/Suppression . .............................................10.2.c, 10.3, 18.4
Revolts—effect....................................................................... 18.4.b
Revolts—effect....................................................................... 18.4.b
Revolts—PW effect................................................................ 18.5.b
Revolts—spread......................................................................18.4.a
Santa Anna . .................................................................... 3.6, 7.1.b.
Seizing a port..................................................................... 9.6, 14.4
Siege ............................................................................... 10.5, 13.3
Squadron activation ........................................................... 9.6,14.3
State control........................................................................... 18.1.b
State control and PW............................................................. 18.5.b
Step losses............................................................2.2.a, 11.2.h, 11.4
Strategy card use . .......................................................................... 8
Supply Event............................................................................... 9.2
Supply Wagon/Supply Event check................................... 8.3.d, 9.2
Suppress revolt.......................................................................... 10.3
Type of Battle . .......................................................................11.2.a
Underlined MA . ....................................................................10.2.c
US control of fortress............................................................. 13.3.b
US Declaration of War................................................. 7.1.d, 18.3.b
War and Crisis decks................................................................... 8.2
War declaration table...............................................................18.3.a
War Declaration Table.............................................................18.3.a
War declared at beginning of turn.......................................... 18.3.b

GMT Games, LLC

P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308
www.GMTGames.com

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC

</rulebook>
			
						                           
						               													<description>The Halls of Montezuma is a fast paced game of the Mexican War which takes you back to the era of Manifest Destiny. The Halls of Montezuma is a Card Driven Game, allowing players the opportunity to recreate the various events and actions in Mexico from 1846 to 1848. The historical cast of characters is here, from Doniphan to Arista, Scott to Santa Anna. Even Lee, Jackson, Beauregard and Grant make appearances.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Strategy card play allows you to move your forces, make events happen, activate the fleet, secure control of your lines of communication, and even invade Mexico with General Scott.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The outcome is never a foregone conclusion. Victory comes from driving Mexico's political will down to zero; but each battle's outcome is in doubt - a few troops performing superbly can defeat many troops performing poorly. Mexico can achieve a quick sudden-death victory before the U.S. has declared war and can bring its force to bear.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Components&amp;#10;&amp;#10;        Rules booklet&amp;#10;        Deck of 110 Strategy &amp;amp; Action cards&amp;#10;        One 22x34 mapsheet&amp;#10;        Player aid cards&amp;#10;        Quick Start card&amp;#10;        Two 5/8-inch counter sheets (352 counters total)&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;DESIGNERS Michael Welker &amp;amp; David Fox&amp;#10;DEVELOPER William Cooper&amp;#10;COUNTER ART Rodger B. MacGowan &amp;amp; Mark Simonitch&amp;#10;MAP ART Tim Schlief&amp;#10;CARD ART Mike Simonitch&amp;#10;&amp;#10;(from GMT website)&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2009" />
						               				<minplayers value="2" />
						               				<maxplayers value="2" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="7">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="2" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="2" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="240" />
						               				<minplaytime value="240" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="240" />
						               				<minage value="11" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="4">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="7">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="1" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="6" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="2710" value="Post-Napoleonic" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1019" value="Wargame" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2018" value="Campaign / Battle Card Driven" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2072" value="Dice Rolling" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2850" value="Events" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2078" value="Point to Point Movement" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2070" value="Simulation" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="10642" value="Country: Mexico" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="58087" value="History: Mexican – American War" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="61979" value="Players: Two Player Only Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="72016" value="Players: Two Players Only Wargames" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="1114" value="David A. Fox" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="1113" value="Michael Welker" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="74862" value="Tom Lovell" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="71" value="Rodger B. MacGowan" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="20661" value="Timothy Schleif" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="140" value="Mark Simonitch" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="52" value="GMT Games" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="231" />
			<average value="6.51853" />
			<bayesaverage value="5.60808" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="7252" bayesaverage="5.60808" />
																				<rank type="family" id="4664" name="wargames" friendlyname="War Game Rank" value="1261" bayesaverage="6.00169" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.81044" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="848" />
			<trading value="37" />
			<wanting value="27" />
			<wishing value="68" />
			<numcomments value="124" />
			<numweights value="43" />
			<averageweight value="3.1395" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>