<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="163068">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/9gob752VqEklQFV_gz16hw__thumb/img/C2GPhkDu7fWK6L64MTOaYVRCgS4=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic2585510.png</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/9gob752VqEklQFV_gz16hw__original/img/ivQUea2qrHp2TDLM4i7gp1123vQ=/0x0/filters:format(png)/pic2585510.png</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Trickerion: Legends of Illusion" />
			
						                               				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Trickerion: Légende de l&#039;illusion" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Trickerion: Lendas da Ilusão" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Trickerion: Leyendas de Ilusión" />
			    				
				<name type="alternate" sortindex="1" value="Trickerion: Meister der Magie" />
				<rulebook>R U L E S O F P L AY

I. INTRODUCTION

Y OF MAG
O

E

R

C

IT

TH

IA

Decades ago it used to be a bustling city, the Capitol of Illusion, but now only the shadow of its former glory remains. The golden age ended
the day Dahlgaard the Magnificent, the city’s selfless benefactor and the greatest illusionist in history mysteriously vanished at the finale
of his ultimate performance decades ago. No word was heard of him ever since.
Until now.
One night, four talented illusionists, masters of different fields of magic, received a mysterious invitation. The great Dahlgaard himself, returning
from the unknown, called for them to reveal the secret he had kept for a lifetime: the truth about the Trickerion Stone, his shining amber relic.
Despite what many believed, it was much more than merely his lucky charm. He revealed that the stone bestows supernatural intellect, speed and
perception to its owner – the qualities of the perfect illusionist.
Dahlgaard’s secret was only a part of his grand design: after his death, he wants Magoria to flourish again as the City of Illusion, under
the guidance of a worthy successor, who will inherit the Stone and his whole legacy. This successor is to be chosen from the four illusionists in
a five-week contest for fame and fortune.
With so much at stake, the four magicians will stop at nothing to win.
Who has what it takes to become the next Legend of Illusion?
Read more about Dahlgaard and the Trickerion Stone at www.trickerion.com!

II. GOAL OF THE GAME
In Trickerion – Legends of Illusion, players take on the role of famous stage illusionists in the mystical city of Magoria. Their goal is to
acquire the most Fame over the course of five weeks, thus winning a grand competition for the mighty Trickerion Stone. Players will be
able to learn more and more breathtaking Magic Tricks, acquire Components for them, and extend their team to be able to take more
Actions each turn. Tricks are stored and prepared in the Magicians’ own Workshop. At the end of every turn, each Magician can perform
their own spectacular magic show for Fame, fortune and shards of the mysterious Trickerion Stone. The player who is the most famous
after five weeks wins the game.

2

III. GAME CONTENTS

CONTENT BREAKDOWN

SUMMARY

Below is a quick outline of the game’s components. This section
can always be referenced later, but the rules here are only a
summary - details can be found in the Game Phases chapter.

	1x 	 Main Game Board

Game elements and concepts that are not part of the base game
are always highlighted with this color.

	4x 	 Player Game Boards
	12x 	 Specialist Board Extensions

TRICK CARDS

	 2x	 Wooden Character Disks (8 in each player’s colors)
3

Trick cards come in four different categories:

M

E

	48x 	 Trick cards (4+4+4 in each category)

CH

S

L

	6x 	 Downtown Dice

ANIC

A

	8x 	 Player Markers

PI

RITUA

L

ES

O

CAPE

PTICAL

Magic Tricks are the centerpiece of Trickerion. The core flow of
the game consists of learning these Tricks, obtaining Components
for them, preparing them, and finally combining them to compose
breathtaking Performances in the Theater.

	40x 	 Permanent Assignment cards (10 for each player)
48x 	 Special Assignment cards (12 for each Location)
	90x 	 Power cards (30 in each color)
	40x 	 Performance cards
	8x 	 Magician cards (double-sided)

Trick Category

	8x 	 Magician Poster cards
	12x	 Turn Setup cards

Component
Requirement

	64x 	 Trick Markers
	16x 	 Symbol Markers
	96x 	 Components (40 Basic, 32 Advanced, 24 Superior)
	28x 	 1 Coin Tokens
	16x	 5 Coin Tokens
	27x 	 Prophecy Tokens

Symbol Marker
Slot

‘Prepare’ Action
Point cost

Yields

Trick Marker
Slot

	50x 	 Trickerion Shards
	1x 	 Trickerion Stone turn marker

Endgame
Bonus

Fame
Threshold

Detailed rules regarding Trick cards can be found in the Learn
Trick, Prepare Trick, Set Up Trick and Perform sections.

	4x 	 Magician Workbook
	1x 	 Rulebook

COMPONENTS

Wood

Glass

Rope

Petroleum

Padlock

Mirror

Metal

Fabric

Saw

Animal

Disguise

Cog

Basic
3

Advanced

Superior

Each Trick needs a certain amount of Components to be prepared
and Performed. There are three categories of Components in
Trickerion: Basic, Advanced and Superior, costing 1, 2 and 3 Coins
respectively. They can be bought at the Market Row and are kept
in the Magician’s Workshop.

There are three types of Characters: Apprentices, Specialists and
the Magician, each with a different Action Point value. There are
three sub-types of Specialists: Manager, Assistant, and Engineer.
MAIN GAME BOARD

Detailed rules for Components can be found in the Market Row,
Workshop, and Prepare Trick sections.
ASSIGNMENT CARDS

Assignment cards are used to plan a player’s turn in the
‘Assignment’ phase. Each one represents a Location, where a
Character will be placed. There are four Locations in the base
game: the Downtown, the Market Row, the Workshop and the
Theater. The fifth Location, the Dark Alley, is not used in the base
game. There are two types of Assignment cards: Permanent and
Special.

Permanent Assignment cards
Most Locations are found on the Main Game Board. All Locations
have Character slots (with modifiers), where the Characters can
be placed. Fame points gained during the game are immediately
measured on the Fame Track around the Theater.
The Main Game Board is double sided - the side marked with the
black cat symbol is only used with the Dark Alley expansion.

Special Assignment cards

DOWNTOWN DICE

Permanent Assignment cards are part of the players’ starting
setup. Special Assignment cards can be obtained at the Dark Alley.

These dice are rolled at the beginning of each turn to determine
the options at the Downtown Location for the turn.

See the ‘Assignment’ phase for details on how to use Assignment cards.
WOODEN CHARACTER DISKS

See the ‘Roll Dice’ phase for details.

The wooden disks that can be placed during the game are referred
to as Characters. They are sent to different Locations using
Assignment cards, where they spend their available Action Points
(marked with a symbol) to carry out one or more Actions.

P L AY E R G A M E B O A R D S

The Player Game Board is the Magician’s headquarters. This is
where the Assignment cards are placed during the ‘Assignment’
phase, and where the player’s Components and Tricks are kept. It
also serves as the Workshop Location.

Specialists

Magician

Engineer

Manager

The Player Game Board can be extended to the right by hiring
Specialists.
Assistant

Apprentice
4

At the end of the turn in which a Specialist is hired, the player
receives its respective board extension together with the wooden
Character disk, and places it next to his or her player board.

Trick Slots
Workshop
Slot

See the ‘Hire Character’ Action and the ‘End Turn’ phase for
detailed rules.
THE MAGICIAN CARDS

These cards represent your chosen
Magician. Each has a Favorite
Trick category printed above his or
her name, which is relevant when
learning Tricks.

Component
Slots

Magician Card

The card’s side with the black cat
symbol is used only with the Dark
Alley expansion.

Character Slots

MAGICIAN POSTER CARDS

The Player Game Boards are double sided - the side marked with
the black cat symbol is only used with the Dark Alley expansion.
SPECIALIST GAME BOARD EXTENSIONS

These mini boards serve as extensions for the Player Game Boards.
Each one is associated with a Specialist.
Engineer

Manager

Assistant

Magician Posters are used to Advertise after the ‘Set Initiative
Order’ phase (see the ‘Advertise’ phase).

Trick Slot

P L AY E R M A R K E R S
Multi Component
Slot

The purpose of these colored player markers is to track the players’
Initiative Order and their progress on the Fame track.
TRICK AND SYMBOL MARKERS
Apprentice
Slot

The Engineer’s extension has an additional, special Trick slot.
Whenever this Trick is Prepared, the player receives an additional
Trick Marker on it.

Each player has four sets of Trick Markers with different symbols.
Trick Markers of a specific symbol always belong to, and identify, a
Trick card. A Symbol Marker belongs to each set of Trick Markers,
which is placed on the Trick card when it is learned, assigning the
chosen Symbol to the Trick. During the game, Trick Markers can
be moved from the Trick card onto Performance cards.

The Manager’s extension has two Multi Component slots.
Component piles on these slots count as if they consisted of one
more of that Component.
The Assistant’s extension lets you have an extra Apprentice who
does not have to be paid for in the ‘Pay Wages’ phase.

5

Trick Markers
(on Trick)

Trick Marker

Trick Markers
(on Performance)

TRICKERION SHARDS

These shards are pieces of the legendary Trickerion Stone, and
serve as the third resource next to Fame and Coins.

Symbol Marker

See the ‘Prepare Trick’ and ‘Set Up Trick’ Actions for the detailed
use of Trick Markers.

They are awarded for performing certain Tricks, creating Trick
Links on specific slots on Performance cards, or having your
Engineer in the Theater when you perform.

PERFORMANCE CARDS

In the base game, Shards can be spent to buy additional Action
Points ( ). Excess Shards at the end of the base game are worth
one Fame point each.
TRICKERION STONE

The Trickerion Stone functions as the Turn Counter. At the end
of each turn, it is advanced one step forward on the Turn Counter
track. The base game ends after five turns.

These cards are located in the Theater and each symbolizes
a Performance, consisting of one or more Tricks, which are
represented by the Trick Markers on them. Trick Markers can be
moved onto these cards by taking the ‘Set Up Trick’ Action in the
Theater. The Performances created this way are the main source
of Fame points and Coins. As the game progresses, these cards
will symbolize more and more prestigious Theaters.

MAGICIAN WORKBOOK

The Magician’s Workbook contains
an image of all available Tricks
that can be learned, as well as a
description of each Prophecy, and
a breakdown of the phases of each
turn. It helps players plan in advance
what Tricks to learn and what
Components to buy.

The Magnus Pantheon cards are only used with the Dark Alley
expansion. The Performance cards with gray Trick Markers printed
on them are only used with the optional two-player Duel of
Magicians rules.
COINS

PROPHECIES

Prophecies are not part of the base game - they are only used with
the Dark Alley expansion.
Coins are the basic currency in the world of Trickerion, available in
denominations of 1 (silver) and 5 (gold).

Active Prophecy

The main source of Coins is the payment received in the
‘Performance’ phase, but there are various other sources, such as
the Bank in the Downtown and Trick Links.
Coins are typically spent on buying Components at the Market
Row and paying Wages.

Pending Prophecies

6

The purpose of the Prophecy tokens is to alter certain game rules
turn by turn. At all times, the Prophecy next to the Turn Track
is the Active one, and it affects the game during the given turn,
while the other three (inside the crystal ball) are the Pending
Prophecies, which will take effect in the three subsequent turns.
A detailed explanation of Prophecies can be found in the Magician
Workbook of each player.

CHARACTERS

MAGICIAN POWERS

Magician Powers are not part of the base game - they are only used
with the Magician Powers expansion (see Expansions).

1. 	

Generic Character Disk

2. 	

Magician Disk

3. 	

Assistant Disk

4. 	

Engineer Disk

5. 	

Manager Disk

6. 	

Apprentice Disk

OTHER GAME ELEMENTS

No two Magicians are the same. As they strive for greatness, they
can learn powerful abilities to specialize themselves in their art. In
the game, these abilities are called Magician Powers.

1. 	

Die

2. 	

Component

3. 	

Basic Component

4. 	

Advanced Component

5. 	

Superior Component

6. 	

Trick Marker

YIELDS

TURN SETUP CARDS

1. 	

Fame

2. 	

Coin

3. 	

Shard

OTHER SYMBOLS

1. 		Action Point
2. 		Fame Threshold
3.		Any
(Trick Category or Action)
?

Turn Setup cards are only used with the Duel of Magicians optional
rules. They are used to set up the available Character slots at each
Location at the beginning of each turn.

4. 		Now
5. 		During the ‘End of Turn’ phase

KEY TO THE SYMBOLS USED
CARDS

1. 	

6.	

	Receive Now

7.	

	Receive During the ‘End of Turn’ phase

8. 		Spend
Trick card

9. 		Active Player
10.	

2. 	

Performance card

3. 	

Permanent Assignment card

4. 	

Special Assignment card

	Other Player(s)

11. 		Link
12.	

	Link with Shard

13. 		Performance/Perform
14.		Advertise
15. 		Game End
7

I V. G A M E S E T U P

Riverside Theater Performance cards (drawn randomly from
the remaining cards, not from the Performance Deck) equal
to the number of players minus one. The Magnus Pantheon
Performance cards are not used in the base game.

GENERAL SETUP
Place the Main Game Board in the middle of the table, with the
base game side up.

4.	 Place all Components, Trickerion Shards and Coins in a pile
next to the game board where all players can reach them.

1.	 Separate the Trick cards with Fame Thresholds 1 and 16 (the
number in the star symbol on the Trick card) into four decks
by category, and put them face up above the respective slots
in the Dahlgaard Residence part of the Downtown. Tricks
with a Fame Threshold of 36 are not used in the base game.

5.	 Finally, place the Trickerion Stone on the I. slot of the Turn
Counter track (below the Fame track).
2 - 3 P L A Y E R R U L E S : In a 2 or 3 player game, two or one +1

Action Point slots respectively are not used at the Downtown, Market
Row and Dark Alley Locations. You may use the face-down wooden
disks of the leftover player color(s) to cover these slots for the
duration of the game. Optionally, you may use the Duel of Magicians
rule variant for two-player games (see the Appendix for details).

2.	 Fill up the Market Row’s Buy area with a Wood, a Metal, a
Glass and a Fabric Component. This will be the Market Row’s
initial stock.
3.	 Create the Performance Deck with two Riverside Theater and
two Grand Magorian Performance cards, chosen randomly
and placed on top of each other in this order. Put this deck
face down next to the Theater. Finally, from left to right, fill
up the Performance card slots in the Theater with a number of

2 players

PERFORMANCE CARDS

3 players

TRICKS

4 players

INITIATIVE
ORDER

(see later)

1.

3.

PERFORMANCE DECK
3.

4.

2.

5.

COIN, SHARD AND
C O M P O N E N T S U P P LY
8

P L AY E R S E T U P

•	 A starting hand of 9 Permanent Assignment cards
(3 Theater, 2 Workshop, 2 Market Row, 2 Downtown).

Starting with the player who most recently wore a top hat
and in a clockwise order, each player chooses a Magician with
a Favorite Trick category not chosen before, then receives
the respective Player Game Board and the following:

•	 All Character Disks of the player’s color. Place the
Magician and 1 Apprentice disk on their respective slots
on the Player Game Board. Keep the rest next to the Player
Game Board as a personal supply.

•	 The Magician card with the Base Game side face up.

•	 A Specialist of the player’s choice, its respective Game Board
Extension, and a bonus based on the chosen Specialist:

•	 The Magician Poster card.
•	 All Trick and Symbol Markers in the player’s color (4
different symbols with 4+1 Markers each).

	

•	 Component(s) of the player’s choice for a total Coin value of
2, placed in the Workshop.

» Manager: Additional Component(s) for a total Coin
value of 2, placed on the Manager’s Board Extension.

	

» Engineer: A Trick card of the player’s choice with Fame
Threshold of 1, chosen after all starting Tricks have been
selected, placed on the Engineer’s Board Extension.
Mark it with a Symbol Marker.

	

»
Assistant: An additional Apprentice placed on the
Apprentice slot on the Assistant’s Board Extension.

•	 A Trick card with a Fame Threshold of 1, chosen from the
Magician’s Favorite Trick category, placed in the Workshop.
Mark it with a Symbol Marker.
I M P O R T A N T : If you meet your chosen starting Trick’s

Component requirements with your starting Components, you
receive the Trick with a number Trick Markers on it equal to the
number of overlapping squares on the card’s Trick Marker slot.
This is essentially a free ‘Prepare’ Action for that Trick at the start
of the game (see the ‘Prepare’ under the Locations section).

•	 10/12/14/16 Coins, based on the starting Initiative Order
(see later).
•	 1 Trickerion Shard.

P L AY E R G A M E B O A R D

1 Magician disk + Magician Card
1 Apprentice disk
Components (total Coin value of 2)
1 Trick (Fame Threshold 1)
POSTER

ASSIGNMENT CARDS

ONE CHOSEN SPECIALIST

1 Manager disk
Component(s)
(total Coin value of 2)
TRICK & SYMBOL MARKERS

9

1 Engineer disk
1 Trick
(Fame Threshold 1)
1 SHARD

1 Assistant disk
1 Apprentice disk

COINS

V. G A M E P H A S E S
FIRST TIME SETUP FOR BEGINNERS

SUMMARY

Instead of choosing starting Tricks, Components and Specialists,
we recommend the following starting setup for first-time players:

ROLL DICE

Based on the Favorite Trick category of the chosen Magician:

The six Downtown dice are rolled and placed on the Downtown
Location.

Optical: the Enchanted Butterflies Trick with two Trick
Markers and the respective Symbol Marker, 2 Fabric and
a Manager with 1 Animal.

SET INITIATIVE ORDER

Rearrange the Initiative Order according to the opposite of the
Fame point ranking of each player (the player with the least Fame
points takes the first position). This phase is skipped in the first
turn.

Mechanical: The Linking Rings Trick with two Trick Markers and
the respective Symbol Marker, 2 Metal and an Assistant with 1
Apprentice.
Escape: The Barricaded Barrels Trick with two Trick Markers and
the respective Symbol Marker, 2 Wood and an Engineer with the
Stocks Escape Trick.

ADVERTISE

Players may receive 2 Fame points once by paying 1-4 Coins
depending on their position in the Initiative Order.

Spiritual: the Mind Reading Trick with three Trick Markers and
the respective Symbol Marker, 2 Glass and a Manager with 1 Rope.

ASSIGNMENT PHASE

Players simultaneously plan the upcoming ‘Place Characters’
phase by placing Assignment cards from their hands face down
below their Characters.

STARTING FAME POINTS AND INITIATIVE ORDER

After having completed the Player Setup, place a wooden cylinder
in each of the players’ colors on the Initiative Order circles (left
edge of the Main Game Board) in a random order. This will be
the Initiative Order in the first turn. In the subsequent turns, the
Initiative Order will depend on the players’ Fame points. (see ‘Set
Initiative Order’ phase).

PLACE CHARACTERS PHASE

All Assignment cards are revealed, then, following the Initiative
order, players place their Characters at the Location specified on
the Assignment card below them, one at a time. Characters can
be placed in any order. Based on the amount of Action Points they
have when they are placed, they immediately take Action(s) at the
Location.

2 P L A Y E R R U L E S : In two-player games, only the first and

the third Initiative Order slots are used (this influences the cost
of Advertise).

PERFORMANCE PHASE

In a Thursday to Sunday order, each Magician on the Performance
slots can Perform ALL Tricks on a chosen Performance card with
at least one of his own Trick Markers. The owner of each Trick
Marker receives the respective Trick’s Yields. The Performing
Magician receives additional bonuses.

Then, players on the second/third/fourth slot in the Initiative
Order receive 2/4/6 additional Coins.
Finally, place the second wooden cylinder in each of the players’
colors on the 5 Fame slot on the Fame Track. Since it is possible to
lose Fame points, the starting Fame score is 5.

END TURN PHASE

•	 Pay Wages
•	 Return Characters
•	 Orders Arrive
•	 Move Performance cards
•	 Remove Posters
•	 Move Turn Counter

10

GAME PHASE DETAILS

put their Poster on the slot above their wooden cylinder, and
immediately receive 2 Fame. The Poster cards are removed during
the ‘End Turn’ phase.

ROLL DICE

ASSIGNMENT PHASE

Each turn begins with the starting player rolling the six Downtown
dice. The result of this roll determines:

In the ‘Assignment’ phase, players use their hand of Assignment
cards to plan the placement of their Characters in advance for
the ‘Place Characters’ phase. To plan a Character’s placement,
the player places an Assignment card face down below the
Character disk on the player board. This Character will be placed
at the Location printed on the card during the next phase.

•	 which Trick categories will be available for learning,
•	 which Characters can be hired,
•	 how many Coins can be taken at the Bank.

After the roll, the dice are placed on the respective, matching
colored slots at the Downtown. An X result on a die means no Action
is available for that particular die this turn.

This is done simultaneously by all players until everyone has
either placed a face-down Assignment card below all of his or her
Characters, or chooses not to place any more. Characters with no
Assignment cards below them cannot be placed during the ‘Place
Characters’ phase and will automatically be Idle (see Idle Characters
in the subsequent section).

SET INITIATIVE ORDER

The players’ Initiative Order is always tracked
with the player markers of their color.
At the beginning of each turn, the starting
positions are rearranged based on each player’s
Fame points. The Initiative Order is always set
to be the opposite of the players’ Fame Point
order (the player with the least Fame points
will act first).

Least Fame

PLACE CHARACTERS PHASE

At the beginning of this phase, all previously placed Assignment
cards are simultaneously revealed.
Starting with the first player in the Initiative Order, each player
places one Character on a free Character slot at a Location
(either on the Main Game Board, or the player’s own Workshop).
A Character can only be placed on the Location printed on the
Assignment card below it. Players continue to place one Character
at a time in this manner, until all Characters are either placed or Idle.

I M P O R T A N T : If two or more players finish

their turns on the same Fame slot, reverse
their Initiative Order when it is next set.

Advertise
(2 Fame)

I M P O R T A N T : The ‘Set Initiative Order’

phase is skipped in the first turn.

IDLE CHARACTERS

ADVERTISE

After the Initiative Order is set, players
have the chance to use their Poster cards to
Advertise once per turn. If they choose to
do so, they pay Coins equal to the number
of their slot in the Initiative Order (1-4),

An Idle Character is not placed on any Location during the ‘Place
Characters’ phase, and is left on the player’s Game Board. Idle
Characters are not paid for during the ‘End Turn’ phase. You may
choose to leave a Character Idle by turning its Assignment card
face down during the ‘Place Characters’ phase instead of placing it,
then the phase continues with the next player in the Initiative Order.

Most Fame

11

ENHANCE CHARACTER

You can always buy +1 Action Point once when placing a Character
by paying a Trickerion Shard at any Location except for the
Theater.

When playing with the “Dark Alley” or “Magician Powers”
expansions, other effects can further modify the amount of Action
Points your Characters have.
The placed Character’s Action Points are immediately spent on
one or more available Action(s) at the respective Location - they
cannot be saved for later. The Action Point cost of each Action
is printed in a circle under its symbol. Once the player has taken
all Actions he or she wanted with a placed Character, proceed
with the Character placement of the next player in the Initiative
Order.

The Action(s) a Character can take at any given Location depends
on the following:
•	 Available Action Points when the Character is placed
•	 Available Actions at the Location
The Locations and all their available Actions are discussed in detail
in the Locations chapter, while the Action Point system is detailed
in the subsequent chapter.

CHARACTER PLACEMENT
Downtown Example

THE ACTION POINT SYSTEM

When a Character is placed at a Location, it
receives Action Points, which are spent on one
or more Actions at the Location. The amount of
Action Points is based on the following:
T Y P E O F T H E C H A R A C T E R : determines

the base amount of Action Points when the
Character is placed.
•	 Apprentices: 1
•	 Specialists: 2
•	 Magician: 3
T H E S L O T M O D I F I E R : Character slots at

all Locations have Action Point modifiers printed
under them. When a Character is placed on a
slot, this number is added to or subtracted from
its base Action Point value.

Character Action
Points
Slot Modifiers
Trickerion Shards
(maximum 1)

Special
Assignment Cards
(Dark Alley only)
TOTAL

EXAMPLE
SPENDING

Base APs
Slot Modifier
12

LOCATIONS

FAME THRESHOLD

Each Trick has a Fame Threshold value printed in a star
in the lower right corner. You may only learn a Trick if
you have equal to, or more Fame points than its Fame
Threshold.
Matching Fame Thresholds: If you have less Fame than the
desired Trick’s Fame Threshold, you may pay the difference in
Coins when you use the ‘Learn Trick’ Action to learn it.

Players can use the Downtown to add new Tricks to their repertoire
by visiting the great Dahlgaard in his Residence, expand their team
by hiring Characters from the Inn, or obtain additional Coins when
needed from the Bank.

FAVO R I T E T R I C K C AT E G O R Y

The following Actions can be taken at the Downtown:

You can always choose to learn a Trick from your Magician’s
Favorite Trick Category (symbol over the Magician’s name on the
card) instead of the ones available. A chosen die still has to be set
to its X face if you learn a Trick this way.

L E A R N T R I C K ( 3 ) : The player chooses a
Trick from the Dahlgaard Residence, puts it on
an empty Trick slot in his or her Workshop, and
places an unused Symbol Marker on it.

The category of the newly learned Trick must correspond with the
symbol on one of the Dahlgaard Residence dice. The ‘?’ symbol
means that any Trick category can be chosen.

The player
chooses an Inn die, and places an unused
Character corresponding with the die roll from
his or her supply on the Inn. The chosen die
is then set to its X face. During the ‘Return
Characters’ phase, the hired Character is added to the player’s
team. If it was a Specialist, its Board Extension is also added to the
player’s Game Board. A player may only hire one of each type of
Specialist (Assistant, Engineer, Manager).
HIRE

After learning the Trick, set the corresponding die to its X face.

CHARACTER

(3 ):

T A K E C O I N S ( 3 ) : The player chooses

a Bank die, and takes Coins equal to the die
roll from the supply. Then, the player sets the
chosen die to its X face.
I M P O R T A N T : You DO NOT have to meet a Trick’s Component
requirements to learn it.
I M P O R T A N T : You may return Tricks you no longer need to
the Dahlgaard Residence decks at any time. If you do, remove
all of its Trick Markers from the game (including the ones on the
Performance cards).

13

Acquired Components are placed on the Component slots on the
Player Game Board. Different Components occupy separate slots, but
multiples of the same type are piled upon each other. The maximum
amount a player may have of a Component is 3. You may return
Components to the general supply any time to make room for new ones.

R E R O L L D I E ( 1 ) : The player may reroll

a Dahlgaard Residence, Inn or Bank die. As a
result, the Tricks, Characters and Coins available
in the Downtown may change.
S E T D I E ( 2 ) : The player may freely change

I M P O R T A N T : The Manager’s Board Extension contains two

the result of any one die roll (e.g. change an “X”
roll to a Manager to hire it later).

Multi Component slots. Component piles on these slots count as
if they consisted of one more of that Component.
B A R G A I N ( 1 ) : You may only use Bargain
together with a ‘Buy’ Action. You may decrease
the total price of Components you buy by 1
Coin per Action Point spent on ‘Bargain’. You
may never decrease the total price to 0.
O R D E R ( 1 ) : If players need a Component
which is not currently available in the Market
Row, they have to Order it. For 1 Action Point,
a player may place any Component from the
supply on an open slot in the Order area (as
long as the same Component type is not already
there).

Each Trick has a certain Component requirement. Until these
Components are collected, the Trick cannot be Prepared, and thus
cannot be Performed in the Theater. The Market Row is the place
where these Components can be obtained – for a price.
The following Actions can be taken in the Market Row:
B U Y ( 1 ) : For 1 Action Point, players may buy up to

three Component of the same type. They also have
to pay the price of each Component bought (1/2/3
Coins per Basic/Advanced/Superior Component).
Only Components in the Market Row’s Buy
area (the actual stock) can be bought this way.

These Components will be moved to the corresponding slot in the
Buy area during the ‘Orders Arrive’ phase, and will be available for
Buying in the following turn. See ‘End Turn’ phase for more details.
Q U I C K O R D E R ( 2 ) : In some situations,

players can’t afford to wait a turn for the desired
Components. For 2 Action Points, a player
may place any Component on the Quick Order
slot in the Market Row (if the slot isn’t empty,
return the Component there to the supply first). That Component
becomes part of the Market Row’s stock this turn (for all players),
and can be acquired with the ‘Buy’ Action, but costs 1 additional
Coin. During the ‘End Turn’ phase, the Component on the Quick
Order slot is returned to the supply.

I M P O R T A N T : Bought Components are taken from the general

supply, not from the Buy area itself. The number of Components
are not considered limited, in the unlikely case that a Component
type runs out, replacements can be used.
14

If you Prepare a Trick, place a number of Trick Markers on it equal
to the number of overlapping squares in the lower left box. Use
Trick Markers with the same symbol as the Symbol Marker you
placed on the Trick when you learned it.

EXAMPLES OF MARKET ROW ACTIONS

A player places his Engineer (2 ) on the +2 Market Row slot.
He has 2+2=4 Action Points in total. He spends two to Order
a Petroleum (-1 ) and a Padlock (-1 ), and two more to Buy
two Ropes (-1 ) and three Metal (-1 ). Buy Actions also have
a Coin cost: the player pays 7 (2*2+3*1) Coins for the bought
Components.

I M P O R T A N T : If you do not meet a Trick’s Component

requirements, or already have one or more Trick Markers on it,
you cannot use the ‘Prepare’ Action on that Trick.
I M P O R T A N T : The Components required for the Trick are NOT
returned to the supply when preparing it.

A player places his Magician (3 ) on the +2 Market Row slot,
so he has 3+2=5 Action Points in total. He desperately needs a
Mirror, but it is not available this turn. He is also short on cash, so
he spends two Action Points to Quick Order a Mirror (-2 ), one
more to Buy it (-1 ) and two more to Bargain its price down from
4 Coins to 2 (-2 ).

EXAMPLE OF A ‘PREPARE’ ACTION

The player has 3 Fabric and 3 Wood, so he can use the ‘Prepare’
Action on his card Manipulation Trick (1 ). When he learned the
Trick earlier, he marked it with the spade symbol, so he receives 2
Trick Markers with the Spade symbol now.
I M P O R T A N T : Tricks on the Engineer’s Trick slot receive 1

additional Trick Marker when Prepared.
The following Actions become available when the respective Specialist
is hired. They can be taken by any Character, not only the Specialist.
Remember: The Specialists’ Trick/Component/Apprentice slots are
better than the original ones on the Player Game Board!

The Workshop slightly differs from the other Locations in two ways:
•	 Each player has their own respective Workshop where only
their own Characters can be placed.
•	 The Action Point cost of the ‘Prepare’ Action varies depending
on the Tricks you have.

M O V E T R I C K S ( 1 ) : Move one of your
Tricks to the Engineer’s Trick slot, or exchange
the Trick there with another of your own Tricks.

The following Actions can be taken in the Workshop:

M O V E C O M P O N E N T S ( 1 ) : Move one of

P R E P A R E ( 1 - 3 ) : The number of Action

your Component piles to the Manager’s Multi
Component slot or exchange the pile there with
another of your Component piles.

Points required to Prepare each Trick is printed
in a circle in the lower left box (the Trick Marker
slot). Like at other Locations, you may take
multiple ‘Prepare’ Actions with one Character
- the only limit is the number of Action Points
you have.

M O V E A P P R E N T I C E S ( 1 ) : Permanently

reallocate one of your Apprentices and the
Assignment card below it (if any) to the
Assistant’s Apprentice slot (if it’s empty).
15

TRICK LINKS

After Setting Up a Trick Marker, if two of
the same Trick Category symbols are in the
same Link circle (as seen on the picture),
those two Tricks are linked. The player who
created the Link(s) immediately receives a
bonus for each Link depending on the Fame
Threshold of the Trick he created the Link
with. Additionally, if there is a Shard symbol
in the Link circle where the Link is created,
each player with a Trick Marker in the link also
immediately receives a Trickerion Shard. It is
possible to create multiple Links with a single
Trick Marker placement. Creating Links is not
obligatory.

The Theater is the place where the Tricks you learned and perfected
turn into spectacular Performances, yielding massive amounts of
Fame and Coins to the player at the end of each turn.
In terms of Character placement, the Theater slightly differs from
other Locations in three ways:
•	 Weekday Restriction: All
Character slots in the Theater
are divided into four weekdays:
Thursday, Friday, Saturday
and Sunday. A player can only
place his or her Character(s)
on exactly one weekday during
a turn, which must not already
be occupied by an opponent.

BONUS FOR LINKING TRICKS

•	 Fame Threshold 1: 1 Fame or 1 Coin
•	 Fame Threshold 16: 2 Fame or 2 Coins
•	 Fame Threshold 36: 3 Fame or 3 Coins

•	 No ‘Enhance Character’: You cannot buy additional Action
Points for your Characters in the Theater for Trickerion Shards.

R E S C H E D U L E ( 1 ) : You may move one

•	 Performance Slots: The bottom line of the Character slots
are the Performance slots, where only Magicians can be placed.

of your Trick Markers from a Performance
card to a free slot on the same or any other
Performance card. Rules of Trick Marker
placement apply. You don’t receive Link
Bonuses for moving a Trick Marker this way.

The following Actions can be taken in the Theater:
S E T U P T R I C K ( 1 ) : The player may move

one of his Trick Markers from a Trick in the
Workshop onto a free slot on a Performance
card of his or her choice – this Trick will be
represented by the Marker until it is either
Performed, or the Performance card is discarded
at the end of a turn.

P E R F O R M ( M A G I C I A N O N L Y ) : This
is a special Action that can only be taken by
the Magician in the subsequent ‘Performance’
phase.

During the ‘Place Characters’ phase, the player places his or her
Magician on one of the open Performance slots (only if he has
a Theater Assignment card, of course). This does not have any
immediate effect in the ‘Place Characters’ phase - the Magician’s
three Action Points are forfeited. The ‘Perform’ Action will be
executed during the subsequent ‘Performance’ phase.

RULES OF TRICK MARKER PLACEMENT

•	 The Trick Marker’s corner that corresponds with the Trick’s
category must be in a Link circle connecting two slots.
•	 Two Trick Markers of the same color AND the same symbol
(e.g. two blue Spades) cannot be in the same Performance.

N O T E : Magician Characters can also be used to Set Up and

Reschedule Tricks (like any other Character) but in this case they
have to be placed on the backstage slots, so they cannot Perform
this turn.
A detailed example of a ‘Place Characters’ phase in the Theater
can be found in the Appendix.

16

THE PERFORMANCE PHASE

YIELD MODIFIERS

The payouts of Thursday and Sunday
are different than those of Friday and
Saturday. When having at least one
Character on a Thursday slot, the
player subtracts 1 from the Fame and Coin yields of all of his or
her Performed Tricks, while when having one on any Sunday slot,
he or she adds 1 to the Fame and Coin yields of all of his or her
Performed Tricks. This also applies when the player’s Tricks are part
of another player’s Performance, and when the player’s Magician
is not present in the Theater. If the player has no Characters at
all in the Theater when his Tricks are Performed, he receives the
same Yield modifiers as the performer. A Trick’s Fame or Coin
yield can never be less than 0.

Once all players have placed all Characters they wanted, the
‘Performance’ phase begins. The players with their Magicians on
the Performance slots may now take their ‘Perform’ Actions. The
Performances are rewarded with generous amounts of Fame and
Coins, and occasionally Trickerion Shards.
PERFORM

In a Thursday to Sunday order (NOT in the Initiative Order), a
player with a Magician on the respective Performance slot may
choose a Performance card that has at least one of his or her Trick
Markers on it, and Performs ALL Tricks on it. The Performance
card may have Trick Markers from other players on it as well. In
this case, those opponents are guest performers in the show, and
their Tricks are also Performed.

P E R F O R M E R B O N U S E S (P E R F O R M E R O N LY )

After a Performance is concluded, all Trick Markers from the card
are returned to their owner’s unused supply, then players may
move on to the next Performance.

On top of the Yields of his or her Tricks, the Performing Magician
also receives the following bonuses:
•	 Link Bonus: 1 Fame for each Trick Link in the Performance.
•	 Specialist Bonus: The Performing
Magician also receives the following
bonuses if he or she has Specialist(s)
behind them in the Theater this turn:
	

» 2 Fame for an Assistant

	

» 3 Coins for a Manager

	

» 1 Trickerion Shard for an Engineer
•	 Performance card Bonus: The Fame,
Coin or Shard value printed in the bottom
box of the chosen Performance card.

Once all Performances are concluded and everyone received their
payouts, the ‘Performance‘ phase is over and the ‘End Turn’ phase
begins.
PERFORM (SUMMARY)

In the weekday order, players with a Magician on one of the
Performance slots choose ONE Performance card with their own
Trick Marker(s) on it and Perform ALL Tricks on it. All players
receive the Yields after their own Tricks.
•	 Performer receives 1 bonus Fame per Link in the Performance.

Y I E L D PAY M E N T ( E V E R Y O N E )

•	 Performer receives bonus Fame, Coins or Shards based on
their Specialist(s) in the Theater.

All players with at least one Trick Marker in the
Performance receive the Yields (Fame, Coin and
Shard) of ALL of their own Trick cards represented by
their Trick Markers on the Performance card.

•	 Performer receives bonus Fame, Coins or Shards based on
the chosen Performance card.

17

•	 Remove Posters: All Magician Poster cards are returned to
their owners’ hands.

END TURN PHASE

The ‘End Turn’ phase consists of six quick sub-phases to wrap up
the turn and prepare for the new one.

•	 Move Turn Counter: Advance the Trickerion Stone one step
forward on the Turn Counter track.

•	 Pay Wages:
	

» 1 Coin is paid for each working Apprentice (except for
the one on the Assistant’s Board Extension).

	

» 2 Coins are paid for each working Specialist.

	» P
 layers who cannot pay Wages lose 2 Fame for each
Coin not paid, to a minimum of 0. Wages must be
paid as long as the player has at least 1 Coin.
•	 Return Characters: Every Character (including the ones
hired during the turn) is returned to their owner’s Game
Board. If a Specialist was hired, its respective Board Extension
is added to its owner’s Game Board.

This concludes the game turn - after the Turn counter has been
moved, a new turn begins.
GAME END

•	 Orders Arrive: Move all Components from the Order area to
the respective slots in the Buy area. The Components already
on those slots are replaced by the ordered Components and
returned to the supply. The Component in the Quick Order
slot is also returned to the supply.

After the fifth turn’s ‘End Turn’ phase, a final scoring occurs,
where players can collect further Fame points based on the assets
they acquired throughout the game. In the Initiative Order, each
player receives:
•	 1 Fame for each unspent Trickerion Shard
•	 1 Fame per 3 leftover Coins
•	 2 Fame for each Apprentice
•	 3 Fame for each Specialist
After the final scoring is concluded, the game ends and the
player with the most Fame points wins, and receives the mighty
Trickerion Stone. If there is a tie, the player who’s ahead in the
Initiative Order wins.

•	 Move Performance cards: All Performance cards are moved
one slot around the Theater in a clockwise direction. From
the third turn onward, the last Performance card (and all
Trick Markers on it) is discarded. Then, the top card of the
Performance deck is placed on the leftmost empty slot. This
means 2/3/4 players will always have 3/4/5 Performance
cards available during turns 3-5.
2 Players

3 Players
4 Players
18

V I . E XPA N S IO N S

P L AY E R S E T U P

Players use the Magician card with the side
with the black cat symbol face up. In this
game variant, each Magician has an important
Special Ability that can greatly influence the
game play. Refer to the Appendix for the
detailed explanation of each Magician Ability.

THE DARK ALLEY
This expansion adds the following new elements to the game:
•	 A new Location: the Dark Alley
•	 Two additional turns: the game will end after seven turns
instead of five

Each player receives a starting hand of 6 Permanent
Assignment cards (2 Theater, 1 Workshop, 1
Market Row, 1 Downtown, 1 Dark Alley).

•	 An additional tier of Trick cards, with a Fame Threshold of 36
•	 Prophecies that alter the game rules for a turn
The following changes apply to the base game rules:
GENERAL SETUP

Flip the Main Game Board and all Player Game Boards to their
“Dark Alley” side (marked with a black cat symbol). Separate
all Trick cards into four decks by category and put them face up
above the respective slots in the Dahlgaard Residence part of the
Downtown. Each deck should consist of 12 Trick cards instead of
the base game’s 8.

After the General and Player Setup is finished, randomly choose
three Pending Prophecies, and place them on the respective
slots on the Fortune Teller orb. Put the remaining Prophecies in
a face down pile next to the Main Game Board (there is no Active
Prophecy in the first turn).

Shuffle the four Special Assignment decks (sorted by Location)
and put them face up on the respective slots in the Dark Alley.

PLACE CHARACTERS PHASE

Players can also use the Dark Alley Location during the
‘Assignment’ and ‘Place Characters’ phases.

If the Magicians are not afraid to get their hands dirty to gain
an edge in the fierce competition, the Dark Alley is the place to
go. Here, the standard Assignments can be spiced up with some
dirty tricks, and even the future can be influenced by visiting the
mysterious Fortune Teller.

Create the Performance Deck with two Magnus Pantheon, two
Grand Magorian and two Riverside Theater Performance cards,
chosen randomly and placed on top of each other in this order.

SPECIAL ASSIGNMENT CARDS

In the Dark Alley, players can acquire Special Assignment cards
for each of the other four Locations. When drawn, these cards
are added to the player’s hand of Assignment cards, and are used
during the subsequent ‘Assignment’ phases just like the Permanent
ones (they are placed below Characters, which are later placed on
the Location indicated on the card).
19

•	 Discard Special Assignment cards: All used Special
Assignment cards are discarded into a face-down discard pile.
Face-down cards below Idle Characters are not considered
used, and are returned to the player’s hand. After all used
Special Assignment cards are discarded, the top card of each
Assignment deck is put to the bottom.

The two differences between Permanent and Special Assignment cards:
•	 Special Assignment cards can only be used once. During the
‘End Turn’ phase, used Special Assignment cards are discarded
into a face-down discard pile.
•	 Each Special Assignment card has a
powerful bonus printed on it. This bonus
typically enhances a specific Action
(shown by the framed image above the
card text) at the card’s Location, and
only applies for one such Action, even if
the player takes more than one of that
Action with the Character (an exception
is the ‘Traveling Merchant’ card). When a Character is placed
using a Special Assignment card, any Action can be chosen at
the Special Assignment card’s Location, but if it’s not the one
enhanced by the card, the bonus is lost. Some cards have the
“?” printed in the frame; in that case the bonus is applicable to
any Action at the Location once. When the Character is placed,
players may always choose to forfeit the Special Assignment’s
ability and use it to gain +1 at that Location instead.

GAME END

The game ends after the seventh turn instead of the fifth. The
final scoring is different from that of the base game. All players
receive:
•	 1 Fame for each unspent Trickerion Shard
•	 1 Fame per 3 leftover Coins
•	 2 Fame for each unused Special Assignment card in their hand
Players may potentially also gain Fame points for their Tricks
with a Fame Threshold of 36. Each of these Tricks has a condition
printed on the bottom. If both the condition and the Trick’s
Component requirements are met, the player scores an amount
of Fame stated in the condition at the end of the game.

The following Actions can be taken in the Dark Alley:

EXAMPLE

D R A W F I R S T C A R D ( 1 ) : The player

The player has the Assistant’s Revenge Trick in his Workshop, and
he has the necessary Components for it. If he also has an Assistant
at the end of the game, he receives 7 additional Fame in the end
game scoring.

draws the top card of any Special Assignment
deck in the Dark Alley.
D R A W F U R T H E R C A R D S ( 2 ) : The
second and further Special Assignment cards
drawn cost 2 Action Points each.

F O R T U N E T E L L I N G ( 1 ) : The player

may move each Pending Prophecy one slot in
a clockwise direction.

END TURN PHASE

The following sub-phases are added to the ‘End Turn’ phase:
•	 Move Prophecies: The Active Prophecy is discarded and
the Pending Prophecy in the leftmost slot is moved to the
Active Prophecy slot adjacent to the Turn Counter track. This
Prophecy will be active during the next turn and will influence
the game rules. Move the remaining Prophecies in clockwise
order, then draw a new one and place it on the rightmost
Prophecy slot.

20

TRICKERION SHARDS

MAGICIAN POWERS

In this game variant, Trickerion
Shards are stored on the Power
slots of the Player Game Board
by putting each received Shard on
the Shard symbols there. Shards
must be added from the bottom
up (starting with the 1 Shard slot),
and spent from the top down. A
Power slot with a Shard on all of
its Shard symbols is considered
open and Powers can be placed
there. When a Shard is spent
from a Power slot, the Power
placed there is immediately
returned to your hand.

This expansion introduces a new element to the game: Magician
Powers. These offer a powerful new way to customize your
Magician and add further strategic depth to your game.
The Magician Powers variant can only be played together with the
Dark Alley variant.
The following changes apply to the basic game rules when playing
with Magician Powers:
GENERAL SETUP

Shuffle each of the three Power decks (yellow, orange and red), then
place them face down next to the Main Game Board where players
can conveniently reach them. Similarly to Trick cards, Magician
Powers of different colors also have Fame Thresholds of 1, 16 or 36
(printed in a star on each side of the card).

In case you have a Shard on all
slots, and have excess ones, those
are spent first.

Spend Shards

Receive Shards

GAME END

The final scoring is different from that of the base game or the
Dark Alley expansion. All players receive:

P L AY E R S E T U P

•	 1 Fame per 3 leftover Coins

In addition to the basic starting setup, each player receives 4
Magician Powers of each color (12 in total). Players then evaluate
these cards and discard any 4, so they have 8 to use throughout
the game.

•	 2 Fame for each unused Special Assignment card in their hand

ASSIGNMENT PHASE

Players may potentially also gain Fame points for their Tricks
with a Fame Threshold of 36. Each of these Tricks has a condition
printed on the bottom. If both the condition and the Trick’s
Component requirements are met, the player scores an amount
of Fame stated in the condition at the end of the game.

At the beginning of the ‘Assignment’ phase, each player may learn
up to one Power card.

In this game variant, Trickerion Shards do not grant Fame points
at the end of the game by default.

Each player receives 3 Trickerion Shards instead of 1.

Powers are learned by placing them face up next to the Power
slots on the left edge of the Player Game Board. A Power can only
be placed next to a Power slot if
•	

It is printed on the Power card as a valid slot

•	

The slot is opened with Trickerion Shards (see below under
Trickerion Shards)

•	

You meet the Power’s Fame Threshold (or pay the difference
between the Fame Threshold and your actual Fame with
Coins)

If a slot already has a Power placed next to it, you must return it to
your hand before placing a new Power there.
21

VII. APPENDIX

E L E C T R A ( S U P E R C H A R G E ) : You

may choose to pile two Markers of the
same Trick on a Trick slot when she sets
up a Trick. It counts as one Trick and
Link Bonuses are paid only once. When
performed, this Trick yields 1/2/3 additional
Fame point(s) and Coin(s) depending on
its Fame Threshold (1/16/36).

MAGICIAN ABILITIES
THE MECHANIKER (MECHANICAL
E N H A N C E M E N T ) : Once per turn, one

of your Apprentices receives an additional
Action Point when placed at any Location
except for the Theater.

THE GENTLEMAN (MAGIC FOR
T H E M A S S E S ) : Whenever the Magician
is placed on a Downtown, Market Row or
Dark Alley slot, you receive Fame equal to
the number of Trick cards you have.

PRIESTESS OF MYSTICISM (FATE
W E A V I N G ) : For 1 Dark Alley Action

Point, you may discard the Active Prophecy,
then replace it with a Pending Prophecy and
draw a new one in its place.

OPTIONAL RULE VARIANT

MASTER OF CHAINS (BREAKING

DUEL OF MAGICIANS

F R E E ) : Before the ‘Performance’ phase,

you may take a special ‘Reschedule’ Action
without placing any Characters. Unlike the
normal ‘Reschedule’ Action, you receive the
Link Bonuses if you create Link(s) with this
placement.
THE

GREAT

OPTICO

The Duel of Magicians game variant is an optional rule set designed
to make the traditional two-player games more tense and diverse.
Two new game elements are used in the Duel of Magicians:

(MIMESIS):

Once per turn, you may use one of your
Permanent Assignment cards with an
effect of an opponent’s revealed Special
Assignment card of the same Location.

•	

Performance cards with gray Trick Markers printed on
them

GENERAL SETUP

Create a deck with five (base game) or seven (Dark Alley) face-up
Turn Setup cards and place them next to the Main Game Board.

You may choose to receive the Yield of an
opponent’s Trick in the same Performance
instead of your own Trick’s Yield, as long as
you are the Performer and the opponent’s
Trick has the same or lower Fame Threshold
as yours. The opponent receives one less
Fame for the Trick stolen this way.
SPIRITMASTER

Turn Setup cards

The following changes apply to the base game rules:

THE RED LOTUS (TRICK STEAL):

YORUBA

•	

Use the Performance cards with gray Trick Markers printed on
them to create the Performance Deck.
ROLL DICE

After rolling the Downtown dice, place the top card of the Turn
Setup card deck next to the deck. Based on the layout printed
on the card, cover 2 slots in the Downtown, Market Row and
Dark Alley, and 2 Weekdays in the Theater using the face-down
wooden disks of leftover player colors.

(SOUL

P O S S E S S I O N ) : Once per turn, before

an opponent chooses a card to Perform,
you may pay one Shard. If you do, you may
choose the card to Perform for that player.
The chosen card must have at least one of
the opponent’s Trick Markers on it.

This way, there will be different Character slots and Weekdays
available each turn, and, since players can always see the
upcoming card, they can plan one turn ahead.
TRICK LINKS

Players may now create Links with the ‘neutral’, gray Trick Markers
printed on the Performance cards by default.

22

CREDITS

PRODUCER

Brent Lloyd
GAME DESIGN
CHARACTER MODELS

Viktor Péter

Szabina Szőgyi as Assistant

Richárd Ámann

Benjamin Tompai as Assistant

GAME ARTWORK

Anna Kokavecz as Manager

Villő Farkas – Art Director (Interface, Character Art, Cityscape)

Péter Biacsics as Manager

Lacza Fejes – Illustrator (Trick illustrations)

Kriszta Vészi as Engineer

Csilla Bíró – Illustrator (Trick illustrations)

Péter Csaba as Engineer

Márton Gyula Kiss - Illustrator (Trick illustrations)

Emőke Bada as Fortune Teller

Ágnes Staudt – Illustrator (Workshop art)

Bálint Bada as Yoruba Spiritmaster

Attila Sáfrány – Illustrator (Posters)

Soma Hajnóczy as The Gentleman

Gergő Ádám – Illustrator (Posters)

Dorka Péter as Electra
Gergely Karácsonyi as the Master of Chains

RULEBOOK EDITORS

Hai Thanh Le Phuong as The Red Lotus

Viktor Péter

SPECIAL THANKS

Villő Farkas

4330 awesome Kickstarter backers, who helped us make
Trickerion a reality,

PROOFREADERS

Rebecca and Sven Stratmann for rallying more than 100 German
backers for our Kickstarter campaign,

Jesús Sánchez López
Lutz Pietschker

Herbert Székely and András Kormanik for their essential help in
launching our Kickstarter campaign,

Lars Frauenrath
Fabien Allois

Soma Hajnóczi for sneaking some real magic into Trickerion,

Sherry Tiao

Richard Ham, Christopher Dickinson, Antonios Sartzetakis,
Ryan LaFlamme and Markus Weihrauch for reviewing the game,

P L AY T E S T E R S

Péter Csaba from DropBy Digital for helping us since the very
beginning in every possible way,

Special thanks to Géza Gálos and Dániel Tóth-Szegő for the
dedicated playtesting and the excellent ideas!

Gergely Karácsonyi from DropBy Digital for the office space
and the awesome website,
Ferenc Somoskői for the encouragement and for spreading the
word about Trickerion,

Ádám Jóna, Ádám Török, Ádám Turczi, Ágnes Viktória Takács,
Anna Kokavecz, Anton Bendarjevskiy, Balázs Hámori, Balázs
Lenhardt, Bastian Zug, Bence Krénusz, Benedek Farkas, Benjámin
Tompai, Bettina Krénusz, Dániel Turchányi, Dávid Tóth, Dorka
Péter, Eszter Teszárik, Ferenc Somoskői, Gábor Bálint, Katalin
Marosy, Kriszta Vészi, Krisztina Szeder – Szabó, László Rigler, Luca
Bonta, Mihály Vincze, Péter Biacsics, Péter Csaba, Péter Péter,
Péter Somogyi, Róbert Ámann, Sándor Tabajdi, Soma Hajnóczy,
Szilvi Vincze, Tivadar Farkas, Zoltán Dervadelin, Zoltán Papp

The SpeakEasy guys for the videos,
Viktor Csete for the beautiful and timely prototypes,
Szabina Szőgyi for her essential help in Essen,
And most of all, our parents, friends and partners for helping
and motivating us on the long road.
THANK YOU!

Everyone from Anduril’s Flame Club, Gém Club and Essen Spiel
2014 who played Trickerion and gave us excellent feedback.

© MindClash Games, 2015. All rights reserved.
23

EXAMPLE A: CHARACTER
AND TRICK MARKER
PL ACEMENT IN THE THEATER

EXAMPLE B: PERFORMANCE
PHASE

The green player placed his Magician on the Sunday Performance
slot to be able to Perform in the upcoming phase (1). No other
player can place any Character on any Sunday slot for the
remainder of the turn. Green could still place other Character(s)
on the Sunday backstage slots, but he already has leftover
Trick Markers to perform from the earlier turns (on the first
Performance card).

The blue, yellow and green players will be performing this turn.
Having chosen Thursday, the blue player is the first to choose
which card to Perform. He chooses the third one, with two of his
own and one red Trick Marker on it. He receives the Yields printed
on the two Trick cards corresponding to the blue Markers, but he
has to subtract 1 Coin and 1 Fame from each Trick’s Yields (-2/-2
total) for performing on Thursday. Additionally, he receives 2
bonus Fame points for the 2 Links in the Performance, 2 bonus
Fame for having the Assistant in the Theater, and another 2 bonus
Fame for the chosen Performance card.

The yellow player places his Manager on the Friday slot (2). The
Friday performance is before Saturday and they have the same
Yields, so the yellow player has a better chance to perform the
card he likes. He has 2 Action points, so he chooses to set up 2
Tricks (2a and 2b). This creates a Link, which immediately yields 1
Fame or 1 Coin to the yellow player.

The red player also receives the Yield on his Trick card corresponding
to the red Marker. The -1/-1 deduction does not apply to him since
he chose Saturday this turn.

The blue player places his Assistant on a Thursday slot (3). This
gives him +1 Action Point, adding up to a total of three, but a -1
Fame/-1 Coin deduction later for each of his Performed Tricks.
For two Action points, he places 2 Trick Markers (3a and 3b),
creates a Link, and receives his choice of 2 Coins or 2 Fame (the
spade Trick is an advanced one, with Fame Threshold 16). For his
third Action Point, he places a third Trick Marker on the second
card, creates a Link with the yellow player, and receives 2 more
Coins or Fame (3c). Again, the Spade Trick is an advanced one
with a Fame Threshold of 16.

The yellow player chooses the second Performance. He receives
his Tricks’ Yields, 3 bonus Fame for the 3 Links on the card, 3
bonus Coins for his Manager in the Theater, and 1 Fame for the
chosen Performance card. The blue and the red players also
receive the Yields for their individual Tricks, the blue player with a
-1/-1 deduction for having chosen Thursday.
Finally, the green player chooses the first card, receives the
Yields of his two tricks, each with a +1/+1 bonus for performing on
Sunday. He also receives +2 Fame for two Links on the card (the
green and the yellow Trick Markers are not Linked), and 1 Coin
for the chosen Performance card. The yellow and the red players
also receive the Yields for their single Tricks, with no bonus or
deduction (for having chosen Friday and Saturday, respectively).

The yellow player places an Apprentice on the remaining Friday
slot. For his 1 Action Point, he places a Trick Marker on the first
card, but since his Trick is of the Mechanical category, he is unable
to create a Link (4).
This turn, the red player uses his Magician to set up Tricks instead
of Performing (5). His goal is to have his Tricks performed by
other players. He forfeits the Performer Bonus this way, but it
lets him use the 3 Action Points of his Magician. He uses them to
set up 3 Tricks, on different Performance cards each, so they are
all sure to be performed (5a, 5b and 5c). He is also able to create
a Link with each placement.

The blue player could also have chosen the second Performance,
since he has one Marker in it. In this case, he would receive the
Yield of only one Trick, but three bonus Fame instead of two,
because there are three Links in this Performance. This would
leave the first Performance as the yellow player’s only choice,
and the third card would not be performed at all, since the red
Magician is in the backstage rather than the Performance slot.
This scenario would be the worst for the green player, since he
would have nothing to perform. He would still receive the Yields
of his two Tricks in the yellow player’s Performance, along with a
+1 Fame and +1 Coin Yield bonus for each Trick (for Sunday), but
he would have to forfeit the Performer Bonuses.

The blue player places his Magician on the Thursday Performance
slot (6). This makes him the first performer in the ‘Performance’
phase.
Finally, the yellow player places his Magician on the Friday
Performance slot (7).

24

EXAMPLE A
4.
4
3.

2.

5A

5.

2B
6.

7.

1.

2A

3C
5B

3A

3B
5C

EXAMPLE B

1.

2.

3.

25

</rulebook>
			
						               													<description>Trickerion is a competitive Euro-style strategy game set in a fictional world inspired by the late 19th century urban life and culture, spiced with a pinch of supernatural.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Players take on the roles of rival stage illusionists, each with their own strengths and characteristics. They are striving for fortune and fame in a competition hosted by a legendary magician, looking for a successor worthy of the mighty Trickerion Stone, which is fabled to grant supernatural power to its owner.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Using worker placement and simultaneous action selection mechanisms, the Illusionists and their teams of helpers &amp;mdash; the Engineer, the Assistant, the Manager, and a handful of Apprentices &amp;ndash; obtain blueprints and components for increasingly complex magic tricks, expand the team and set up performances by visiting the Downtown, Dark Alley, Market Row and Theater locations on the main game board depicting a late 19th century cityscape.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The tricks are stored and prepared on the Magician's own Workshop game board, while the performances themselves take place at the Theater in the form of a tile placement mini-game with lots of player interaction. The performances yield Fame points and Coins to their owners based on the tricks they consist of. Fame points have multiple uses, but they also serve as a win condition - After turn 7, when the last Performance card is revealed, the game ends and the illusionist with the most Fame points wins.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The game offers 48 different Tricks to be learned from the Optical, Spiritual, Mechanical and Escape categories, over 90 character abilities, and 40 Special Assignment cards that influence the actions taken at the various game locations. The base game can be expanded with two optional rule modules to add further strategic depth to the game.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The &amp;quot;Dark Alley&amp;quot; expansion included in the base game adds a new location to the game. It also comes with 48 new Special Assignment cards, a new tier of Tricks, and 27 Prophecy tokens that can alter certain game rules turn by turn, giving the game additional variety.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2015" />
						               				<minplayers value="2" />
						               				<maxplayers value="4" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="133">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="59" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="17" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="76" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="14" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="38" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="61" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="3" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="76" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="28" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="10" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="54" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="180" />
						               				<minplaytime value="60" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="180" />
						               				<minage value="14" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="33">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="4" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="22" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="6" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="21">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="5" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="16" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="2710" value="Post-Napoleonic" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2001" value="Action Points" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2689" value="Action Queue" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2887" value="Catch the Leader" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2072" value="Dice Rolling" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2020" value="Simultaneous Action Selection" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2002" value="Tile Placement" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2826" value="Turn Order: Stat-Based" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2082" value="Worker Placement" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2933" value="Worker Placement, Different Worker Types" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="65328" value="Components: Dice with Icons" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="73592" value="Components: Gems/Crystals" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="8374" value="Crowdfunding: Kickstarter" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="22135" value="Crowdfunding: Spieleschmiede" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="70948" value="Digital Implementations: Tabletopia" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="58069" value="Game: Trickerion" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="75455" value="Theme: Art style – Art Deco" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="290975" value="Trickerion: Collector's Upgrade Pack" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="244358" value="Trickerion: Dahlgaard's Academy" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="172659" value="Trickerion: Dahlgaard's Gifts" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="255743" value="Trickerion: Dawn of Technology" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameexpansion" id="266238" value="Trickerion: The Secret Workshop" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecompilation" id="255668" value="Trickerion: Collector's Edition" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="76971" value="Richard Amann" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="76578" value="Viktor Peter" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="76972" value="Villő Farkas" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="85502" value="László Fejes" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="29156" value="Mindclash Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="1009" value="APE Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="31839" value="Corax Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="42325" value="Grok Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="30677" value="Maldito Games" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="29409" value="Super Meeple" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="8297" />
			<average value="7.95056" />
			<bayesaverage value="7.48377" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="113" bayesaverage="7.48377" />
																				<rank type="family" id="5497" name="strategygames" friendlyname="Strategy Game Rank" value="79" bayesaverage="7.58257" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.425" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="12574" />
			<trading value="173" />
			<wanting value="647" />
			<wishing value="3668" />
			<numcomments value="1564" />
			<numweights value="578" />
			<averageweight value="4.2232" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>