<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="18748">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/THnnB9SIT0gN5s8tp-Hy_g__thumb/img/2BJfdXsj-GvOiIfiA0d9ahs4NXM=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic407727.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/THnnB9SIT0gN5s8tp-Hy_g__original/img/wKwixgsVgHvhtjaNkpnida-4nfg=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic407727.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Unhappy King Charles!" />
				<rulebook>UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

1

© 2008 GMT Games, LLC
P.O. Box 1308, Hanford, CA 93232-1308, USA
www.GMTGames.com

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

v1.0 October 2008
#0814

2

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

CONTENTS
1.0

INTRODUCTION

3

10.0 BATTLES

18

Game Summary

3

2.0

GAME COMPONENTS

4

2.1
2.2

The Map
The Playing Pieces

4
5

3.0

GLOSSARY

5

4.0

SETTING UP THE GAME

6

4.1
4.2
4.3
4.4

Deck Assembly
Unit Set-Up
Political Control Markers
Remaining Setup

6
6
7
7

10.1
10.2
10.3
10.4
10.5
10.6
10.7
10.8

18
19
19
19
19
19
19
19

5.0

SEQUENCE OF PLAY

7

5.1
5.2
5.3
5.4
5.5
5.6
5.7
5.8
5.9

Housekeeping Phase
Political Control Phase
Recruitment Phase
Draw Strategy Cards Phase
Campaign Phase
Blockade Phase
Desertion and Supply Attrition Phase
Power Base Phase
Turn End Phase

7
7
7
7
7
8
8
8
8

6.0

STRATEGY CARDS

8

6.1
6.2
6.3
6.4
6.5
6.6
6.7
6.8

Operations Strategy Cards
Major Armies
Card procedure
Event Strategy Cards
Mandatory Event Strategy Cards
Individual Special Event Cards
Adding to the Original Draw Deck
Adding to the Second Draw Deck

8
9
9
9
10
11
12
13

7.0

RECRUITMENT

7.1
7.2
7.3

Evasion and Dispersal
Resolving Battles
Retreat
Surrender
Spoils of Victory
Turncoats
Major and Decisive Victories
Nesting

11.0 POLITICAL CONTROL

20

11.1 Placing PC Markers in the Campaign Phase
11.2 The Political Control Phase
11.3 Political Isolation

20
20
20

12.0 DESERTION & THE HORRORS OF WAR

20

12.1
12.2
12.3
12.4

20
20
21
21

Desertion Limitation
Desertion Selection Process
Supply Attrition
Desertion Example

13.0 LOCAL NOTABLES

21

14.0 FORTRESSES

22

14.1
14.2
14.3
14.4
14.5
14.6

22
22
23
23
23
24

Occupying Fortresses
Besieging
Bombardment
Siege Surrender
Assaults and Immediate Assaults
Battles in Siege Areas

15.0 NAVAL RULES

24

15.1 Diplomatic Strength
15.2 The Queen
15.3 Effects

24
24
24

13

16.0 FOG OF WAR

25

Common Recruitment Rules
The Recruitment Phase
Recruitment Cards

13
14
14

17.0 WINNING THE GAME

25

8.0

GENERALS

15

17.1 Automatic Victory
17.2 Power Base Victory
17.3 Winning at the End of the Game

25
25
25

8.1
8.2
8.3
8.4

Bringing Generals Into Play
Lone Generals
Leaving, Transferring & Picking Up Brigades
Army Size Limits

15
15
15
15

18.0 OPTIONAL RULES

26

9.0

MOVEMENT AND INTERCEPTION

15

9.1
9.2
9.3
9.4
9.5
9.6
9.7

Operations Strategy Cards
Movement Procedures
Movement Lines
Battle and Movement
Subordinate Armies
Changing PC Marker Control
Interception

15
15
16
16
16
17
17

18.1
18.2
18.3
18.4
18.5

26
26
26
26
26

Stout Cornish Men
Random Desertion Order
Manchester
The Laughter of the Court
Lostwithiel

CREDITS

26

Bibliography

26

INDEX

26

SEQUENCE OF PLAY

28

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

1.0

INTRODUCTION

In the autumn of 1642 the long foreshadowed clash between
Parliament and the supporters of the Royal Prerogative
was brought to a head. At Nottingham before a generally
uninterested audience the King raised the Royal Standard
indicating all who took the field against him were traitors and
rebels. Parliament sought to defeat the King militarily (or
rather the King’s evil counselors for they believed themselves
His Majesty’s most faithful servants) so as to overturn the
Royal Prerogative in matters of tax and defense. In so doing
Parliament had the support of by far the majority of the
aristocracy, the merchant class and the anti-papists. The
King’s aim was to defeat Parliament and establish his control
of funding so as to permit the full flowering of what he
conceived as his divinely sanctioned powers. Into this heady
brew came Papists (seeking freedom of religion), Protestant
sectaries, rebellious Irish nobles, Scots Presbyterians (fresh
from victory over England in the Bishops Wars) and many
other parties. Fortunately for England the great nations of
Europe were otherwise engaged.
Unhappy King Charles! allows two players to decide whether
Commons or Cavalier shall rule in England. Both seek
to establish control over the country and of its economic
structures. They seek not only to defeat their opponents in
battle but also to seize control of the local government of
England and Wales.
NB: In these rules any comments or explanations given in
italics do not form part of the rules themselves. Any references
to other rules are given with the numbered rule in parenthesis
(e.g. 7.0).

Game Summary
New players please read the Play Book first
Unhappy King Charles! is played over eleven turns, each
representing about four months. Brigades of troops combine
to form Armies (as defined in 3.0) or garrisons of Fortresses
(see 14.0). Only unled Brigades are on the map; the others
are placed on the box of their General on the Command
Displays. General counters move on the maps.
Movement and other activities require Activation using an
Operations Strategy Card (6.0); each Operations Card bears
a number showing that card’s Operations Points value. The
value of the Operations card must be greater than or equal
to the General’s Strategy Rating (2.2). Armies of five or more
Brigades must use a 3 value Operations Card (6.2). Campaign
Cards can be used to Activate multiple Generals with Armies
of any size. The other cards are Event Strategy Cards, and
these cards permit the player to do a number of things—take
control of Areas, transfer Brigades, receive new cards, etc.
(6.4)—that reflect actual events. The event described on each
Event Card may usually be played by either the Royalist or the
Parliament player (the card graphics make the distinction),
although some cards may be played by either player. If a
player holds a card with an Event that does not pertain to
him, he may discard it for minor activities (6.4).

3

The Cards are drawn each turn. There are six decks of cards;
three are turn-based in their introduction.
(1) Alt-Hist cards
(2) Core Cards (Both players receive two Core Cards each
turn, guaranteeing a minimum level of activity)
(3) Early War cards
(4) Mid-War cards
(5) Late War cards
(6) Mandatory cards
You can store one or more cards in certain circumstances to
constitute a reserve (5.5).
Each player must make at least six card plays per turn if he has
that many cards available. See rule 5.5 for details. Usually, the
Royalist player plays first for the opening turns of the game
and the Parliament player plays first in the later turns. See 5.5
for this as well.
Each Mandatory card must be played for its Event during the
Turn in which it is drawn (6.5). The war does not actually
begin until the “Raising the Royal Standard” Mandatory card
is played, though limited activity can occur before this.
Leader counters (8.0) are either Generals (with a Strategy and
Battle Rating) or Local Notables (governors of Fortresses).
Generals can be Field Generals who operate everywhere,
or Regional Generals who can suffer disadvantages when
outside their Region. Generals cannot transfer Brigades to
other Generals unless Event Cards permit; Brigades remain
with their original General until elimination, Dispersal or
Desertion takes them. Local Notables can transfer Brigades
to friendly Generals.
Brigades come in two types: Veterans (Combat Value 2)
and Militia (Combat Value 1). Usually, Militia units must
be Recruited before Veterans of that Region. Each Region’s
Areas and Brigades share the same color. Recruitment is
usually limited to the Region of origin. Brigades lost in
combat are not available for Recruitment (though some
Event Cards can bring them back).
Control of the map is an important part of the game, with
Political Control (PC) markers placed on Areas to denote
control of that Area. Each Area is either neutral (no PC
marker) or controlled (checkered Royalist PC marker or
orange Parliament PC marker). These markers are placed:
• before the game begins,
• in the Housekeeping Phase of the game,
• by means of Event or Operations Cards,
• by placement of Local Notable markers,
• by conversion as Armies move across the map,
• by winning Battles, or
• by occupation in the Political Control Phase.
Fortress Areas can be converted only by Event Cards and by
Surrender resulting from Sieges.
You can lose the game by not having enough Areas under
control (17.2). Control of Areas can be lost if they are Isolated
(11.3).

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

4

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

Fresh Brigades are received by Recruitment (7.0). In the
Recruitment Phase a number of Brigades are received based
on historical levels (subject to availability) at Recruitment
Areas or with Local Notables. Control of these Areas is
vital. Only units from the correct Region can be Recruited
in a Recruitment Area (7.2). Additionally, the use of one
Operations Card or one Discarded Event Card per turn
permits extra Recruitment (7.3). Royalist Recruitment outside
the Recruitment phase is limited to Regional Generals only,
though with the bonus that the Brigades can be Recruited
straight into the General’s Army rather than at a Recruitment
Area (7.3.1). Some Event Cards also raise Brigades (6.4). The
number of Brigades Recruited each turn reduces during the
War. Some of the Brigades which Disperse rather than fight
can return during Recruitment (7.1.7).
Armies are usually limited to four Brigades except for a
few Generals who can command up to nine Brigades (8.4).
Armies can be Subordinated to other Armies (i.e., the Armies
combine into one larger Army) if the commanding General
has a higher Subordinating Level (9.5). Armies with Generals
of the same Level cannot combine. When Armies combine,
Brigades still remain with their original General.
Movement is based on Army size. The smaller the Army the
faster it can move (9.2). Movement across the map is by means
of Areas joined by movement lines. There are three kinds of
movement lines (9.3). Control of Areas can change during
movement if Movement Points are spent (9.6). Non-moving
Armies can attempt Interception (9.7), placing themselves in
the path of the moving Army to cause Battle.
Battles are resolved using the Combat Value of the Brigades,
the General’s Battle Ratings, and (when played) Combat
Cards. But before any Battle is fought one side can try to
Evade (leave the Area) or Disperse (remove itself before
combat)—see 10.1. Losses in combat are not available
for Recruitment, although certain cards allow them to be
brought back into the game. Drawn and Decisive Victories
kill Veteran Brigades (if there are any) first. The loser must
Retreat and can suffer further losses if he Retreats through
enemy PC markers. Major and Decisive Victories earn extra
Strategy Cards.
Each turn Desertion occurs based on a pre-determined level
that causes Armies to reduce in strength over the game.
Desertion is performed according to criteria that ensure that
losses usually occur in the largest armies which are nearest
to the enemy (12.0). Armies of 5 or more Brigades will also
suffer Supply Attrition losses.
Fortresses cover a wide range of locations. They are ranked by
class and their ability to withstand Bombardment. Surrender
occurs by Siege or Event Card. Siege requires the attention
of an Army for some time (most Fortresses will require more
than one Activation to capture). If attacked during that time
the Besieger can be forced to abandon the Siege (14.6).
Assaults (14.5) can be attempted (at a cost in losses).
Naval rules use the draw of a chit once a year to determine the
aggregate degree of naval support for each side (15.0). Naval
status can affect Sieges and Recruiting.
The game can be won by an Automatic Victory, by one side
failing to control enough Areas, or at the end of the eleventh
turn (17.0).

2.0

GAME COMPONENTS

Unhappy King Charles! is comprised of:
One map
One sheet of 5/8” counters
One sheet of 1/2” counters
Two 8.5” x 11” Player Reference Cards
One Rules Book
One Playbook
110 Strategy Cards

2.1

The Map

The game map consists of Areas that are connected to one
another by lines. Areas are:
• Circular: Standard Area
• Diamond-shaped: Local Notable Set-up Area
• Pentagonal: Limited Fortress
• Hexagonal: Supply Fortress

All Areas have their border in the color of their Region. The
regions are also separated by a dotted border line.
An Area that is also a Port has an anchor symbol
(for example London). Ports are used only for some
Events and affect Bombardment (never for regular
movement).
Areas with a pink wash under them are Economic
Infrastructures—see the Victory rules.
The connecting lines between Areas can be Road (solid
green line), Mountain (double brown line), or Maritime
(dotted blue line) (see Movement, below). Two Areas that are
connected by a line are considered adjacent to each other.

Some Areas are printed with a blue fill and an icon of a
Royalist PC marker; others have an orange fill and an icon
of a Parliament PC marker—these graphical indicators show
Areas of initial support to aid in setting up the game. Political
Control Markers in the relevant color are placed on these
Areas.
Recruitment Areas have a drummer icon in the
Region color, and a flag denoting which side may
use that Area for Recruitment. A Recruitment Area
can be outside its own Region.
Example: London is a Recruitment Area for Parliament South
and East, and Shrewsbury a Royalist Recruitment Area for Wales
(even though not in Wales).
Fortress Areas have two numbers, firstly the Fortress Class,
secondly the Surrender Value.
Example: London is listed as 3/11, a Class 3 Fortress requiring a
Bombardment Value of 11 to Surrender.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

2.2

The Playing Pieces

BRIGADES
Each combat unit (which has an illustration of soldiers
printed on it) represents about 3,000 men (ration strength).
Some Brigades are portrayed as Cavalry and some as Infantry,
but this has no effect on combat. Each Brigade is worth the
Combat Value printed on it (one or two), and its name will be
printed in the color of a Region. The names of the Brigades
are mostly for historical ambiance, although some Brigades
are named specifically in the rules.

Each unit has a number and a letter. The number is its
Combat Value. The letter is its Region of Recruitment, also
indicated by text color matching the border color of all Areas
in that Region:
S = South (blue)

The factors on General counters are the Strategy Rating on
the left and the Battle Rating on the Right. A 2/3* General
has a Strategy Rating of 2 for Activation (6.1) and 3 for all
other purposes (for example Evasion and Interception).
Historical Note: As administrators these Generals were no worse
than other Generals, but less swift in maneuver.
POLITICAL CONTROL MARKERS
Control of an Area is marked with Political Control Markers—
abbreviated in these rules to “PC markers”.

OTHER MARKERS
Other markers are used to indicate various game statuses,
such as the current turn, the naval status, major armies and
other game conditions.

3.0

E = East (green)
W = Wales (orange)

5

GLOSSARY

N = North (red)

Any capitalized terms in the rules have a specific meaning.
The following terms are used in the game.

M = Midlands (purple)

1d6: One six-sided die. (2d6 refers to two six-sided dice.)

The color band indicates the unit’s affiliation:
Green band (and Cross of St Andrew) is Covenanter,
Purple band is Lorrainer,
Orange band is Parliament and
Blue band is Royalist.
A counter with a little St George’s flag is a Royalist unit from
the army in Ireland (henceforth “Irish”).
GENERALS
Generals come in two varieties: Field Generals and Regional
Generals. Local Notables have some limited command
abilities but are not Generals (13.0).

Army: An Army consists of a General (8.0), and one or
more friendly Brigades (which are placed on his Command
Display). An Army can also include Subordinate Generals and
the Brigades on the Command Display of the Subordinate
General (9.5). Brigades without a General, or Brigades with
only a Local Notable, are never an Army. References to
Brigades in the rules include Brigades in Armies.
Assault: After Bombardment, a Besieging Army can attempt
to force a Fortress to Surrender by launching an Assault
(14.5). An Assault is permitted only where a Bombardment
value of 5 or more has been amassed. Local Notables can
never be subject to an Assault.
Bombardment: Besieging Armies may Bombard Fortresses to
attempt to force them to Surrender (14.3). The Surrender
Value of a Fortress is the number of Bombardment Points the
Besieging army must accrue in order to force the Surrender.
Combat Cards: Cards bearing the notation “Combat Card” are
used in order to affect the Battle in which they are played.

•

Command Display: The player reference cards have Command
Displays printed on them. These Displays have boxes for each
General or Local Notable in the game. All Brigades on a
General’s Command Display and on the Command Displays
of any Subordinates are “under command” of the General on
the map.

Field Generals have their factors in black.
Example: Prince Rupert is a Field General.

•

Regional Generals have their name in
white on a background printed in their
Region Color and their Region or Regions’
identifying letter(s) next to the portrait.
Example: Newcastle is a Regional General from the North. Waller
is a Regional General in both the South and the Midlands.

•

Local Notables have no factors. Their name
is printed in their Region color on a white
background and their Region identifying
letter is next to the portrait.

Core Cards: The two Operations Strategy Cards (worth 1
Operation and 2 Operations respectively) available to each
player every turn. When played, the Core Cards remain away
from the Discard pile so that they can be easily returned
to the players’ hands during the next Draw Strategy Cards
Phase. Core Cards may not be retained as Ace-in-the-Hole
cards (see 6.0).

Example: Massey is a Local Notable.
© GMT Games LLC, 2008

6

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

Event Strategy Card: An Event Strategy Card (often abbreviated
to “Event Card”) is a Card that is NOT an Operations Card
(see above). It is a Strategy Card that represents a historical
(or counterfactual) event that can be triggered by a player
playing the card during a Campaign Round.

4.0

Friendly Area: An Area is friendly if it is marked with a
friendly PC marker.

At the start of play, do the following:

Immediate Assault: An Immediate Assault is a variant of
Assault that does not require an Army to Bombard a Fortress
(14.5). Only certain Generals can Immediate Assault.

4.1
1.

SETTING UP THE
GAME
Deck Assembly

Divide the Strategy cards into the following decks:
a. The four Core Cards.
b. The “Early War” Cards,

Militia Brigade: Any Brigade with a Combat Value of 1. Usually,
all Militia Brigades belonging to a specific Region must be
Recruited before any Veteran Brigades of that Region.

c. The three “Mandatory” Cards,

Operations Strategy Card: An Operations Strategy Card
(often abbreviated to “Operations Card” or “Ops Card”) is a
Strategy Card that has 1, 2 or 3 Operations marked as its title
OR is a Minor or Major Campaign Card.

f. The “Alt-Hist” Cards.
2.

Put decks (d), (e), and (f) aside for later.

3.

Political Control: A player has political control of an Area
when one of his PC markers is in that Area. The presence of
enemy Armies or Brigades in an Area does not immediately
affect Political Control.

Give the two Royalist Core Cards to the Royalist player
and the two Parliament Core Cards to the Parliament
player.

4.

Locate the “Raising of The Standard” Mandatory Card
and place the other two Mandatory Cards aside for later.

5.

Shuffle the “Early War” Cards and draw the top nine
cards, add the “Raising of The Standard” Mandatory
Card to these nine cards and shuffle again, deal five
cards to each player. The remainder of the Early War
cards comprise the Draw Deck.

Response Cards: Cards bearing the notation “Response”—
these are played during the other player’s Activation
(although one of them, Turnham Green, may be played
instead as a standard Event Strategy Card).
Region: Each Area on the map is in one of five Regions
(North, Midlands, East, South and Wales) each of which has
a distinctive color (respectively Red, Purple, Green, Blue and
Orange). The color of an Area’s border shows the Region to
which it belongs.
Siege: Brigades and Armies inside Fortresses cannot be forced
into Battle. However, enemy Armies may Besiege them, either
Assaulting or Bombarding them into Surrender (14.0).
Strategy Card: Generic name for both Operations Strategy
Card and Event Strategy Card.
Subordinates: Armies that have been taken under command
by another General (9.5). The Subordinate General’s counter
is placed on the Command Display of the commanding
General to show Subordination. Subordinates act as part of
the Army of the commanding General (though no transfers
of Brigades between Command Displays can occur) until
such time as their Subordinated General Activates separately
and leaves or the Subordinate is left behind. Subordinates
cannot undertake any activity other than Activating to move
out of the Army to which they are Subordinated.
Veteran Brigade: Any Brigade with a Combat Value of 2. In
both Drawn Battles and Decisive Victories, Veteran Brigades
(if involved in the Battle) are lost before Militia Brigades.

d. The “Mid War” Cards,
e. The “Late War” Cards, and

4.2

Unit Set-Up

Set up the units as listed below. Set-up is in the format:
Area Name, Area Region, General (if any), Brigade name
(Region letter and strength in brackets) or name of Local
Notable.
Units with a General are placed in his Command Display box
on the Player Reference Card, not on the map.
PARLIAMENT SET UP
Wakefield (North): Lord Fairfax [Cloth Towns’ Militias
(N1)]
London (East): Essex [Eastern Association (E1), Eastern
Association (E1), Fiennes (M1) and Assheton (M1)]
London (East): London Trained Bands (E1) inside London
(place under the PC marker)
Exeter (South): Bedford [Hesilrigg’s Lobsters (S1) and
Pophams’s (S1)]
Portsmouth (South): Waller [Western Association (S1)]
Gloucester (Midlands): Massey Local Notable*
Macclesfield (Midlands): Brereton Local Notable*
Peterborough (East): Willoughby Local Notable
Parliament Reinforcements Box: Empty
* Be sure to use the Local Notable counters for Massey and
Brereton, not the Regional General counters.
ROYALIST SET UP
York (North): King Charles [King’s Lifeguard (M2) and
Rupert’s Lifeguard (S2)]

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!
Newcastle (North): Newcastle [Whitecoats (N2)]

7

placement. If there is no available Area for a player, the
player skips his placement.

Historical Note: William Cavendish held several titles during his
lifetime. He was created Earl of Newcastle in 1628, Marquis of
Newcastle in 1643 and Duke of Newcastle in 1665.

Designer’s Note: The placement of a PC marker here represents
the action of local committees spreading each faction’s influence
far away from the armies.

St Austell (South): Hopton [Grenvile’s Cornish (S2)]

Preston (Midlands): Earl of Derby Local Notable

Then, if this is Late 1642 (i.e., Game Turn 1), Late 1643,
Late 1644 or Late 1645, the Parliament Player draws a
Naval Chit and adjusts the Naval Status (stack the Naval
Chits with the Naval Status Marker on the Naval Status
Chart). See 15.0 for more details on Naval Status.

Royalist Reinforcements Box: Byron, Prince Rupert and
Prince Maurice

Play Note: The turns where a naval chit is drawn are marked
with an anchor on the turn chart.

Shrewsbury (Midlands): [Lord Herbert’s (W1), Wilmot’s
(M1) and Northern Levies (W1)]

3.

Cardiff (Wales): Lord Herbert Local Notable

To help with set-up, the General, Brigade, and Local Notable
counters have their starting Areas or Command Display box
setup locations printed on the reverse. Generals placed on
the Turn Record Track (see 4.4) have the turn of their arrival
printed on the reverse.

5.2

Political Control Phase

(There is no Political Control Phase on the first Turn.)
In the Political Control Phase:
1.

Place the correct PC marker in each Area marked with a
PC marker icon on the map (for example, Oxford for the
Royalists and London for the Parliamentarians). Each such
Area is also printed with the appropriate color fill.

Both players place PC markers in all non-Fortress Areas
that are occupied by one of their Armies or Local
Notables (11.2), if one of their PC markers is not already
there, and

2.

The players remove markers to reflect Political Isolation
(11.3).

4.4

5.3

4.3

Political Control Markers

Remaining Setup

1.

Place the five naval status markers in an opaque
container.

2.

Place the Game Turn Marker on Turn 1 of the Turn
Record Track.

3.

Place Generals named on the Turn Record Track in the
correct space, ready for arrival.

4.

Place all other unused Generals in their boxes on the
Command Display.

5.

Sort your Brigades by Region, placing 2 Value Brigades
(Veterans) at the bottom of each stack as a reminder that
all 1 Value Brigades (Militia) must usually be Recruited if
available (7.4).

5.0

SEQUENCE OF PLAY

Unhappy King Charles! is played in Game Turns, each of which
covers four historical months. Each turn is played in the
following phases in the order given below.

5.1

Housekeeping Phase

In the Housekeeping Phase:
1.

2.

Recruitment Phase

Beginning with the Parliament player, each side places
Recruited Brigades (7.0) and, if desired, Blockade & Siege
Markers (14.2).

5.4

Draw Strategy Cards Phase

(There is no Draw Strategy Cards Phase on the first Turn.)
This phase creates each player’s “hand” of cards for use in
the Campaign Phase of this Game Turn. First, each player
recovers his two Core Cards. The Parliament player then
deals four Strategy Cards from the Draw Deck to each player
one at a time, starting with the Royalist player. Each player’s
hand for the Game Turn will therefore consist of at least six
cards: four from the Draw Deck and the two Core Cards. “Ace
in the Hole” cards (5.5 and 6.2) are also part of the player’s
arsenal.
If there are insufficient cards to deal four to each player,
deal both players the same number of cards, with the
Royalist player getting the last card in case of an odd number
remaining. Instructions for adding further cards are at 6.7
and 6.8.
Play Note: Running out of cards in the deck is rare, and occurs
when there are an exceptional number of major/decisive Battles.
Note, however, that adding the Late War cards (6.8) occurs only
when all the Early and Mid War cards have been drawn.

Each player transfers all of his Generals from the
Unemployed Generals Box to the Reinforcements Box.
Any Generals on the Turn Record Track for the current
turn are moved into the Reinforcements Box as well.

5.5

Then each Player must place a PC marker in one neutral
Area (Parliament player first). The Area must be adjacent
to a friendly PC marker, but not adjacent to an enemy PC
marker, Local Notable or Army, and its change of control
must not be such as will cause Political Isolation (11.3)
for any other PC markers. Unled Brigades do not prevent

The players alternately play or discard Strategy Cards one at
a time until both players have passed. A player can pass at
any time after they have played (including discarding) six
cards—combat cards and other response cards are included
in this total. They are forced to pass only when they have no
cards remaining.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

Campaign Phase

8

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

EXCEPTIONS
• Forced removals of cards do not count toward the six
card plays required except for Mandatory Cards.
•

The play of cards arising from victories does not count
toward the six card plays required.

•

If one player passes the other player can continue playing
and discarding until they also pass. Once a player has
passed, they cannot play or discard another card in that
Phase. A player who holds a Mandatory Strategy Card
(6.5) cannot pass until it is played. If a player runs out of
cards before playing six (due to Events), he simply passes
once his hand is empty.
Play Note: If you find it hard to track how many cards you have
played, keep them face up in front of you until the end of the
turn and then place them in the discard pile. However, if the
Parliament player is allowed a draw from the discard pile (10.7),
make sure to add all the cards to it.

GOING FIRST
The Royalist Player chooses who plays the first card in a turn
until the New Model Army Event (6.5) has been played. At
that point the choice passes to the Parliament Player.

•

The game ends automatically in the Turn End Phase of
the winter 1645 Turn. Victory Points are then counted
according to 17.3 and a winner is declared.

6.0

STRATEGY CARDS

In Unhappy King Charles! the two players move, fight, Bombard
Fortresses, place PC markers, Recruit Brigades and cause
events to occur all by playing Strategy Cards. Each turn each
Player is dealt four Strategy cards from the top of the Draw
Deck; the Parliament player deals them out one at a time,
with the top card going to the Royalist player, the second to
the Parliament player, and so on. A further two Core Cards
are available to each player each turn. There are two types of
Strategy Cards:
•

Operations Strategy Cards (including Campaign Strategy
Cards) and,

•

Event Strategy Cards.

Exception: Where the player selected to go second does
not wish to do so, they can insist on going first if they have
a “Major Campaign” or “Minor Campaign” card, which must
then be their first card play.
ACE IN THE HOLE
All unplayed cards at the end of a Campaign Phase are placed
aside (face down) and can be played in later turns (see 6.0).
These are known as “Ace in the Hole” cards.

5.6

Blockade Phase

Armies with a “Blockade & Siege” marker (not just a Siege
marker) can now Bombard the Fortress on which the Marker
is placed (no Operations Card is required). See 14.2 and 14.3
for details.

5.7

Desertion and Supply
Attrition Phase

Check the Game- Turn track and inflict the number of
Desertions required (12.0). Then remove Brigades that are
subject to Supply Attrition (12.3). Deserting Brigades and
those lost to Supply Attrition are available for Recruitment
next Game Turn.

5.8

Power Base Phase

Check for victory (17.0).

5.9

Operations Card (left) and Event Card (right)
Some Event Strategy Cards can cause Strategy Cards to be lost
(both players are permitted to see them) or extra Strategy
Cards to be drawn from the Draw Deck (only the Owner sees
these).
ACE IN THE HOLE
Each player starts the game with seven cards but only six plays
a turn are required. Remaining cards can be stored for later.
These stored cards are considered part of the player’s hand
and can be played normally, except that they are kept facedown beside the map in plain view until played, and they may
not be removed by the opponent’s play of an Event Card. You
cannot put Core Cards or Combat Cards in the store. The
stored cards can never be used in the Winter 1645 turn.
Play Note: “Ace in the Hole” cards are kept outside of the normal
hand so the opponent can confirm that no illegal cards were kept.
In addition, it serves as a reminder that these cards are immune
to removal.

6.1

Tu r n E n d P h a s e

If the game has not ended, recover the Core Cards for each
player (they are part of the players’ hands for the next turn),
place any Strategy Cards used for Recruits into the discard
pile, and advance the Turn Marker one box on the Turn
Record Track. There are three ways in which the game can
end:
•

The game ends immediately if either player achieves an
Automatic Victory during the Power Base Phase.

•

The game ends immediately if King Charles Surrenders
as the result of a Siege (8.2 and 14.4) or a Battle (10.4)

Operations Strategy Cards

An Operations Strategy Card allows a player to undertake one
of the following things:
1.

Bring Recruits into play (7.0). The procedures used by
the Royalist and Parliament players are different. Only
one such card can be played each Turn by each player.

2.

Bombard a Fortress (14.2) in the same Area as a friendly
General with an Army having sufficient Brigades for
Besieging that Fortress AND whose Strategy Rating is less
than or equal to the number printed on the Operations
Strategy Card (but see Major Armies below).

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!
3.

Activate for Raiding a number of Local Notables equal
to the number printed on the Operations Strategy Card
(13.0).

4.

Activate for movement (9.0) a General whose Strategy
Rating is less than or equal to the number printed
on the Operations Strategy Card (but see 6.2 below).
This General can be brought onto the map from the
Reinforcements Box (8.1):
a.

A “1” Operations Strategy Card can only Activate
a General with a Strategy Rating of 1.

b.

A “2” Operations Strategy Card can Activate a
General with a Strategy Rating of 1 or 2, or a
“(2/3*)” leader.

c.

A “3” card can Activate any General, and is
required to Activate a Major Army (6.2).

5.

Perform multiple instances of items 2-4 above by playing
a Minor or Major Campaign Card (see immediately
below this list for details).

6.

Place a number of PC markers on the map equal to the
value of the card (11.1).

MINOR AND MAJOR CAMPAIGN CARDS
Campaign cards allow the number of Generals specified
on the card—irrespective of Strategy Rating—to move or
Bombard. For any or all of the Activations allowed by the
card, a Local Notable may be Activated in place of a General
(13.0). Generals move and fight one at a time—there is no
simultaneous or coordinated movement.

9

of the Subordinates and moving them away, leaving less than
five Brigades with the former Major Army. The five-Brigade
restriction applies to the Army Activating and includes any
Brigades or Subordinates to be picked up while Activated
(if Activated with anything less than a 3 Operations Card, a
General may not pick up Brigades that would raise its total
to 5 or higher during that Activation). Place a Major Army
counter to indicate these stacks. Only the Generals noted in
rule 8.4 may command Major Armies; all other Generals are
restricted to four Brigades. Brigades in Subordinated Armies
do count when determining Major Army status.

6.3

Card procedure

When a Strategy Card of either kind is played or discarded,
read its text and then place it on the discard pile. Core Cards
once played are not discarded but instead placed to the side
to be recovered next turn. When an Operations Strategy
Card is used to bring Recruits into the game, it is instead
placed face-up in the appropriate Royalist or Parliament
Recruitment Card Box. The latter cards are cleared at the end
of each turn to the discard pile.

6.4

Event Strategy Cards

The play of an Event Strategy Card causes a specific event
to occur. Each of the Event Strategy Cards has instructions
that state the specific effect. These must be followed exactly
(conditioned by the following paragraphs). Where a player
receives a card that does not benefit him—the cards are
graphically coded to denote which player benefits—and is
not one of the three Mandatory Event Strategy Cards (6.5)
then he can discard it (placing it face-up in the discard
pile)—and note that discards may be used for specific actions
(see “Discarded Event Strategy Cards below).
Designer’s Note: A discarded event will still have occurred, but it
clearly had less effect than it did historically.

Minor and Major Campaign Cards
Note that the same Brigades can never be moved by more
than one General by a single card play, and each General can
only be Activated once per card. Campaign cards also allow
the player not scheduled to go first that turn to become the
first player instead (5.5).
Play Note: A player can Activate any mix of Armies and Local
Notables, in any combination or order, and can mix Bombardment
and Movement Activations freely. If Bombardment is chosen the
stack must still meet the conditions of Bombardment.

6.2

Major Armies

Armies of five or more Brigades require a
3 Operations Card or a Campaign Card to
Activate them for movement or Bombardment
irrespective of the General’s Strategy Ratings. A
Major Army can be broken up during Activation
in two ways and only if it has Subordinates: firstly, by Activating
the Army with a 3 Operations Card or Campaign Card but
leaving behind sufficient Subordinates to drop the Army
below five Brigades (9.5). Secondly, by Activating one or more

RESPONSE CARDS
Two Event Strategy cards bear the label “Response Card”.
Response Cards are played during the other player’s
Activation, halting that Activation until the event on the card
is enacted, after which the Activating player continues. One
of the Response Cards—Turnham Green (see 6.6)—may be
played either as a normal Event Card or as a Response Card.
PLACING OF PC MARKERS
Where an Event Strategy Card calls for PC markers to be
placed, the player can place his own markers anywhere and,
unless the card states that the PC markers must be placed
in “Open Areas”, can replace enemy PCs with his own (11.1
but see the next paragraph). A card specifying “Open Areas”
means Areas that do not currently have PC markers.
REMOVAL OF PC MARKERS
An enemy PC marker cannot be removed from a Fortress
Area unless specifically noted on the card (or in the rules), or
from an Area occupied by an enemy Army, Brigade or Local
Notable.
PLACING BRIGADES
All Brigades placed as instructed by an Event Card must
be from the Region in which they are placed. As with
Recruitment, Militia must be placed if available (7.4), unless

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

10

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

the card specifies Veteran Brigades. If no qualifying Brigades
are available, those permanently lost in combat (10.2) can
be used. If none of these are available, the shortfall is lost.
Brigades must be placed with any friendly Army, Local
Notable or PC marker, but not with a garrison under Siege. If
there is no such legal placement, the Brigades are lost. This is
different from the normal Recruitment process.
REMOVAL OF BRIGADES
Where an Event Strategy Card calls for the removal of Brigades
from the map the Player suffering the loss chooses these at
his own discretion from Brigades in the specified Region.
Unless otherwise indicated the losses are not permanent and
Brigades are available for Recruitment immediately.
REMOVAL OF STRATEGY CARDS
Where an event calls for one or more Strategy Cards to be
removed from a player’s hand, the player who played the
event randomly chooses which cards are removed. Any cards
stored from a previous turn are immune from removal.
Any card that is removed from a player’s hand in this way is
discarded after being examined by both players. Exception:
If a Mandatory Event Strategy Card is drawn it must be
immediately played (see below), and is considered to have
been played by the player from whose hand it was drawn.
DISCARDING EVENT STRATEGY CARDS
Players can discard any Strategy Card (other than a
Mandatory Event Strategy Card). A discarded Event Card can
be used as a Limited 1 Operations Card: it may not be used to
Activate Field Generals or Regional Generals for movement
or Bombardment, but it may be used to place a PC marker,
Activate one Raiding Local Notable or for Recruitment, just
as for other Operations Cards).
COMBAT CARDS
Combat cards must be played or discarded on the turn they
are drawn. They may never be saved as an “Ace in the Hole”.
As with all other events, however, a discarded Combat Card
can be used as a Limited 1 Operations Card (see paragraph
above). Note that a Combat Card, even if played for the
purpose of Battle, does count as one of the player’s six played
cards in that turn.

of the play of an Event Card, the Mandatory Event takes place
immediately, and is considered to have been played by the
player from whose hand it was removed.
Once a Mandatory Event Strategy Card is played it is removed
from the game permanently, put aside and not shuffled into
the pack.
There are three Mandatory Event Strategy Cards, with effects
as follows:
RAISING OF THE STANDARD
Before this card is played Armies cannot enter Areas
containing enemy Brigades, Intercept enemy Armies or
attempt to Bombard or Assault enemy Fortresses.
Both sides can place PC markers, move, play Event Cards
(these cards are not limited even if the Royal Standard has
not been played, so they can take enemy PC markers) and
Recruit. Local Notables can Raid. Neither side can remove
enemy PC markers during movement. Sir William Waller
cannot move. Once the card is played, all these restrictions
are lifted.
Play Note: Waller is besieging Portsmouth at game start. There
is no need for a Siege marker, since it is already marked for
Parliament (it falls when the Standard is played).
If the Parliament Player plays this card or it is played by being
removed from his hand by a Royalist Event Card, treat it as
also being an additional Parliament Recruitment; he may
place one Brigade in a location permitted in the Recruitment
Phase.
ARMY OF THE SOLEMN LEAGUE AND COVENANT
The Parliament Player places the five Covenanter Brigades
in Leven’s Command Box and then (irrespective of who
played the card), immediately Activates Leven for movement
upon placement of these Brigades. Leven starts in Carlisle or
Berwick (choice of the Parliament Player). This placement is
considered normal movement (although the placement itself
costs no Movement Points), so it can trigger Interception
(9.7) or Battle. If Leven fights a Battle and loses or draws,
his Activation is over as normal and he is kept off the map.
He may attempt entry again on a later Activation in the same
way.
Additionally, in Late 1644 the Parliament Player can Activate
Callander and two Covenanter Brigades (he places the
Brigades on Callander’s General Display). Callander starts
in Carlisle or Berwick upon Activation in the same way as
Leven. Both Callander and Leven may command Parliament
Brigades, but no Parliament General may command
Covenanter Brigades or Subordinate Covenanter Generals.

6.5

Mandatory Event Strategy
Cards

The player to whom Mandatory Event Strategy Cards are
dealt must play them in the Game Turn in which they are
dealt. They cannot be discarded or retained. This can mean
that the player might suffer a disadvantage by the playing—he
cannot avoid this. His only choice is when in the Turn the
Card is played. If the card is selected for removal as the result

Covenanter Armies may not Disperse, but they may move off
the game map (withdrawing into Scotland) by being at Carlisle
or Berwick and spending one further move. Once moved off
they do not return, and any cards mandating Covenanter
withdrawal or arrival is disregarded in that respect.
If this card is played by the Royalist Player or it is played
by being removed from his hand by a Parliament Event
Card, after the Parliament Player has completed Leven’s
Activation, the Royalist Player gets an immediate (additional)
Recruitment, as in the Recruitment Phase, with a value of 2
Brigades (but neither can be Northern Brigades).

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

11

NEW MODEL ARMY
When the New Model Army card is played the Parliament
Player follows this procedure:

(5) Now place the Poyntz General counter with any
Parliament stack (or keep him in the Reinforcements
Box).

(1) Remove the counters for Willoughby, Essex, Manchester,
Waller and Lord Fairfax from the map or the player cards
for the rest of the game and place their Brigades and any
Subordinate Armies in the Area the Generals occupied
before removal.

(6) Any Parliament Brigades left without a General as the
result of the New Model Army changes, or Brigades which
will otherwise cause a new Major Army (6.2) to exist, and
any Siege Train can be moved up to three Areas (but
never through or into Areas containing enemy Armies
or Brigades) at the choice of the Parliament player.
Parliament Generals may now pick up any Brigades (or
the Siege Train) that are in their Areas.

(2) Then remove from play for the rest of the game four
Parliament Brigades (these may bear any Region
designation). These must be Veteran (2 value) Brigades.
Where insufficient Veteran Brigades exist use Militia
Brigades to make up the number of Brigades (NOT
the Combat Value) removed. Where there are not four
Parliament Brigades on the map then remove such
Brigades as there are and then any un-recruited Veteran
Parliament Brigades to come to a total of four. If there are
not enough Brigades to come to four then any shortfall
need not be met.
Historical Note: These pieces are removed due to The SelfDenying Ordinance: “Be it ordained by the Lords and
Commons assembled in Parliament, that all and every of
the members of either House of Parliament shall be, and by
authority of this Ordinance are discharged at the end of forty
days after the passing of this Ordinance, of and from all and
every office or command military or civil, granted or conferred
by both or either of the said Houses of this present Parliament,
or by any authority derived from both or either of them since the
20th day of November, 1640.”
(3) Exchange Tom Fairfax’s Northern counter (whether it
is on or off the map) for his Lord General counter (see
next paragraph for how the Lord General comes onto
the map). Then exchange Massey’s and Brereton’s Local
Notable counters for their Regional General Markers if
these counters are still in play. If Lord Herbert is still in
play exchange his Local Notable counter for Gerard. If
any replaced Local Notable was under Siege, the new
General must immediately fight a Battle or Disperse
(order of Battles is selected by the Parliament player).
These Generals are not removed simply because they lack
Brigades until the end of the NMA procedure (unled
Brigades may be able to join them, see (6) below), nor
is the Siege Train removed simply because it is no longer
with a friendly Army.
(4) Now place Cromwell in London together with two
New Model Army Brigades on his Command Display.
If London is Besieged or Masked then place them in
another East Region Area with a Parliament PC marker.
If there is no such Area is available then place the stack
on any Area with a Parliament PC marker. The other
three New Model Army Brigades are placed on the Lord
General’s Command Display. If this gives him more
Brigades than he can command, the excess are lost. If the
Lord General is off the map immediately place him on
any Area with a Parliament PC marker in the East, South
or North Regions. If there is no such Area is available
then place the counter on any Area with a Parliament PC
marker.

(7) Any Subordinate Armies left by the removal of a General
that cannot stack must then be moved up to three Areas
(but never through or into Areas containing enemy
Armies or Brigades) at the choice of the Parliament
player. If they cannot do so, the Generals are removed
to the Unemployed Generals Box and the Brigades are
removed from the map.
(8) Remove any Generals left without Brigades.

6.6

Individual Special Event
Cards

The cards listed here contain special events. Once the event
specified by the card has occurred, the card is discarded
normally, but the event cannot happen again.
THE KING ABANDONS THE BISHOPS
Remove all Covenanter Brigades and
Generals from the map. Any Fortress
garrisoned only by Covenanters that
is under Siege Surrenders (otherwise
Parliament simply retains control) Any
Subordinate Armies left by the removal
of a General that cannot now stack must
then be moved up to three Areas (but
never through or into enemy Brigades) at
the choice of the Parliament player. If they
cannot do so, the Generals are removed to the Unemployed
Generals Box and the Brigades are removed from the map.
CHARLES OF LORRAINE
The Royalist Player places the Lorraine Brigades on Charles
of Lorraine’s box on the Command Display Card, and
place Charles of Lorraine at either Bristol or Newcastle.
His placement Area must be Royalist-controlled at that time
otherwise the card has no effect. While the Lorrainers are in
England the Royalists cannot use a Grandee Recruitment
Card (7.3.1). Charles of Lorraine may Subordinate other
Generals but may only have Lorrainer Brigades and Generals
on his own Command Display.
LONDON RISING
To check for a London Rising roll 1d6 and modify as follows:
•

less the number of Parliament controlled economic
infrastructures

•

less the number of Parliament Brigades in the Fortress of
London

•

plus the number of Royalist controlled economic
infrastructures.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

12

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

If the score is 5 or higher London is captured by a Royalist
coup. The Parliament Player can place Parliament Brigades
that were in London (if any) in an unoccupied Area adjacent
to London at his choice (if no such Area is available, Disperse
the Brigades). Any other score has no effect.
THE CESSATION
The “Irish” Brigades can be placed in any
Port Area in the Midlands or Wales that
does not have a Parliament PC marker. If
the Naval Score is negative, the landing
Area is expanded to include the South.
“Irish” Brigades may be commanded by
any Royalist General.
PRINCE RUPERT DISMISSED
Remove the Prince Rupert counter from play permanently.
He can be replaced by any available Royalist General in
the Unemployed Generals Box—the replacement General
is placed in that same Area, and Rupert’s Brigades are
transferred to the new General’s Display (whether or not
he can actually command that number of Brigades). If no
General is available Rupert’s Brigades are left uncommanded
in the Area he occupied prior to removal. If Rupert has
already been removed, this event does nothing.
QUEEN MARY
Queen Mary arrives in the game with the
“Henrietta Maria lands” Event Card. Place the
marker for “The Queen” in York or any Port
Area on the eastern coast of the Northern
Region. The Queen is not a General and cannot
be removed from the map until after Late 1644 (from any
Royalist controlled Port Area). The Queen can only travel
with a Royalist Army. If at any time the Queen is in a Fortress
which Surrenders or with an Army that Disperses or suffers a
defeat she is captured and removed. In the Late 1644 Turn
she cannot be moved. If the Queen appears in the game and
exits uncaptured then deduct 1 from Naval Status. If the
Queen appears in the game and is captured then add 2 to
Naval Status.

EARL OF BRENTFORD
After playing the card, the Royalist player takes
the Earl of Brentford marker and retains it (place
it on the Command Display of King Charles). In
any turn before Winter 1644 where Charles I
commands in a Battle, the Royalist player may
discard the marker to add 1 to his Battle Total after the dice
are rolled. This point cannot convert an Indecisive Victory
into a Major Victory.
SIR JOHN MELDRUM AT NEWARK
This card may be played against an unoccupied Class 1
Fortress even though no Besieging Army is in place.
TURNHAM GREEN
The Turnham Green event can be played either as a normal
Parliamentary Event Strategy Card or during a Royalist
Activation (interrupting play)—in either case, a Royalist army
must be in one of the six Areas directly connected to London.
If played during a Royalist Activation the Royalist army halts
temporarily until the Parliament player enacts the event.
The event allows the Parliament player to pick up any and
all Parliament Brigades and Generals within three Areas of
London and place them in the London Area—they cannot
be Intercepted, nor do enemy forces in their path stop this
movement. After this (if played as a Response card), the
Royalist Activation continues. Play of this card during the
Royalist Activation counts towards the six required card plays
in a turn, but Parliament plays the next card (if he has any)
in that turn.
Whenever Turnham Green is played the resulting stack in
London must not breach any Army or stacking rules. Where
permitted by the rules in general unled Brigades moved by
this card may be placed inside the Fortress.

6.7

Adding to the Original Draw
Deck

At the beginning of Winter 1643 follow the following
procedure:
1.

Shuffle the “Alt-Hist” Cards

Historical Note: She was with child and in Late 1644 was
delivered of a girl, the Princess Henrietta Anne who was to become
Madame, the first wife of Philippe d’Orleans brother of Louis
XIV.

2.

Draw face down the top two “Alt-Hist” cards and put aside
the rest of the cards for later,

3.

Shuffle together the “Mid War” Cards and the two “AltHist” cards just drawn.

ROLAND LAUGHARNE/NEWARK GARRISON
If played by the Royalist and the Newark Local Notable has
not yet appeared; place the Newark Garrison counter at
Newark. If played by Parliament and the Roland Laugharne
Local Notable has not yet appeared, place the Laugharne
counter at Pembroke.

4.

On the top of these cards place the “Army of the Solemn
League and Covenant” Card.

5.

Place the shuffled stack of cards from 4. beneath the
remaining current undrawn deck.

6.

Deal cards as usual.

LIEUTENANT GENERAL OF HIS MAJESTY’S ARMIES
Mark this by placing the Lieutenant-General
counter on Prince Rupert’s Command Display.
If Rupert is currently Subordinated to a Level 2
General he Subordinates that General. If he is
currently Subordinated to a Level 1 General, use
the rules in 9.5 for illegal Subordination to resolve.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

6.8

Adding to the Second Draw
Deck

When the Second Draw Deck is fully drawn then follow the
following procedure:
1.

Draw face down the top two “Alt-Hist” cards; the rest of
the “Alt-Hist” cards are put aside and not used again,

2.

Shuffle together the “Late War” Deck and the two Alt-Hist
cards just drawn. These now become the Draw Deck.

3.

If the last card dealt was to the Royalist Player then give
the “New Model Army” Mandatory Strategy Card to the
Parliament Player.

4.

If the last card dealt was to the Parliament Player then
exchange it for the “New Model Army” Mandatory
Strategy Card and pass that last card to the Royalist.

5.

Continuing dealing to reach four cards for each player.

7.0

RECRUITMENT

New Brigades can be brought into play in three ways:,
(a) They may be placed in the Recruitment Phase of each
Game Turn. This method does not require the play of a
card.
(b) Both sides can play one Operations or Discard card
per turn to bring Recruits into the game unless certain
Events are in play. The card is placed on the relevant
space on the Player Card to remind you of the one card
limit. This action is known as a Grandee Recruitment for
the Royalist Player or an Assessment and Sequestration
Recruitment for the Parliament Player.
(c) Some Event Cards bring new Brigades in to play. See rule
6.4 for details.
Unless otherwise noted—with Battle losses the main
exception (10.2)—any time a Brigade is lost or removed it is
available immediately for Recruitment. Only losses indicated
as permanent may not be Recruited (though see 6.4, Placing
Brigades).

7.1

Common Recruitment Rules

7.1.1
VETERANS OR MILITIA?
Where a number of Brigades in a Region are available as
Recruits, Militia Brigades (1 value units) must be Recruited
first, Veteran Brigades (2 value units) only if no Militia are
available. The Naval (15.0) and Powicke Bridge (7.1.2) rules,
as well as some Event Cards, can give exceptions to this. This
rule no longer applies to the Royalists once the New Model
Army card is played.
7.1.2
POWICKE BRIDGE
Once in each of the first two Turns of the game, during the
Recruitment Phase, the Royalist Player can Recruit a Veteran
Brigade in place of a Militia Brigade.
Historical Note: Powicke Bridge was the first significant action
of the war (23 September, 1642), with Prince Rupert covering
the escape of Sir John Byron with the treasury from Oxford and
gaining a reputation as an invincible cavalry commander.
Play Note: A question that arises with this rule is: Why would
the Royalist Player not automatically choose a Veteran Brigade

13

in each of the first two turns? The answer is that one strategy
available to the Royalist Player is to keep the Veterans off the map
as long as possible, as they’ll be needed as Parliament gets stronger
later in the game.
7.1.3
THE NEW MODEL
New Model Army Brigades can be Recruited in any Region
except Wales.
7.1.4
SIEGE TRAINS
Instead of one Brigade of Recruitment a player
can bring a Siege Train marker onto the map.
There can only ever be one such counter in play
for each side. The counter must be placed in a
friendly Fortress anywhere on the map and can
be placed in the same Area as a newly Recruited Brigade.
Historical Note: Cannon for a Siege Train were usually stored in
Fortresses.
A player may remove a Siege Train from the map at the same
time as he plays a Strategy Card, with the marker then placed
on the Turn Chart on the next turn to indicate that it can be
Recruited again any time after the current turn ends. Under
no circumstances may a Siege Train be transferred to another
General or dropped off—it must be removed and Recruited
again. Any Friendly Army can pick an unled Siege Train from
its Fortress.
A Siege Train does not count as a Brigade for stacking or any
other purpose. It must remain with a friendly Army or in a
Fortress; remove the counter to the turn track if it is ever not
the case.
7.1.5
LACK OF ECONOMIC INFRASTRUCTURES
A Player who controls no Economic Infrastructures (17.3)
cannot play a Recruitment Card. They still receive their
Recruits during the Recruitment Phase.
7.1.6

COVENANTER, IRISH AND LORRAINER
RECRUITMENT
No Covenanter, Irish or Lorrainer Brigades can be Recruited.
These units only arrive on the play of Event Cards.
7.1.7
DISPERSED BRIGADES
Reforming Brigades: Dispersed Brigades (see 10.1) are placed
in the Unemployed Generals Box. At the next Recruitment
Phase, the owning player chooses half of these Brigades
(rounding down) for placement in that Phase as if they were
Recruits in addition to the number listed for that turn. The
Dispersed Brigades not selected as additional Recruits are
available for normal Recruitment.
Placing Reformed Brigades: The reforming Dispersed
Brigades do not affect the number of Brigades available
for Recruitment under 7.2 or 7.3. Each of the reforming
Brigades must be placed on a friendly PC marker in their
Region, providing that they are not placed in the same Area
with any other Brigade placed in that Recruitment Phase
(whether Recruit or reforming). Reforming “Irish” Brigades
may appear in any Region.
Historical Note: Armies could flee during this period but cadres
often reformed. Remember that only English and “Irish” (which
were really English) Brigades can Disperse, Covenanters and
Lorrainers cannot take advantage of that route (see 10.1). Being
foreigners every hand was against them.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

14

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

7.2

The Recruitment Phase

In the Recruitment Phase both players can Recruit the
number of Brigades listed for that turn on the Turn Record
Track, see Rule 7.2.2 (as modified by Naval Chart, see 15.3).
Order of Recruitment: Parliament always Recruits first, then
the Royalists.
Under Command: If a friendly General or Local Notable
is in the same Area as the newly Recruited Brigade, the
Brigade can be immediately placed on his Command Display
irrespective of the General’s Region.
Regional Limits: No more than one Brigade from each
Region can be Recruited per Recruitment Phase
Where to Recruit: Recruitment requires a friendly or neutral
controlled Recruitment Area (marked on the map with
a drummer) or friendly Local Notable (represented by a
counter). Each Recruitment Area’s Drummer is marked as
to side (a Parliament or Royalist flag) and the drummer is
marked in Regional colors.
Siege: No Brigade can be Recruited in an Area with a Siege
marker.
7.2.1
PLACING RECRUITED BRIGADES
Recruited Brigades must be placed on either:
•

A friendly or neutral controlled, Recruitment Area of
that Brigade’s Region (captured Recruitment Areas
cannot be used by their conqueror) OR

•

With an unbesieged friendly Local Notable of the same
Region as the Recruited Brigade (place the Brigade on
the Local Notable’s Command Display)
Play Note: The restriction is on one Brigade per Region
Recruitment Area. The Royalists can place two Brigades in the
Midlands by placing a Welsh Brigade in Shrewsbury, which is
a Welsh Recruitment Area and a Midlands Brigade in Chester.
Note that the Drummer icons for each Area are differently colored.
Similarly, Parliament can place two Brigades in London,
provided one is from the East and one is from the South.
Play Note: Brigades can be placed in any Command Display in
the target Area, including Subordinate Displays.

7.2.2
RECRUITING NUMBERS
The number of Brigades each side recruits in each
Recruitment Phase is listed on the Turn Record Track, but is
summarized as follows:
Recruited in or
by means of

Late
1642

Winter
1642

1643 to
1644

1645

Recruitment
Phase

1

3

2

1

Operations
Card

2

2

2

2

Discarded
Event Card

1

1

1

1

7.2.3 PLACING GENERALS
Any number of Generals from the Reinforcements Box can
be placed for free in the Recruitment Phase. Generals can
only be placed in an Area without any enemy counter (PC
marker, Brigade or General). Field Generals can be placed in

any such Area. Regional Generals must be placed in any such
Area in their own Region or where their Region’s Brigades
can be Recruited.
Generals placed during the Recruitment Phase must be
placed with friendly Brigades and must constitute an Army
(even if Subordinated, 9.5) upon placement. They can take
Brigades from a Local Notable in the same Area and/or take
uncontrolled Brigades from the map to achieve this. Note
that Generals may also come into play as per 8.1.
7.2.4
THE REINFORCEMENTS BOX
Each player has a Reinforcements Box on their Command
Display in which he keeps those of his Generals that are
available as reinforcements.

7.3

Recruitment Cards

Players may play one Strategy Card per Game Turn to Recruit.
The Royalists may only Recruit in this way as described in
Rule 7.3.1; Parliament only under rule 7.3.2.
7.3.1
ROYALIST GRANDEE RECRUITMENT CARD
The Royalist Player can play one Operations Card (of any
value) as a Recruitment card each turn to Recruit two
Brigades or discard an Event Card to Recruit one Brigade.
Playing such a card can also bring any number of Regional
Generals into play. This card, which becomes known as the
“Grandee Recruitment Card” for that turn only, can be any
card except for a mandatory Event Card. The following
restrictions to Recruitment apply:
•

The Brigades Recruited must be placed in the Command
Display of a non-Subordinated Regional General or a
Local Notable. The Brigade Recruited must be from
the same Region as the Regional General or the Local
Notable with which it is placed. The Brigade must be
from the same Region as the Area of placement. No
Brigade can be placed in an Area with a Siege marker.

•

Only one Brigade is permitted to be placed per General
or Local Notable for each Card played, but more than
one Brigade can be Recruited in a Region.

•

Only Regional Generals can be placed with the Grandee
card, and are placed as in 7.2.3.
Historical Note: Field Generals cannot Recruit under this rule
because they lack the local support and considerable estates
of the Grandees. Parliament had more success at receiving
funding in specie, for the King it was often in kind—units
raised by loyal if inexperienced nobles.

7.3.2

PARLIAMENT ASSESSMENT AND SEQUESTRATION
RECRUITMENT CARD
The Parliament Player may play one Operations Card (of
any value) as a Recruitment card each turn to Recruit two
Brigades or discard an Event Card to Recruit one Brigade.
This card, which becomes known as his “Assessment and
Sequestration Recruitment Card”, may be any card except for
a Mandatory Event Card. Playing such a card can also bring
any number of Generals into play.
The Recruited Brigades are placed as in Rule 7.2.1, except
that more than one Brigade can be placed in the same Region
(but not in the same Area). Note that Brigade placement
resulting from a Parliament Assessment and Sequestration
card differs from that of a Royalist Grandee card.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

15

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

8.0

GENERALS

8.4

An Army cannot exist without a General. Generals require
Operations Strategy Cards to Activate, and stacks of Brigades
without Generals cannot be Activated. General counters are
never stacked in the same Area as other General counters
(due to Subordination, see 9.5). Generals come in two types:
Field and Regional Generals. See 2.2 under Generals to
identify the types.

8.1

Bringing Generals Into Play

Generals can be brought onto the map in the Recruitment
Phase (7.2.3) and/or by Recruitment Card (7.3), Event
Cards, and Operations Cards (6.1). To place with an
Operations card (which must have enough Strategy Points
to Activate the General normally), the General is placed as
in the Recruitment Phase (7.2), and then must be Activated
by the card just played. A discarded Strategy Card may not be
used for this purpose.

8.2

Most Generals can have no more than four Brigades in their
Army (including any Subordinated Armies, see 9.5). The
following favored Generals can have more than four Brigades
but no more than nine Brigades in their Army.
(Royalist) King Charles, Rupert while a LieutenantGeneral (see Event Card) and Newcastle,
(Lorrainer) Charles of Lorraine,
(Covenanter) Leven,
(Parliament) Essex and the Lord General.
Players cannot pick up or Recruit any Brigades which would
violate this size limit.

Lone Generals

The owning player must remove to the Unemployed Generals
Box any General (including a Subordinate or Subordinating
General) who has no Brigades at any stage after placement
unless otherwise provided. If the General is under Siege,
he Surrenders automatically (10.4); if this happens to King
Charles, the Parliament Player instantly wins the game.

8.3

Army Size Limits

L e a v i n g , Tr a n s f e r r i n g &
Picking Up Brigades

Generals cannot drop off Brigades as they move. A General
can never remove a Brigade from his Command Display
except as a result of the Brigade’s elimination in Battle,
Desertion, or removal or transfer by play of an Event Card.
You cannot ignore any Brigades in an Army for any purpose
(to avoid losses in combat, for example).
Play Note: Some Events will remove Brigades, such as Clubmen.
Some allow for voluntary removal (and transfer), such as the
Cavalry Commander cards.
Although Brigades cannot be dropped off, unled Brigades
and those with Local Notables can be (there is no obligation)
picked up by Generals and placed on their Command Display
in three cases:
1.

Where a General is active in an Area with such Brigades

2.

Where an Enemy Army enters an Area with a Friendly
Army and eligible Brigades, and

3.

When a General is placed with eligible Brigades (for
example Brigades Recruited in a Recruitment Area).

COVENANTER AND LORRAINERS
Covenanter and Lorrainer Brigades may be dropped off but
may only be under the command of Covenanter or Lorrainer
commanders respectively.
Historical Note: The Scots detached forces to besiege Newcastle
while the main army moved south. Given their “national” nature
exemption from the factional rules seems correct.

Both Charles and Newcastle can command 9 Brigades each. However,
if Charles Subordinates Newcastle, as here, Charles still cannot
command more than 9 total Brigades between them.

9.0

MOVEMENT AND
INTERCEPTION

Brigades cannot move unless on a Command Display. A
General, in turn, can only move when a Strategy Card is
played to Activate them (see 9.1). A General can be moved
more than once in a Turn, the maximum number of
movements being limited only by the number of Operations
and Campaign Cards the owning player has. Brigades can
only be moved by one General per card.

9.1

Operations Strategy Cards

Generals can be Activated by the play of an Operations Card
(6.1) or Minor and Major Campaign Card (6.1). Major Armies
of five Brigades or greater require the play of a 3 Operations
card or Campaign card to Activate (6.2).

9.2

Movement Procedures

A Field or Regional General has a number of Movement
Points (MP) based on the size of his Army:
Number of Brigades
in Army

Number of
Movement Points
available for that
Army

Number of Areas
that the Army may
Evade

One to three

4

2

Four to six

3

1

Seven to nine

2

1

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

16

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

As the Army moves the number of Brigades may increase
resulting in a decrease in available Movement Points. At any
time following an increase or decrease in Army size where
the number of Movement Points spent equals or exceeds
the available number at that instant, then movement ceases
immediately.
Example: An Army with three Brigades moves 2 Movement Points
(it has maximum Movement Points of 4) and picks up a Brigade.
As it has spent 2 Movement Points it now has only one Movement
Point remaining.
Example: Waller and 2 Brigades Activate, he has four Movement
Points. He moves three Areas and picks up two more Brigades.
His movement allowance is now three and he cannot therefore
move further. Note, however, that had he spent all four of his
Movement Points to enter the Area with the two Brigades he still
would have been able to pick them up.
BREAKING UP SIEGE LINES
An Army with a Siege Marker must pay one Movement Point
to remove it, unless it is attacked, in which case it may remove
it in order to maximize its defense (14.6).

9.3

Movement Lines

Movement can only occur between Areas connected by a
movement line. Movement lines come in three varieties:
Road (single green lines), Mountain (double brown lines),
and Maritime (dotted blue lines).
•

Road movement costs one
Movement Point to move to
an adjacent Area,

•

Mountain or Maritime lines
cost two Movement Points to
move to an adjacent Area.

MARITIME LINES
In addition to costing 2 Movement Points, no more than 2
Brigades may cross a Maritime line with each Operations
Card. Interception (9.7) cannot take place across a Maritime
line, and only 2 Brigades may Evade (10.1) or Retreat (10.3)
across a Maritime line. Finally, a Maritime line cannot be used
to avoid Political Isolation (11.3).

Battle and Movement

Movement of a General is temporarily halted on entering an
Area containing enemy Brigades. The General can continue
to move if he wins the Battle and has Movement Points left
after paying one Movement Point for leaving the Battle
Area. This Movement Point does not apply if the opposing
Army Evades or Disperses; in such a case the General simply
continues his movement (if desired).

9.5

Play Note: Some of the things that can prevent Subordination are
Generals of the same Level, inability to command the Brigades,
too many Brigades to command or insufficient movement to
remove a Siege marker.
If they cannot be Subordinated, they cannot end up stacked
together in the same Area (and see “Illegal Position” below).
SUBORDINATING LEVELS
The choice of the Subordinate depends on the Level of
the two commanding Generals. Two Generals of the same
Level as each other cannot combine Armies (so cannot stack
together). Where Generals have different levels then the
lower level General Subordinates to the higher level General
even if the latter was not moving. If the Activating General
is Subordinated, his Activation ends. Subordination is never
mandatory until movement has ceased. Subordinates can
be the same Level as each other but must be lower than the
General to which they are Subordinated.
Brigades commanded by a Subordinate remain with the
Subordinate on the Subordinate’s Command Display and
cannot be transferred. Rather, place the Subordinate on
his new commander’s Command Display. For all purposes,
when counting Brigades in an Army, count all Brigades of
all Subordinates in the total (this is true even if the superior
General loses all his Brigades). Army Size is the only limitation
on the number of Generals and Brigades in an Army (four or
nine Brigades, see 8.4).
LEAVING ARMIES
A Subordinate can be Activated separately by an appropriate
Operations Card and can move away from a combined Army
OR a Subordinate can be dropped off by the commanding
General during any movement, Evasion or Interception. Note
that a Subordinate may not Intercept or Evade on his own.

A General must be able to pay the
full number of Movement Points
to complete each movement.
He cannot end his turn between
Areas.

9.4

If two Armies from the same side finish movement,
Interception, Evasion or Retreat in the same Area, one of
them must be Subordinated.

Subordinate Armies

If a friendly Army enters and exits an Area with another
friendly Army one Army can become a Subordinate of the
other.

GARRISON EXCEPTION
Two friendly Generals can be in the same Fortress Area without
Subordination if one is Besieged or Masked (14.0) and the
other not. If the enemy Army leaves and Subordination is not
possible, use the “Illegal Position” rule (below) to resolve the
issue.
ILLEGAL POSITION
Due to Interception, Drawn Battles, Events and other
situations an Army can be in an illegal Subordination
position. If this occurs at the end of that Activation, retrace
that Army’s movement until it is in a legal position. In other
circumstances, the owning player moves an Army to an
adjacent Area without enemy Brigades (if no such Areas,
Disperse), repeating until the illegal situation is resolved.
RIVALRIES
Waller cannot Subordinate to Essex.
Play Note: The “Committee of Both Kingdoms” Event Card can
temporarily lift this restriction and permit one joint venture
between Waller and Essex.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!
COVENANTERS AND LORRAINERS
Covenanter Brigades may only be under command of
Covenanter Generals, and Covenanter Generals can only be
Subordinate to other Covenanter Generals (that is, Callander
may Subordinate to Leven). Lorrainer Brigades may only be
under the command of Charles of Lorraine.

across a Maritime line. Subordinated Generals may not
Intercept on their own, but they may do so as part of their
commanding General’s army.
Play Note: No double Interceptions are allowed, unlike some card
driven wargames.
Play Note: The restriction on not Intercepting where a friendly
Army occupies the potential target Area is because Armies of this
period were not coordinated at all and tended to stay away from
each other. This is different than other card driven games, and
does require different play. English armies of this period could not
form cordons.

SUBORDINATING LEVELS
(Level One is highest, Level Four is the lowest)
Level

Royalist Generals

One

King Charles I, Charles of Lorraine, Rupert
(if Lt.-General)

Two

Goring, Newcastle

Three

Maurice, Rupert (if not Lt.-General)

Four

Byron, Hopton, Langdale, Gerard

Level

Parliament Generals

One

Essex, Leven, Lord General (NMA)

Two

Manchester, Waller, Cromwell

Three

Tom Fairfax (North)

Four

Bedford, Poyntz, Lord Fairfax, and Massey
and Brereton (when Regional Generals)

Example: Leven (5 Brigades) sits before York. During the next
two Activations, Manchester (2 Brigades) and Tom Fairfax (2
Brigades) enter the York Area. Both are lower level than Leven and
both must Subordinate to him. The Brigades are not moved, but
the General counters are placed on Leven’s Command Display.

9.6

Changing PC Marker Control

An Activated Army can place a friendly PC marker (and, if
necessary, simultaneously remove an enemy PC marker) in
its current Area (but not a Fortress) by spending 1 Movement
Point (11.1)—this is in addition to the Movement Point it
spends to enter the Area or is the first Movement Point if it
starts the Activation in the Area.
Designer’s Note: Placing PC markers during movement represents
capturing minor garrisons and the suppression of enemy partisans
that was a staple of the era.

9.7

17

If Bedford moves, Hopton can intercept him in Exeter and
Barnstaple, but not Bath, which is occupied by a Royalist Brigade.
If he intercepts in Exeter, the Battle takes place immediately (see
9.7.5) before Bedford can pick up Skippon’s Parliament Brigade.
9.7.2
RESOLVING INTERCEPTIONS
To determine whether or not an attempt to Intercept
succeeds, the Intercepting player rolls 1d6 and:
•

adds one if the Intercepting General’s Strategy Rating
(not Battle Rating) is numerically lower than that of the
Activating General OR

•

deducts one if the Intercepting General’s Strategy Rating
(not Battle Rating) is numerically higher than that of the
Activating General AND

•

deducts one if attempting Interception over a Mountain
line

NB: The better the General the lower his Strategy Rating.

Interception

Interception occurs during an Army’s movement. To
Intercept, the non-Activating Army moves one Area to
interrupt the movement of an opposing Activating opposing
Army, thereby forcing a Battle.
9.7.1
WHEN CAN AN INTERCEPTION OCCUR?
An Interception can occur when an Activating Army enters an
Area adjacent to an enemy Army. An Army cannot Intercept
into an Area that contains Brigades of its own side. Each nonActivating Army can attempt to Intercept only once per enemy
General Activated, and only one Army can attempt to Intercept
an enemy General in any one Area he enters. Interception is
always voluntary. Interception can only be attempted during a
normal movement Activation (never during Evasion, Retreats
or any other form of movement). Interception cannot occur

If the modified score is 4 or higher Interception occurs,
otherwise the non-Activating Army stays in position and
cannot Intercept again during the current Activation.
Play Note: Mountains hinder both Interception and Evasion
attempts (see 10.1 for the latter).
9.7.3
INTERCEPTION EFFECTS
If an Interception attempt succeeds the Intercepting Army
moves into the target Area and a Battle is fought with the
Activating Army that has also entered that Area (see 10.0)—
there can be no Evasion although there can be Dispersal. The
Activating Army (not the Intercepting Army) still counts as
attacking.
Designer’s Note: The Interceptor is treated as having moved in
anticipation of the Activating force; getting there first.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

18

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

9.7.4

INTERCEPTING INTO A FRIENDLY OCCUPIED
AREA
Armies cannot Intercept into an Area containing a friendly
Army or Brigades.
9.7.5
INTERCEPTING INTO AN ENEMY OCCUPIED AREA
Where an Army Intercepts successfully into an Area containing
an enemy Army or Brigades then only the Interceptor and the
Activating Army have combat immediately. If the Interceptor
wins that Battle he is placed back in the Area from which he
Intercepted. If he loses he Retreats as normal. See 9.5 for how
to handle a Moving Army forced into an illegal position.

10.0

On any other score (or where no available Evasion Area
exists) the Battle is resolved normally.

BATTLES

A Battle occurs when an Army moves or Intercepts (9.7.3)
into an Area that contains enemy Brigades that are not in an
enemy Fortress. The Activating Army is always the Attacker. If
the Activating Army wins a Battle, it can continue movement
if it has available Movement Points, but it must spend one
Movement Point for the Battle (9.4). If an Activating Army
enters a Battle Area on its last Movement Point it may still
fight; the Movement Point for Battle is paid only if the Army
wishes to move further in that Activation. If the Activating
Army loses or draws any Battle, its Activation ends immediately
after the die roll.
Play Note: Because the Activation ends immediately after the die
roll, the losing/drawing Army cannot pick up Brigades in the
Area where it ends movement.

10.1 Evasion and Dispersal
Whenever an Army attacks an enemy Army, the defending
Army can try to Evade. Evasion attempts always happen
after Interception (so you cannot Evade and then attempt
to Intercept with a different Army). Intercepting Armies
and unled Brigades cannot Evade. Where an Army Evades,
the Activating Army can continue moving (since no Battle
has occurred) at no extra Movement cost—it can attempt to
attack the Evading Army again if it has sufficient Movement
Points, and the Evading army may attempt to Evade again
(and so on).
RESOLVING EVASIONS
The Evading player rolls 1d6 and
•

Movement Table (9.2). The Evading Army can move into
any Area that does not contain enemy Brigades. If the Army
contains more than 2 Brigades, they cannot Evade across a
Maritime line. Evaders cannot enter the Area from which the
Activating Army entered their Area.

adds one if the Evading General’s Strategy Rating (not
Battle Rating) is numerically lower than that of the
Activating General OR

•

deducts one if the Evading General’s Strategy Rating
(not Battle Rating) is numerically higher than that of the
Activating General AND

•

deducts one if the Activating Army entered the Area via a
Mountain or Maritime line

NB: The better the General the lower his Strategy Rating.
Play Note: Deducting one from the die-roll if the Activating army
is entering via a mountain or maritime link represents the greater
difficulty in knowing that the army is approaching.
If the modified result is 4 or higher, the Evading Army
can move the number of connected Areas (regardless of
Movement Point cost) listed in the Evasion column of the

Lord Fairfax has just one Brigade in his Army and faces the
King, marching from York. If his Evasion roll is successful,
Fairfax will be able to go to any Area shown, except Shrewsbury
(too far away) or York (the Area the Activating Army came
from). He is even allowed to enter the Local Notable Earl of
Derby’s Area, provided the Earl has no Brigades there.
FORTRESSES
If an Army is attacked in a Fortress Area, and the Army can
occupy the Fortress, the Army may withdraw into the Fortress
(after failing or declining Evasion).
Play Note: In this case, the Army that fails its Evasion simply did
not detect the enemy forces, but still has plenty of time to retire to
the Fortress.
DISPERSAL
Where Evasion was not successful, not possible, or not
attempted either side can elect to Disperse, the defender
choosing first. Both sides reveal their Brigades before these
choices are made.
If a player chooses Dispersal, all of his Dispersing Generals and
their Brigades from the Area are placed in the Unemployed
Generals Box; a Dispersed General is not considered to have
Surrendered. Where the Dispersal Area is not a Fortress,
the attacking Army can place a friendly PC marker there
(replacing any enemy marker) at no cost in Movement Points
(11.1). The Activating Army may continue to move after the
Dispersal of the other Army; it has spent no extra Movement
Points because of the Evasion attempt or the Dispersal.
Covenanter and Lorrainer Brigades may never voluntarily
Disperse; if forced to do so (such as when resolving an illegal
position), they are eliminated instead. An Army containing a
mix of Covenanter, Lorrainer and Parliament Brigades may
Disperse the Parliament Brigades, but the others will always
fight.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

10.2 Resolving Battles

19

•

the score of 1d6,

•

the Combat Value of all his Brigades in the Area,

•

the Battle Rating of his General (where a stack has no
General the Battle Rating is 0), and

Retreat, and this Brigade is immediately available for
Recruitment). A Retreating defending stack cannot enter
the Area from which an attack was launched. If the loser was
the Attacker, the first Area of Retreat must be the Area from
which the stack entered the Battle Area. If a Retreating stack
has more than 2 Brigades, it cannot utilize a Maritime line.
A Retreat cannot violate Subordination rules (9.5). A stack
that cannot Retreat must Surrender (10.4). Retreat is not
Activation, so Subordinates cannot de-stack.

•

the modifiers from any Combat Card played (this counts
as one of the six required card plays).

Play Note: Unlike some card-driven games, Retreats CAN end in
neutral or enemy-controlled Areas.

Before resolving the Battle, either player (starting with the
Attacker) can play one Combat Card (and no more than
one). After playing cards, each player adds:

These two Battle Scores are then compared and the difference
calculated.
Scores that are equal or have a difference of one are Drawn
Battles: each side loses one Brigade (Veteran if available).
Drawn Battles where the Attacker outscored the Defender
are known as Attacker Drawn Battles; all other Drawn Battles
are known as Defender Drawn Battles (see below for the
difference in treatment).
Scores with a difference of two to four are Indecisive
Victories: the higher score wins and the loser loses one
Brigade (Militia if available). The winner loses no units.

10.4 Surrender
If the loser cannot Retreat then it must Surrender. Brigades
that Surrender are eliminated from the game. These are
permanent losses and they cannot be Recruited again.
Surrendered Generals are put in the Unemployed Generals
Box.
A General also Surrenders if all his Brigades are lost in Battle,
unless stacked with a Subordinate who retains at least one
Brigade. If King Charles Surrenders the Parliament Player
wins an Automatic Victory.

Scores with a difference of five or more are Major Victories:
the higher score wins (the winner loses no units) and the
losers loses two Brigades—Militia if available. This can
become a Decisive Victory as per 10.7. However, in a Decisive
Victory the losses must be from Veteran Brigades if present at
the Battle.

10.5 Spoils of Victory

DRAWN BATTLES
Defender Drawn Battles: The attacking Army returns to the
Area it left to enter the Battle Area and its Activation (if any)
is complete (using rule 9.5 to resolve an illegal Subordination
position). This withdrawal does not count as Retreat or
Movement.

In a 1644 or 1645 turn the winner of a Major or Decisive
Victory may add an additional Friendly Brigade to their army
from those eliminated in the Battle (note that this will be an
enemy unit, since the winner loses no units in such Battles).
Lorrainer or Covenanter Generals do not get this bonus
Brigade.

Attacker Drawn Battles: The defender Retreats as if the loser
in Rule 10.3 below.

Historical Note: As the war wore on, it became more common for
soldiers to change sides.

DECISIVE VICTORY
If either side achieves a Major Victory AND had played a
Combat Card marked “Decisive Victory”, the Major Victory
becomes a Decisive Victory (10.7).

10.7 Major and Decisive Victories

LOSSES
Battle losses (not those from Dispersal, Retreat, Desertion, or
Supply Attrition) are permanent; the unit destroyed cannot
be Recruited again that game. (Though Event Cards can call
the units back—see 6.4, Placing Brigades.) Put the eliminated
unit(s) aside.

10.3 Retreat
After a Battle which was not a Drawn Battle the loser must
Retreat at least one Area, but (at the loser’s discretion) it
can Retreat further up to its Evasion distance (9.2) at its
reduced size. A stack of unled Brigades is treated as if they
were combined into an Army for determining their Retreat
distance). All Brigades must Retreat to the same Area.
The Retreat cannot be into any Areas containing enemy
Brigades. If a Retreat enters an Area with an enemy PC
marker, a further Brigade is lost (one at most per entire

A winning Army (not unled Brigades) can place a friendly
PC marker in the Battle Area (replacing any enemy marker if
necessary) if the Battle Area was not a Fortress (11.1).

1 0 . 6 Tu r n c o a t s

The winner of a Major Victory draws a Strategy Card from the
deck and the winner of a Decisive Victory draws two Strategy
Cards as soon as the Battle is completed. He then completes
the original Activation if any Movement Points remain to be
used from that Activation. Immediately upon completing that
Activation he must play or discard his ‘victory cards’. Play now
returns to the normal alternating process.
The Royalists draw their extra Strategy Cards from the top of
the undrawn deck. The Parliament Player draws cards from
the discard pile (these are drawn randomly after shuffling).
These cards do not count towards the six card requirement
before passing (5.0). If there are insufficient cards in the draw
pile, extra draws are lost.

10.8 Nesting
It is possible for more than one Major/Decisive Victory to
occur in an Activation. Draw the cards for each Major/Decisive
Victory (the winner can examine them) and place them aside
in plain sight. Each set is played in the order drawn. If during
the play of bonus cards a further Major/Decisive Victory

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

20

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

occurs then those cards will be played when all previous sets
are exhausted (in short, always play each set in the order they
are earned when the previous set is finished).

11.0

removes his Isolated PC markers. The Royalist player then
does so. The removal of Parliament PC markers could result
in Royalist PC markers avoiding removal.

11.3 Political Isolation

POLITICAL
CONTROL

A PC marker is Isolated when it cannot trace a chain of its own
contiguous PC markers and/or empty Areas to one of:

Control of Areas is indicated by Political Control (PC)
Markers. An Area is one of the following: neutral or open (no
marker), Royalist (a blue marker) and Parliament (an orange
marker).

•

A friendly controlled Supply Fortress (not a limited
Fortress) which is not Masked or Besieged by an enemy
Army (14.0),

•

A friendly unbesieged Local Notable, or

11.1 Placing PC Markers in the
Campaign Phase

•

A friendly Army

PC markers can be placed during the Campaign Phase
•

As a result of playing an Operations Card (6.1) or
Discarded Event Card (6.4) to place PC markers;

•

As the result of an Army spending an extra Movement
Point in a non-Fortress Area (9.6)—with this method
PC markers may be placed on open Areas or enemy PC
markers may be replaced by friendly ones;

•

As the result of a Local Notable Raid (13.0);

•

As a result of playing a relevant Event Card (6.4);

•

As a result of causing a Dispersal (10.1);

•

As the result of winning a Battle or forcing the Surrender
of a Fortress (10.4 and 14.4).

OPERATIONS CARDS
Operations Strategy Cards can be played to place a number of
PC markers up to their value (Minor/Major Campaign Cards
cannot place PC markers). A discarded Event Card can be
used to place one PC marker.
A PC marker can be placed in any open Area or in a nonFortress Area with a friendly Army or Local Notable (which
can replace an enemy PC marker). New markers must be
placed adjacent to a friendly PC marker that existed prior to
the current card play.
Play Note: Control cannot be imposed by a tendril of connected
Areas placed in the same Activation, it is a more gradual matter.
FORTRESS CONTROL
Fortress Areas change control only by Surrendering (14.4) or
by an Event Card that specifically allows a change of Fortress
control. Note that Local Notable Areas are not Fortress Areas
by themselves; however, the Local Notable counter makes the
Area a Fortress Area.
Play Note: The events which can cause a change of Fortress control
are: Hotham’s Plot, Lord Wilmot’s Plot, Sir John Meldrum, Plots:
The Hothams & Sir John Carew and the Earl of Holland’s Plot/
Lady d’Aubigny’s Scheme.

11.2 The Political Control Phase
In the Political Control Phase, players first place PC markers
in all non-Fortress Areas that are occupied by friendly
Brigades or friendly Local Notables (replacing an enemy
marker if present).
Then, players remove all Isolated PC markers (11.3). First
the Parliament player identifies his Isolated Areas. He then

This chain cannot use the Maritime line between Hull and
Gainsborough.
Fortresses themselves, whether supply Fortresses or limited
Fortresses, are never Isolated.

Truro, St. Austell and Barnstaple have been cut off from
Hopton’s Army by Bedford and a barrier of Parliamentcontrolled Areas. In the next Political Control Phase all three
Royalist PC Markers will be removed.

12.0

DESERTION & THE
H O R R O R S O F WA R

Desertion takes place in the Desertion and Supply Attrition
Phase of each Game Turn. Consult the Turn Record Track;
the Desertion Number for the current Game Turn is the
number of Brigades to be removed by each side. Parliament
selects which Brigades to remove first, although no Brigades
are actually removed until both sides have selected which
to remove. Removed Brigades are available immediately for
Recruitment.

12.1 Desertion Limitation
The Desertion Number cannot reduce a Player’s total Brigades
on the map below five. Any unmet Desertion requirement
that would do so is disregarded. Irish or Covenanter units
must be used to meet the Desertion Number when the total
number of other friendly Brigades is five or less. (They do not
otherwise Desert). Lorrainer Brigades can always be used to
meet the Desertion requirement.

12.2 Desertion Selection Process
Brigades are selected for Desertion using the following
categories (and in the following order), but the total number
of Brigades removed never exceeds the Desertion Number
for the current Game Turn.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!
For each category find whether any Areas meet the conditions
then remove one Brigade from each such Area (up to the
limit required). Where a choice exists the owning player can
select which Brigades to lose. However, an Area with only one
Brigade must not be chosen in preference to an alternative
with more than one Brigade.
If further Desertions are required move down to the next
category and repeat the process. If necessary, return to
the first category and cycle through the list as many times
as required until all Desertions are removed (or the Key
Limitation is reached).
The same Area can appear under each category, and thus lose
multiple Brigades in one turn (if the limit for the Game Turn
allows).
DESERTION ORDER CATEGORIES
1. Armies with Regional Generals (including Subordinates)
outside the Region of those Generals irrespective of the
Region of their Brigades. A Covenanter General with
Parliament Brigades outside the North also suffers losses
under this category.
2.

Armies of more than three Brigades.

3.

Armies in an Area adjacent to or same space as an enemy
Army that is not Masked or Besieged (13.0).

4.

Armies in an Area with an enemy PC marker (including
those that are Masked or Besieged (13.0).

5.

All Areas with friendly Brigades. This is the only occasion
unled Brigades suffer Desertion.

Historical Note: The tendency for 17th century armies to fall
apart was pronounced. Troops preferred not to move too far from
home, especially not into enemy territory. Close proximity to the
enemy reduced foraging opportunities and might result in combat.
The risk of disease was always stronger in large armies.
LONE GENERALS
If a General is left with no Brigades after Desertion, he is
removed to the Unemployed Generals Box as per 8.2.

12.3 Supply Attrition
After Desertion is completed any Area with 5 or more friendly
Brigades must lose any one Brigade to Supply Attrition.

21

Essex loses one Brigade under Category 2 (large armies).
Essex loses a further Brigade under Category 3. Although
Manchester is also in this category he has only one Brigade
and thus cannot be chosen before Essex. That completes the
Parliament Desertion. However, as Essex has 5 Brigades left
he will suffer Supply Attrition (12.3) as well—losing another
Brigade. For the Royalists no Armies meet category 1. King
Charles is in Category 2 and he loses a Brigade. Both King
Charles and Rupert meet Category 3, and both will lose a
Brigade, completing the Royalist Desertion.

13.0

LOCAL NOTABLES

Local Notables (LN) counters are placed only on Local
Notable Areas, either before the start of the game (if called
for by the setup instructions) or by the play of specific Event
Cards (see below). A Local Notable Area without a LN
counter is simply a normal Area; once a LN counter has been
placed in that Area, the Area becomes a Fortress until the LN
counter is eliminated.
If a Local Notable is Besieged and Surrenders the counter
is removed from play for the rest of the game—the Besieger
does not get the counter as a Fortress. Local Notables have
an automatic -2 against all Bombardments. Local Notables
never move, fight Battles, Evade or Intercept, and cannot
Subordinate or be Subordinated. Recruits can be placed with
them.
Designer’s Note: Local Notables represent not single places or
individuals but instead are a number of fortified posts and
castles. They are very much a product of their own region, which
is why they cannot Raid outside their Region (no, Derby cannot
Raid in the North).
GARRISONS
Local Notables can have up to four Brigades on their
Command Displays. They can freely transfer Brigades to
friendly Generals in the same Area, even if the General is
simply passing through the Area (they can also be transferred
via the play of specific cards). These Brigades count as a
Fortress garrison for the Local Notable. No Field or Regional
Generals can be within this Fortress.

Historical Note: The large plundering armies of the Thirty Years
Wars were not to be found in England.

12.4 Desertion Example
It is Late 1644 and there are the following Armies in play:
Parliament: Essex (7 Brigades), Waller (3 Brigades),
Manchester (1 Brigade) and Fairfax (2 Brigades)
Royalists: Rupert (3 Brigades), King Charles (4 Brigades),
Herbert (1 Brigade) and Newcastle (3 Brigades).
Rupert and Charles I are adjacent to Essex and Manchester.
All other Armies are not adjacent to any other. All Regional
Generals except Fairfax are in their own Regions. Both sides
must have 3 Brigades Desert.
The Parliament selects his Desertions first (though the
process is simultaneous in its effect). Fairfax must lose a
Brigade for being outside his Region under Category 1.

Parliamentary Local Notable Willoughby can Raid (see
overleaf) Newark, Boston and King’s Lynn. However, he cannot
raid Leicester, as he is an Eastern LN and cannot Raid across
the Region border into the Midlands. He can exchange the PC
Marker on Newark, since the Newark Garrison LN counter has
not been placed and so the Area is not yet a Fortress.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

22

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

RAIDING
An unbesieged Local Notable when Activated can place or
exchange one PC marker in any non-Fortress Area in the same
Region within two Areas of their counter that has no enemy
Brigades (11.1). An Operations Card can be used to Activate
a number of different Local Notables equal to the value of the
Operations Card. They Activate one after the other as with
Minor or Major Campaign cards. A discarded Event Card can
Activate one Local Notable. The Local Notable counter is not
moved when Raiding.

number PLUS the number of Brigades in the Fortress. Such
an Army can Bombard a Fortress by using an Operations Card
that can Activate it (Bombardment may not be combined with
any other activity). A Fortress is not under Siege until a Siege
Marker is placed.

LOCAL NOTABLES AND EVENT CARDS
Some Local Notables appear as a result of an Event Card
(Laugharne, Newark Garrison, Blake, Aimez Loyauté). The
Local Notable marker is placed in the respective diamondshaped Area as follows:
• Laugharne: Pembroke
• Newark Garrison: Newark
• Blake: Lyme
• Basing House: Basing House
Placement occurs irrespective of enemy units. If there are
enemy units or an Army in the Area the Local Notable marker
is placed under those units. If the space is enemy controlled
then control is switched to that of the Local Notable.

14.0

FORTRESSES

Fortress Areas are marked with a pentagon or hexagon
(there is no difference for Siege purposes, but see Isolation,
11.3). Local Notable counters also act as
Fortresses. Armies in an enemy Fortress
Area are either Besieging or Masking the
Fortress. See rule 14.2 for the conditions
of Besieging. Where an Army occupies
an enemy Fortress Area even if the Area
is not Besieged (see 14.2), the Area is
treated as Masked.
Design Note: A masked Fortress is one that is under close
observation by an enemy army. Supply and troop movements will
be affected. However, formal Siege requires much more action on
the part of the enemy army.

14.1 Occupying Fortresses
A limited number of Brigades can be inside a Fortress (place
counters under the PC marker to indicate what is inside) as
against in the same Area. This maximum limit is the Area’s
Fortress Class (so a two Brigade Army, or two unled Brigades,
or a mixture can occupy Oxford) unless it is a Limited Fortress
(those in a pentagonal Area), where the maximum limit is
always one Brigade. Brigades and Armies can be placed inside
the Fortress only when Activated, Recruited or when an Army
is attacked (10.1).
All Brigades on a Local Notable’s Command Display are
considered to be within their Fortress if the leader is. Brigades
inside a Fortress are safe from Battle (10.0).

14.2 Besieging
An enemy Fortress can be Besieged only by an Army with a
number of Brigades that equals or exceeds the Fortress Class

Hopton’s Army is too small to Siege Parliamentary Plymouth, a
Class 3 Fortress. However, if Rupert arrives and Subordinates
Hopton, the combined Army is more than big enough for the job.
LOCAL NOTABLE AREAS
An enemy Local Notable can be Besieged by an Army
consisting of at least as many Brigades as are stacked with the
Local Notable. Whatever the number of Brigades, the Local
Notable has a Surrender Value of 4.
SIEGE MARKERS
A Siege Marker may be placed on any qualifying Army during
its Movement or when Activated for Bombardment. An Army
with a Siege Marker cannot move (though Subordinates can
join or leave the Army), initiate combat, be Subordinated or
attempt an Interception without first removing the Marker.
The removal of a Siege Marker in movement costs one
Movement Point. This includes removing a Siege Marker
from an Army that is Subordinating. If an Army no longer has
sufficient Brigades the Siege Marker is removed immediately
at no cost.
Play Note: Subordinates and Siege Markers: A Siege Marker is
always placed on the Army on the map. Subordinates are free to
come and go without disturbing the marker. However, if another
Army wants to Subordinate the Sieging Army, the marker will be
removed (and will cost a Movement Point—if the MP cannot
be paid, the movement cannot be completed). This is because the
siege lines are set up by the original Army, and the coordination
of Armies was insufficient to permit simply switching who
mans the lines. 17th Century English armies were triumphs of
extemporization, not of experience.
BLOCKADE & SIEGE MARKERS
During the Recruitment Phase you can place a Blockade
& Siege Marker on any Army that can Besiege a Fortress
(you can replace a normal Siege Marker in this way) in the
same Area. A Blockade & Siege Marker acts as a normal
Siege Marker but also permits a “free” Bombardment in the
Blockade Phase. Placing a Blockade & Siege marker does not
count as Recruitment; it is simply a free placement.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

23

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!
Designer’s Note: Blockade & Siege markers represent long-term
leaguers of fortifications that are in place throughout a turn.
They also permit large Covenanter Sieges without spending 3
Operations cards.
GARRISONS
An Army inside a Fortress while Besieged or Masked can be
Activated as normal. It must immediately attack the Besieging
Army, which may Evade or Disperse (10.1) as normal (if the
Besieging Army discards the Siege marker). If all Brigades of
a garrison are removed from a Besieged Fortress, the Fortress
Surrenders immediately (14.4).
EFFECTS OF SIEGE
A Siege marker on a Fortress has the following effects:
no Recruitment may occur at the Fortress (7.2), nor may
Brigades be placed there by Event (6.4); the Fortress cannot
be used to prevent Isolation (11.3); Local Notables cannot
Raid (13.0) and it counts for neither side if it is an Economic
Infrastructure (17.3).
EFFECTS OF MASKING
A Masked Fortress cannot prevent Isolation (11.3) and counts
for neither side if it is an Economic Infrastructure (17.3).

14.3 Bombardment
Each Bombardment will amass a Bombardment Value equal
to:
•

the roll of 1d6

•

plus one if the Siege Train or at least three New Model
Army Brigades are present

•

less two if the Fortress is in a Port Area and the Naval
Score is in favor of the Besieged (positive for Parliament,
or negative for the Royalists). This does not apply to
Local Notables.

•

less two if the Fortress is a Local Notable.

If the result is a positive number, this Bombardment Value is
added to the accumulated Bombardment Value against that
Fortress (if any)—place a Bombardment marker on the map
showing the accumulated value, or record it on a note pad. A
Besieging Army which loses its Siege marker loses the entire
accumulated Bombardment Value instantly (see also 14.6).

14.4 Siege Surrender
Where the accumulated Bombardment Value equals or
exceeds the Surrender Value shown in the table below
(and printed on the map for Fortresses) then the Fortress
Surrenders.
(1) Check for the Honors of War; throw a 1d6 and on a score
of:
1-2 The garrison Disperses
3-6 The garrison is eliminated. This is not a permanent
loss and the Brigades are available for Recruitment
immediately
Local Notables that Surrender are eliminated from
the game permanently. Strategy cards allowing for
placements of a Local Notable that has been eliminated
may no longer be used for the event.
(2) Any enemy Siege Train in the Fortress is removed from
play
(3) A friendly PC marker is placed on the Fortress (11.1).
(4) Any General in the Fortress is moved to the Unemployed
Generals Box. In the event that King Charles Surrenders
the Royalists instantly lose the game.
REQUIRED BOMBARDMENT VALUES
Fortress Class

Surrender
Value

Locations

Local Notable
(Class 0)

4

Numerous

Class 1

4

Shrewsbury, Reading,
Chester, Nottingham,
Worcester, Scarborough

Class 2

7

Newcastle, Oxford, Bristol,
Carlisle

Class 3

11

York, Hull, London,
Plymouth, Dover,
Portsmouth

14.5 Assaults and Immediate
Assaults
A Bombarding Army can elect to Assault a Fortress for
free after a Bombardment Activation. This can normally
be done only when the current Siege has accumulated a
Bombardment Value of 5 or more. However, Sir Thomas
Fairfax, the Lord General, Cromwell, Prince Rupert or Prince
Maurice can assault with any Bombardment Activation, even
if a Bombardment Value of less than 5 (and even zero) has
been accumulated; this action is called an Immediate Assault.
As with any other assault, however, a Siege marker must be in
place.

The King has Oxford under Siege, having
been captured by the Godly. Just one
more Bombardment and the Fortress will
surrender.

A Local Notable can never be the object of an Assault.
Design Note: Local Notables are a zone of Fortresses/fortified
points and require more than a gallant storm.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

24

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

Calculate the effect of Assaults as follows:
2d6 are thrown and the score total modified as follows:
•

Add the number, not Combat Value, of attacking Brigades
(maximum of three)

•

Add 1 for a Class 1 Fortress

•

Subtract 2 for a Class 3 Fortress

•

Subtract the number of defending Brigades

•

Subtract 2 for an Assault against a location with an
accumulated Bombardment Value of less than 5.

If the modified score is 10 or more then the Fortress
Surrenders. Follow the rules for 14.4, except that Generals in
the Fortress are eliminated for the rest of the game and there
is no chance for honors of war.
If the score is less than 10 the Assault is repulsed and the
assaulting General cannot make any further Assaults for the
rest of the game; place a “May Not Assault” marker in his
Command Display box on the Player Card. If Sir Thomas
Fairfax fails an Assault, the Lord General (who replaces him)
cannot make an assault either.
Whether or not an Assault succeeds it always causes the
permanent loss of the Brigade with the highest Combat Value
in the assaulting General’s command. Due to loss of key
“cadres” it cannot be Recruited or trained again in that game;
it may not even be returned via Event Card.

14.6 Battles in Siege Areas
The Besieging Army faced by attack chooses whether to:
(a) Lift the Siege (remove the Siege Marker) and fight the
Battle. Any Brigades in the garrison are added to the
attacking Army for purposes of total combat strength
(with losses applied however the controlling player
chooses) and the General with the higher Subordination
level uses his Battle Rating. However, if Subordination
(9.5) would prevent the Armies from stacking, ignore the
garrison

15.0

N AVA L R U L E S

Each Housekeeping Phase of a Late Year turn
(these turns are marked with anchors on the
Turn Record Track) the Parliament Player
draws one Naval Chit from those remaining of
the original five. Naval Chits are never returned
to the pool after being drawn. The newly drawn Naval Chit
adjusts the Naval Status, which begins the game at zero (0).
Event Cards can also modify the Naval Status. Place the Naval
Status Marker in the relevant box of the Naval Status Chart to
show the current status, and stack all the pulled chits with it.
Designer’s Note: The naval chits are not balanced, because the
Navy supported Parliament by and large during the war.

15.1 Diplomatic Strength
If the Royalist holds London or Bristol, subtract 1 from the
Naval Status Chart level while this condition applies.

15.2 The Queen
If the Queen appears in the game and exits without being
captured then deduct 1 from Naval Status (6.6). If the Queen
appears in the game and is captured then add 2 to Naval
Status. Place the Queen marker on the Naval Status Chart as
a reminder.

15.3 Effects
Control of the sea affects Sieges and Recruitment for the
current Game Turn:
RECRUITMENT EFFECTS
Naval Status

Effect on Recruitment

-5 or less

One extra Brigade can be Recruited per
turn by the Royalist, OR use the benefit for
the “-4 to -3” box below.

-4 to -3

One (only) Brigade Recruited this turn by
the Royalists can be a Veteran, unit even if
a Militia unit is available in that Region.

-2 to +2

No effect on Recruitment

+3 to +4

One (only Brigade Recruited this turn by
the Parliamentarians can be a Veteran unit
even if a Militia unit is available in that
Region.

+5 or higher

One extra Brigade can be Recruited per
turn by the Parliamentarians, OR use the
benefit for the “+3 to +4” box above.

OR
(b) Fight without the number of Brigades necessary to
maintain the Siege (the garrison is not used in Battle in
this case). If the Besieger is defeated, the Siege marker
and the Bombardment Value are both lost.
Historical Note: Marston Moor is an excellent example of a Battle
in a Siege Area. Prince Rupert marched to the relief of York (which
held Newcastle’s Army), which was besieged by Leven, Manchester
and Tom Fairfax. Parliament lifted the Siege and fought, with
the Royalist forces commanded to disaster by Newcastle to whom
Rupert was Subordinated.
If the Besieging Army wins a Major/Decisive Victory then the
Fortress automatically Surrenders per 14.4.
After successfully relieving a Siege, an illegal Subordination
position can result, use 9.5 to resolve.

SIEGE EFFECTS
Naval Status

Effect on Bombardment

-1 or less

Parliament Armies Besieging Royalist
Fortresses in Port Areas subtract 2 from all
Bombardment dice rolls

0

No Siege Effect

+1 or higher

Royalist Armies Besieging Parliament
Fortresses in Port Areas subtract 2 from all
Bombardment dice rolls

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

25

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!
Note that, if, during the Campaign Phase, the Naval Status
reaches a level allowing for extra Recruitment, the player may
do so only if he has not already played his Recruitment card
for that turn.

16.0

F O G O F WA R

You cannot examine your opponent’s Brigades (on the
Command Display, on the map or the stacks of unrecruited
Brigades) except when laid out for Battle or when attempting
to place a Siege Marker. You can request and require the
number of Brigades in each Army (and your opponent must
furnish this information), but not which Brigades and at what
strength.

17.3 Winning at the End of the
Game
In the End Phase of the last Game Turn if no Power Base
victory has occurred, the Parliament Player doubles the
number of his controlled Regions and adds the number of
Economic Infrastructures he controls (for a maximum of 19)
to get the number of Victory Points. He wins if he has 12 or
more Victory Points. Otherwise the King has won. There can
be no tied games at the end of the game.
Region Control is defined as having PC markers in the
majority of Areas in a Region.
NUMBERS OF AREAS
Region

Areas in
Region

# Required
For Control

South

21

11

East

13

7

Wales

9

5

17.1 Automatic Victory

Midlands

17

9

The Parliament player immediately wins if King Charles
Surrenders. See 8.2, 10.4, and 14.4 for how this can happen.

North

15

8

17.0

WINNING THE
GAME

There are a number of ways in which a player can win.

Design Note: If you find this asymmetry unacceptable you can
mutually agree to disable this rule.
The Royalist player immediately wins if, at the end of two
consecutive turns, he controls London and has control of
three Regions; see “Winning at the End of the Game” below
for control of Regions. The controlled Regions need not be
the same on each of the two turns.

17.2 Power Base Victory

ECONOMIC INFRASTRUCTURES
There are a number of key sections of the map, marked in
a pink wash, that are needed to maintain the morale and
finances of the two factions.. These sections are known
as Economic Infrastructures, and are counted for Victory
Purposes at the end of the game. In addition, if you have
no Economic Infrastructures under your control your
Recruitment is reduced (7.1.5).
Play Note: If you control no Economic Infrastructures, you cannot
play a Recruitment card, but you still get Recruits during the
Recruitment phase.

In the Power Base Phase of each turn both players count up
the number of friendly PC markers on the map. If the total is
less than the Power Base Number on the Turn Record Track
for that Game Turn then the game ends and the player (or
players) with insufficient Power Base have lost (both players
can lose under this rule).

Economic Infrastructures are controlled if you have your PC
marker in each Area of the Infrastructure and no Area of the
Infrastructure contains an Enemy Brigade.

Designer’s Note: The power base levels for the early turns are set to
reflect the determination on both sides to pursue the war.

Example: if Newcastle is Masked or Besieged it does not count as
belonging to either side.

Turn

Power Base #

1.

The Northumbrian Coalfield: Newcastle (Coal for
London)

2

Lead Mines: Sheffield (Munitions)

3.

Supplies for the City: A chain of controlled Areas
Northampton-Bedford (General trade)

4.

The Forest of Dean: Forest of Dean (Iron Industry)

5.

The Wine Trade: Bristol (the second city of the Kingdom and
home of the wine and slave trade)

Late 1642

14

Winter 1642

15

Early 1643

16

Late 1643

17

Winter 1643

18

Early 1644

19

6.

The Great Wen: London (General trade)

Late 1644

20

7.

Winter 1644

21

The Wool Road: A chain of controlled Areas SalisburyNewbury-Reading (Wool trade)

Early 1645

22

8.

The Weald: Reigate (Iron Industry)

Late 1645

23

9.

The Cornish Tin Mines: Truro (Tin)

Winter 1645

24

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

26

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

18.0

OPTIONAL RULES

These optional rules can be used if both players agree. They
improve the historical narrative, at the cost of increased
complexity.

18.1 Stout Cornish Men
Only the Royalist Brigades with the word “Cornish” on them
(Slanning and Grenvile’s) can be Recruited in the Truro
Recruitment Area. All other Royalist Southern Brigades
must be Recruited in the Bath Recruitment Area during the
Recruitment Phase.

18.2 Random Desertion Order
If you wish to change the effect of Desertion throw 1d6 before
taking Deserters, the number is the category at which both
Players start (rather than starting at Category 1 every time).
Treat a 6 as 1.

18.3 Manchester
To better capture Manchester’s role in the war, Parliamentary
Eastern Brigades named “Eastern Association” or “Ironsides”
may only be Recruited:

CREDITS
Design: Charles Vasey.
Developers: Joshua Buergel, Andy Lewis, Neil Randall
Playtesters: Gareth Simon, Ian Notter, Steve Crowley, Gary
Philips, Mike Reeves, Stan Buck, Paul Heldrup, Michael
Gouker, Steve Lampon, Ronald Mayer-Opificius, Joshua
Buergel, Neil Randall, Andrew Young, Robin Griller, Dirk
Heinz, Andy Daglish
Keeper of the King’s Pictures: Lee Brimmicombe-Wood.
Master of the King’s Artists: Garry Haggerty.
Figure Collection: Nick Farrell. (Photos by John Carroll.)
Thanks: Mike Siggins, Matthew Hayes, Olivier Clementin,
Guillaume Daudin, and three testers of an earlier version
who did not like the game and whose mention here is by
way of thanks for their effort (Nick Barker, Tony Ferrari, and
Tom Kassel). My thanks also go to Ian Wedge, Steve Crowley
and Joshus Buergel for the index; Ronald Mayer-Opificius
for permission to reproduce the portrait of Montrose; Steve
Carey for having a look at the rules and Ian Notter for tireless
advocacy.

•

In the Cambridge Recruitment Area,

Bibliography

•

with Lord Willoughby, or

•

with the Earl of Manchester if he is in the Eastern
Region; they must be placed directly on to his Command
Display.

The King’s War: C.V. Wedgwood.
All The King’s Armies: Stuart Reid
Leaders of The English Civil War: Toynbee and Ridsdill-Smith
1066 and all that: Sellars and Yeatman
Atlas of the Civil War: P.R. Newman
The Irish and British Wars 1637-1654: James Scott Wheeler
The Civil Wars of England: John Kenyon
The Royalist War Effort 1642-1646: Ronald Hutton

Where more than one such Brigade is Recruited they need
not be placed together.
Historical Note: Edward Montagu, Earl of Manchester
was commander of the army for one of the most important
Parliamentarian organizations—The Eastern Association.

18.4 The Laughter of the Court
If Newcastle is part of a stack that suffers a decisive defeat OR
there are no Royalist PCs in the North Region immediately
suspend play, remove the Newcastle counter from the game
and replace him with Langdale. Two Royalist Northern
Brigades (if available) are also permanently removed from
those available for Recruitment and/or from those in play
(Royalist choice).
Historical Note: Newcastle was so embarrassed by his defeat at
Marston Moor that he left England.

18.5 Lostwithiel
If the Earl of Essex suffers a Decisive defeat while four or
more Areas from London, his entire Army Disperses after he
suffers his losses.
Historical Note: By allowing himself to be trapped by the King
on the Fowey Peninsula Essex could have undone the effect of
Marston Moor.

INDEX
Main entries are in bold.
Ace in the Hole
Activating
Areas
Armies
Assaults
Assessment and
Sequestration
Attrition
Auto Victory
Battle
Battle Ratings
Besiege
Blockade Phase
Bombardment
Brigades
Brigades, placing
Brigades, removal
Campaign Phase
Card Deck
Cessation
Charles of Lorraine

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

5.5, 6.0
6.1, 9.1, 10.0, 13.0
3.0, 2.1, 5.1(2), 11.0
6.2, 8.4
3.0, 14.5
7.3.2
5.7, 12.3
8.2,10.4, 14.4, 17.1
9.4, 9.7.3, 10.0, 14.6
10.2, 14.6
7.1.4, 9.2, 14.0, 14.2, 14.4, 14.6, 15.3,
16.0
5.3, 5.6, 14.2
3.0, 14.2, 14.3
2.2, 3.0, 4.4(5), 6.2, 7.0, 7.1.1, 7.2.1,
8.3, 8.4, 10.2, 15.3
6.4, 7.1.7, 7.2.1
6.4, 7.1.7, 10.4
5.5, 11.1
4.1, 6.7, 6.8
6.6
6.6

27

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!
Combat Cards
Combat Value
Core Cards
Cornish
Covenanter
Decisive Victories
Desertion
Diplomatic Strength
Dispersal
Drawn Battles
Earl of Brentford
Early War
Economic Infrastructure
Evasion
Events
Fog of War
Fortresses
Garrisons
Generals
Grandees
Housekeeping Phase
Illegal Position
Immediate Assault
Interception
Irish
Isolation
King Abandons the Bishops
King Charles
Late War cards
Laugharne
Laughter of the Court
Leven
Lieutenant General
Limited Fortress
Local Notable
London Rising
London
Lone Generals
Lord General
Lorraine
Lostwithiel
Major Army
Major Campaign
Major Victory
Manchester
Mandatory Cards
Maritime lines
Mid War
Militia
Minor Campaign
Mountain lines
Movement
Movement Points
Naval Status
Nesting Card Draws
New Model Army
Newark Garrison
Newcastle

3.0, 6.4, 10.2
2.2, 10.2, 14.5
3.0, 4.0, 5.4, 6.3
see Stout Cornish Men
6.5, 6.6, 7.1.6, 8.3, 9.5, 10.1, 12.1
10.2, 10.6, 10.7
5.7, 12.0, 18.2
15.1
7.1.7, 10.1, 18.5
10.2
6.6
4.1
2.1, 6.6, 7.1.5, 17.3
9.7.3, 10.1
3.0, 6.4, 6.5, 6.6
16.0
2.1, 10.1, 11.1, 11.3, 14.0
13.0, 14.2, 14.4, 14.6
2.2, 4.4, 7.2.3, 8.0
7.3.1
5.1
9.5
see Assault
9.7
2.2, 7.1.6, 7.1.7, 12.1
see Political Isolation
6.6
8.4, 10.4, 17.1
4.0, 6.8
see Roland Laugharne
18.4
6.5, 8.4, 9.5
6.6, 8.4
see Fortresses
2.1, 2.2, 6.1, 7.2, 11.1, 11.3, 13.0,
14.1, 14.2, 14.3, 14.4, 14.5
6.6
15.1, 17.3
8.2, 12.2
8.4, 14.5
2.2, 6.6, 7.1.6, 8.3, 8.4, 9.5, 10.1,
10.6
18.5
6.2
3.0, 5.5, 6.1, 9.1, 11.1, 13.0
10.2, 10.7
18.3
4.1, 5.5, 6.4, 6.5
2.1, 9.3, 9.7.1, 10.1, 10.3, 11.3
4.0, 6.7
3.0, 7.1.1, 10.2, 15.3
see Major Campaign
2.1, 9.3, 9.7.2, 10.1
6.1, 9.0, 10.1, 14.2
9.2
4.4, 15.0
10.8
5.5, 6.5, 6.8, 7.1.1, 7.1.3, 14.3
6.6
8.4, 18.4

Operations
Parliament
Phases
Placing Brigades
by Event
Placing Generals
Political Control

6.1, 6.2, 9.1, 11.1, 13.0, 14.2
4.2, 7.3.2, 17.3
5.0

6.4
7.2.3, 7.3, 8.1
2.2, 3.0, 4.3, 5.2, 9.6, 10.5, 11.0, 13.0,
17.2
Political Isolation
5.1, 5.2, 11.3
Ports
2.1, 14.3
Power Base Victory
17.2
Powicke Bridge
7.1.2
Prince Rupert
6.6, 8.4, 9.5, 14.5
Queen Mary
6.6, 15.2
Raiding
13.0
Raising of the Standard
4.1, 6.5
Recruit
5.9, 6.1(1), 6.3, 6.5, 7.0, 7.1.7, 7.2
Recruitment Areas
2.1, 7.2, 7.2.1, 8.3(3)
Recruitment Card Box
6.3
Recruitment Card
7.1.5, 7.3, 7.3.1, 7.3.2, 8.1
Recruitment Phase
5.3, 6.5, 7.0, 7.1.2, 7.1.5, 7.1.7, 7.2,
7.2.1, 7.2.3, 8.1, 14.2, 15.3, 17.3,
18.1
Reforming Brigades
7.1.7
Region
2.1, 2.2, 7.1.7, 7.2.3
Regional Generals
2.2, 6.4, 6.5(3), 7.2.3, 7.3.1, 9.2,
12.2, 13.0
Regional Limits
7.2
Reinforcements Box
4.2, 6.1(4), 7.2.3, 7.2.4
Removal of Strategy Cards 6.4
Response Cards
6.4
Retreat
9.3, 10.3
Rivalries
9.5
Roads
2.1, 9.3
Roland Laugharne
6.6
Setup
4.2
Siege
see Besiege
Siege Train
6.5(3), 6.5(6), 7.1.4, 14.3, 14.4
Sir William Waller
6.5(1), 9.5
Spoils of Victory
10.5
Stout Cornish Men
18.1
Strategy Cards
6.0, 9.0, 10.7
Strategy Rating
2.2, 6.1(4), 6.2, 9.7.2
Subordination
3.0, 6.5(7), 7.2.3, 7.3.1, 8.0, 8.2, 8.4,
9.5, 9.7.1, 13.0, 14.2, 14.6
Supply Attrition
see Attrition
Supply Fortress
2.1, 11.3
Surrender
5.9, 8.2, 10.3, 10.4, 11.1, 14.2, 14.4,
14.5, 17.1
Surrender Value
2.1, 14.4
Turncoats
10.6
Turnham Green
6.6
Under Command
7.2
Unemployed Generals Box 6.5(7), 6.6, 7.1.7, 8.2, 10.1, 10.4,
12.2, 14.4
Victory Points
5.9, 17.3
Veterans
3.0, 4.4, 6.5(2), 7.1.1, 7.1.2
Wales
2.2, 6.6, 7.1.3, 17.3
Waller
see Sir William Waller
Winning
17.0

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

28

UNHAPPY KING CHARLES!

SEQUENCE OF PLAY
In the Housekeeping Phase:

EXCEPTIONS
• Forced removals of cards do not count toward the six
card plays required except for Mandatory Cards.

1.

•

The play of cards arising from victories does not count
toward the six card plays required.

•

If one player passes the other player can continue playing
and discarding until they also pass. Once a player has
passed, they cannot play or discard another card in that
Phase. A player who holds a Mandatory Strategy Card
(6.5) cannot pass until it is played. If a player runs out of
cards before playing six (due to Events), he simply passes
once his hand is empty.

Housekeeping Phase

2.

3.

Each player transfers all of his Generals from the
Unemployed Generals Box to the Reinforcements Box.
Any Generals on the Turn Record Track for the current
turn are moved into the Reinforcements Box as well.
Then each Player must place a PC marker in one neutral
Area (Parliament player first). The Area must be adjacent
to a friendly PC marker, but not adjacent to an enemy PC
marker, Local Notable or Army, and its change of control
must not be such as will cause Political Isolation (11.3)
for any other PC markers. Unled Brigades do not prevent
placement. If there is no available Area for a player, the
player skips his placement.
Then, if this is Late 1642 (i.e., Game Turn 1), Late 1643,
Late 1644 or Late 1645, the Parliament Player draws a
Naval Chit and adjusts the Naval Status (see 15.0).

Political Control Phase
(There is no Political Control Phase on the first Turn.)
In the Political Control Phase:
1.

Both players place PC markers in all non-Fortress Areas
that are occupied by one of their Armies or Local
Notables (11.2), if one of their PC markers is not already
there, and

2.

The players remove markers to reflect Political Isolation
(11.3).

Recruitment Phase
Beginning with the Parliament player, each side places
Recruited Brigades (7.0) and, if desired, Blockade & Siege
Markers (14.2).

Draw Strategy Cards Phase
(There is no Draw Strategy Cards Phase on the first Turn.)
This phase creates each player’s “hand” of cards for use in
the Campaign Phase of this Game Turn. First, each player
recovers his two Core Cards. The Parliament player then
deals four Strategy Cards from the Draw Deck to each player
one at a time, starting with the Royalist player. Each player’s
hand for the Game Turn will therefore consist of at least six
cards: four from the Draw Deck and the two Core Cards. In
addition he might hold “Ace in the Hole” cards (5.5, 6.2).

GOING FIRST
The Royalist Player chooses who plays the first card in a turn
until the New Model Army Event (6.5) has been played. At
that point the choice passes to the Parliament Player.
Exception: Where the player selected to go second does
not wish to do so, they can insist on going first if they have
a “Major Campaign” or “Minor Campaign” card, which must
then be their first card play.
ACE IN THE HOLE
All unplayed cards at the end of a Campaign Phase are placed
aside (face down) and can be played in later turns (see 6.0).
These are known as “Ace in the Hole” cards.

Blockade Phase
Armies with a “Blockade & Siege” marker (not just a Siege
marker) can now Bombard the Fortress on which the Marker
is placed (no Operations Card is required) (see 14.2 and
14.3).

Desertion and Supply Attrition
Phase
Check the Game- Turn track and inflict the number of
desertions required (12.0). Then remove Brigades that are
subject to Supply Attrition (12.3). Deserting Brigades and
those lost to Supply Attrition are available for Recruitment
next Game Turn.

Power Base Phase
Check for victory (17.0).

Tu r n E n d P h a s e

If there are insufficient cards to deal four to each player,
deal both players the same number of cards, with the
Royalist player getting the last card in case of an odd number
remaining.

If the game has not ended, recover the Core Cards for each
player, place any Strategy Cards used for Recruits into the
discard pile, and advance the Turn Marker one box on the
Turn Record Track. There are three ways in which the game
can end:

Campaign Phase

•

The game ends immediately if either player achieves an
Automatic Victory during the Power Base Phase.

•

The game ends immediately if King Charles surrenders
as the result of a Siege (8.2 and 14.4) or a Battle (10.4)

•

The game ends automatically in the Turn End Phase of
the winter 1645 Turn. Victory Points are then counted
according to 17.3 and a winner is declared.

The players alternately play or discard Strategy Cards one at
a time until both players have passed. A player can pass at
any time after they have played (including discarding) six
cards—combat cards and other response cards are included
in this total. They are forced to pass only when they have no
cards remaining.

© GMT Games LLC, 2008

</rulebook>
			
						                           
						               													<description>Unhappy King Charles! allows two players to decide whether Commons or Cavalier shall rule in England. Both seek to establish control over the country and of its economic structures. They seek not only to defeat their opponents in battle but also to seize control of the local government of England and Wales.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The game is based on We the People, Mark Herman's ingenious game on a later rebellion. As the organization of armies and states was often desultory, the cards do not provide a wide range of choices (as in Paths of Glory). The players in Unhappy King Charles! must make do with what they have. The three decks of cards - Early(1642-1643), Middle(1644) and Late (1645)- have been developed to give the correct feel for the early, middle and late war, based on storyboarding techniques. As befits a Civil War, there is treachery, bravery and stupidity in the events on the cards.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Unhappy King Charles! is played over eleven turns, each representing about four months. Brigades of troops are used to form Armies (defined Rule 3) or garrisons of fortresses (Rule 13). Only unled Brigades are on the map; the others are placed on the box of their General on the Command Displays. Generals move on the maps.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The Armies of Unhappy King Charles! are temporary massings of troops that have as much to do with feudal armies as modern revolutionaries. With inadequate supply and poor equipment it is not surprising that these armies suffer from continual desertion; and in using them you are going to have to ensure they wander the map collecting fresh recruits. Armies can be over 30,000 for a vital siege or battle or 3,000 tough cavalry under Prince Rupert or Black Tom Fairfax.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Movement activations are initiated via a numbered Ops Card, as in We the People, and are based on Army size. The smaller the Army the faster it can move. Movement across the map is by means of Areas joined by movement lines. Control of areas can change during movement if movement points are spent. Non-moving Armies can attempt interception, placing themselves in the path of the moving Army to cause Battle.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The game's basic combat unit is the Brigade, which comes in two types: Veterans (value 2) and militia (value 1). Usually militia units must be recruited before veterans of that Region. Each Region's Areas and Brigades use the same basic colour system. Fresh Brigades are received by Recruitment, which is usually limited to the unit's region of origin. Brigades lost in combat are not available for recruitment (though some Event Cards can bring them back); other losses are available.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Leader counters are either Generals (with a Strategic and Battle Rating) or Local Notables (Governors of fortresses). Generals can be Field Generals (who operate everywhere) or Regional Generals who can suffer disadvantages when outside their Region. Generals cannot transfer Brigades to other Generals (unless Event Cards require), Brigades remain with their original General until death, dispersal or desertion takes them. Local Notables can transfer Brigades to other friendly Generals.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Battles use the Combat Value of Brigades, General's Battle Ratings and Combat Cards to resolve combat. But before any Battle is fought one side can try to Evade (leave the Area) or Disperse (remove itself before combat). Losses in combat are not available for recruitment. Drawn and Decisive Victories will kill Veteran Brigades (if there are any) first. The loser must retreat and can suffer further losses if he retreats through enemy PC Markers. Major and Decisive Victories earn extra Cards.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Fortresses cover a wide range of locations. They are ranked by class and must be forced to Surrender by Siege or Event Card. Siege requires the attention of an Army for some time (most Fortresses will require more than one activation to capture). If attacked during that time the besieger can have to abandon the Siege. Assaults can be attempted (at a cost in losses).&amp;#10;&amp;#10;The game can be won by an Automatic Victory, by one side failing to control enough Areas, or at the end of the eleventh turn.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;For those players who like some counter-factuals a pack of would-be events is provided. Now players can use Dutch squadrons to blockade the King, summon the Duke of Lorraine, or cause a rising in London. As an Optional Rule, four events are drawn each game and shuffled into the middle and late decks.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Components&amp;#10;&amp;#10;     110 Cards&amp;#10;     One 34&amp;quot; x 22&amp;quot; colour paper game map&amp;#10;     Two full-color counter sheets&amp;#10;     One 28 Page Rulebook&amp;#10;     One 24 page Playbook&amp;#10;     Two 11' x 8.5' Player Aid Cards&amp;#10;     Two Six-sided dice&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;&amp;#10;Cover artwork inspired by Sir Anthony van Dyck (1599-1641)&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2008" />
						               				<minplayers value="2" />
						               				<maxplayers value="2" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="20">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="4" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="11" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="18" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="14" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="240" />
						               				<minplaytime value="240" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="240" />
						               				<minage value="0" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="8">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="4" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="12">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="2" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="8" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="2" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1102" value="Civil War" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="2725" value="Pike and Shot" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1019" value="Wargame" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2018" value="Campaign / Battle Card Driven" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2072" value="Dice Rolling" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2078" value="Point to Point Movement" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="14759" value="Country: England" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="9793" value="History: Age of Kings" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="33896" value="History: English Civil War" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamefamily" id="61979" value="Players: Two Player Only Games" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="156" value="Charles Vasey" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="2370" value="Lee Brimmicombe-Wood" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="4424" value="Garry Haggerty" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="71" value="Rodger B. MacGowan" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="52" value="GMT Games" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="703" />
			<average value="7.61847" />
			<bayesaverage value="6.0892" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="2211" bayesaverage="6.0892" />
																				<rank type="family" id="4664" name="wargames" friendlyname="War Game Rank" value="125" bayesaverage="7.10235" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.4028" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="1652" />
			<trading value="17" />
			<wanting value="140" />
			<wishing value="441" />
			<numcomments value="374" />
			<numweights value="124" />
			<averageweight value="3.3145" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>