<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><items termsofuse="https://boardgamegeek.com/xmlapi/termsofuse"><item type="boardgame" id="7571">
         <thumbnail>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/QRRaUH2GxP14kkP1fE-7mw__thumb/img/mRCe6eNU1367837hRXHWDa73pbk=/fit-in/200x150/filters:strip_icc()/pic1188010.jpg</thumbnail>
      <image>https://cf.geekdo-images.com/QRRaUH2GxP14kkP1fE-7mw__original/img/An_Ye5sAT97Fhlm3XT8FffpKmj4=/0x0/filters:format(jpeg)/pic1188010.jpg</image>
                                     				
				<name type="primary" sortindex="1" value="Winds of Plunder" />
				<rulebook>Buccaneering Adventures in the Golden Age of Piracy
Dangerous pirates are sailing on the high seas, ready to board your ship and steal victory!
Sail your own Pirate ship throughout the islands of the Caribbean, stopping at as many
ports of call as possible to enhance your reputation as a fierce Buccaneer. Battle with your
opponents, board their ships and take their weapons, crew, and provisions.
Finding treasures with Buried Treasure maps can earn you even more Victory Points, but
make sure the winds are blowing in the right direction! Learn to use the stronger EastWest winds to your advantage. Cooperate with other Pirates to have the wind blow where
you need it, then sail and use your Action Points wisely to seize plunder and victory!
TABLE OF CONTENTS
Introduction ..........................................................
Box Contents ........................................................
Game Board Overview ........................................
Preparation For Play ............................................
Icon Overview ......................................................
Phases of Each Round ..........................................
Wind Phase ..........................................................
Wind Direction : The Key To Movement ........................
Voting for Blackbeard's Tile and Wind Direction .............
Plundering Phase ..................................................
Action Points .........................................................
Sailing and the Port Arrival Sequence ...........................

2
2
3
3
4
4
4
4
4
5
5
5

Items and Their Advantages ........................................
Action Cards ...........................................................
Buried Treasure Cards ...............................................
Port Reputation Bonuses ...........................................

Game Round Completion ...................................
End-of-Game Bonuses .......................................
Tie Breakers .......................................................
Scoring Recap ....................................................
Variations ...........................................................
Credits ................................................................
Developer's Notes ..............................................

GMT Games
P.O. Box 1308
Hanford, CA 93232-1308 USA

www.GMTGames.com
© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

6
8
9
9
10
10
10
10
10
11
12

Winds of Plunder

2

INTRODUCTION
Peace has broken out between England, France and Spain.
The Monarchs of each country have sworn to enforce the
laws against piracy in the Caribbean. However, news travels
faster than navies. You and your fellow pirates still have time
to enrich yourselves before the fleets arrive, at the expense
of Caribbean natives and each other!
Each round, you will have an opportunity to manipulate the
Winds to your best advantage, then seek Plunder from both
the Caribbean ports and your opponents. Plunder translates
into Victory Points (VPs), and the player with the most VPs
after nine (9) game rounds is the winner.

Blackbeard tile: designates the player
who is entitled to break ties during the
Wind voting phase of each round. This
tile also designates who decides which
player may take his turn first during the
Plundering phase of each
round.
Victory Point (VP) tiles: each tile shows the
item(s) available when a player sails to a given
port, as well as the VPs that the player will score
for that port.
Compass tiles and
plastic arrows: attach one plastic
arrow to each compass tile. Players
will use these compass tiles to
secretly select their preferred
direction for the wind at the start of
each round.

There are many different ways to score VPs in Winds of
Plunder: acquiring VP tiles, earning Port Reputation
bonuses, boarding opponents, finding buried treasure, and –
at the end of the game – gaining bonuses for Weapons, Crew,
Provisions, unused Wind Cubes, and Advantage markers.

BOX CONTENTS
A complete copy of Winds of Plunder includes the following
materials:
•
•
•
•

This game booklet
A Quick Start rules sheet
A reference sheet
A tile sheet, containing:
• 1 Arrow marker
• 1 Game Round marker
• 1 Blackbeard tile
• 18 Victory Point tiles
• 5 Compass tiles
(1 per player)
• 5 plastic arrows
(1 per Compass tile)

• 5 sets of wood pieces
(red, green, blue, yellow,
orange), one per player,
each with:
• 30 cubes
• 1 scoring disk
• 1 ship block
• A deck of 55 cards:
• 40 Action
• 12 Buried Treasure
• 3 Advantage markers
• The game board

Cubes: each player receives 30 wooden cubes. Place
one of these cubes onto each of the four “0” spaces
associated with the tally areas flanking the map (see
the Quick Start graphic). Ten cubes form the player's
initial supply of Wind Cubes, described later in this guide. The
remaining 16 cubes are a reserve supply from which a player
may buy additional Wind Cubes. A player may only use cubes
of his own color.
Scoring disk: marks each player's position on the
Victory Point track.
Pirate ship: marks the port in which each player's
pirate is located during the game.
Action cards: drawn and played by spending
Action Points; explained later in ACTION
CARDS.
Buried Treasure cards:
drawn and played by
arriving in ports; also
explained later.

Game booklet: describes components in detail, along with
providing the rules and examples of play.
Quick Start sheet: provides a condensed form of the game rules
on one side and the diagram shown on the next page on the
other. Players who wish to start a game immediately can use the
Quick Start sheet as their primary rules source and refer back to
this booklet for clarifications as needed.
Reference sheet: on one side, provides a pictorial reference
illustrating key game concepts; on the other, lists the text
associated with all of the Action cards in English, German,
French and Italian. Make this available to all players.
Arrow marker: points to the prevailing wind
direction for a round.
Game Round marker: indicates
the current game round.

Advantage marker cards: also referred to as
Advantage markers. These are three special
cards, one for each of the items that enhance a
pirate ship. The top of each card shows the
specific ship item to which the advantage
applies. The middle of the card shows, in
graphic form, the advantage conferred by the
card. The bottom shows the value of the card
in Victory Points at the end of the game. A
player acquires an Advantage marker by
establishing a clear lead in the item shown. He
retains the card if his tally in that item is later
matched (tied) by another player, but discards it when his tally is
surpassed. Each individual Advantage marker is described in
detail in the ITEMS AND THEIR ADVANTAGES section.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder

3

GAME BOARD OVERVIEW
(setup information given in bold)
Place scoring
disks on “VP”
coin to start

Victory Point
scoring track

Place wind arrow on compass
facing North to start

Port
circles

Place game round marker
on “1” to start

End of game
item bonuses

Ship item icons
on VP tiles
(Weapons, Crew,
Provisions)
match tally areas

Pirate
ship board
tally areas

Thick lines in
tally areas
mark end-ofgame bonus
levels (1 VP
per thick line
crossed)

Place one cube
on zero (0) for
each of the
four tally areas

Port Reputation
bonuses
Victory
Point (VP)
tile spaces
(place one
VP tile on
each space)

Rotation Bar
(6 VP tile spaces)

Treasure Chest
matches icon on
front of Buried
Treasure card

Each different colored band is a separate map area

PREPARATION FOR PLAY
Place the game board in the center of the playing area.
Give Blackbeard’s tile to the player who has traveled the
farthest to play the game.
Each player chooses a color and receives a set of playing
pieces: compass, pirate ship, scoring disk, and 30 cubes.
Next, each player separates the 30 cubes as follows:

Booty is treated differently from
Weapons, Crew and Provisions.
Tally area for Booty is unique to reflect this.

Shuffle the 18 Victory Point (VP) tiles face down. Place a
VP tile in each box next to a port (12 total) on the board.
Place six on the Tile Rotation Bar provided in the lower left
corner of the game board. Turn all of the VP tiles face up.
Separate out the Buried Treasure cards for San Salvador,
Puerto Rico, Turks &amp; Caicos, Santo Domingo, and
Jamaica. These cards have their port names marked in grey
at the bottom. Shuffle these cards and deal one to each of the
players to mark their starting ports.

• four (4) marker cubes, one for each of the Pirate Ship
tally areas flanking the map on the game board,

Each player then places his ship marker on the game board,
next to the circle for the port indicated by his card.

• ten (10) cubes as the player's starting Wind Cubes, and

Reshuffle all 12 Buried Treasure cards and place them face
down near the board. Shuffle the Action deck and place it
face down next to the Buried Treasure cards.

• the remaining 16 cubes to form each player's reserve
supply.
Each player places his disk on the start space in the upper
left of the game board, and the four marker cubes on the “0”
spaces of each Pirate Ship tally area. Players then place their
ten Wind Cubes in plain view and the 16 reserve cubes off to
the side.

Place the Wind Arrow on the game board's compass rose
pointing North and the Round marker on the circle
representing Round 1.
Place the Advantage Markers next to the game board.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder

4

ICON OVERVIEW
A set of common symbols, or icons, appears on the game board as well as on various cards and the pictorial reference. The term
associated with each of these icons is given below. All of these terms will be discussed later in the rules.

Weapons

Crew

Provisions

Buried Treasure
(unscored
Treasure card)

PHASES OF EACH ROUND
Each round has two distinct phases:
1) Wind voting: Players “vote” for the right to choose who
sails first and to set the wind in a favorable direction.

Booty
(scored
Treasure card)

Victory Point
(VP)

Action Point

Port

• If the winds are blowing North (South), you may only
move North (South), either within the same area where
you are presently located or an adjacent area in either
direction. Your destination must be North (South) of
where you began your move.
EXAMPLE: a ship in Puerto Rico may move South with
the wind to either Jamaica, Santo Domingo, Guadeloupe, Barbados, or Trinidad. It may not move to Belize
as this port is neither in the same area as nor an adjacent
area to the one the ship currently occupies.

2) Plundering: Each player, in clockwise turn order, uses
his allotted Action Points and sails to gain Plunder.

WIND PHASE
WIND DIRECTION : THE KEY TO MOVEMENT

VOTING FOR BLACKBEARD'S TILE AND WIND DIRECTION

Prior to a description of the voting process, a few words
concerning wind direction and its effect on ship movement
are necessary.

Each player takes his compass tile and secretly sets the arrow
to his choice of wind direction (North, East, South, or West).
All players MUST then place their compass tiles face down.

As shown on the game board overview, the Caribbean is
divided into four sections, alternating dark and light. These
sections are referred to simply as “areas” of the map for
purposes of movement and for Port Reputation Bonus
scoring (described later in the section labeled PORT
REPUTATION BONUSES).

All players turn their compass tiles face up at the same time,
and keep them next to the board. Note for which direction
each player has voted.

Each area contains three ports. A port will always be one of
four colors, with each color matching one specific area.
The East and West winds are stronger than the North and
South winds. East and West winds allow a greater range
of movement, but also require players to change areas.
Ship movement will depend upon the direction of the wind.
Ships must move from one port to another in the direction
shown by the Wind Arrow on the board's compass rose (see
VOTING FOR BLACKBEARD'S TILE AND WIND
DIRECTION) or as modified by using a Gust of Wind (see
ACTION POINTS). In addition:
• If the winds are blowing East (West), you must move one
or two areas to the East (West). You may not remain in
the same area. A Gust of Wind may be used to move an
extra area East (West).
EXAMPLE: a ship in Puerto Rico may move West to
either San Salvadore, Nassau, Jamaica, Havana,
Cozumel or Belize. It may not move with the West wind to
either Santo Domingo or Turks &amp; Caicos as these ports
are in the same area as Puerto Rico.

Players then secretly take the Wind Cubes they wish to vote
with and place them in their closed fists. Everyone must
participate, even if they do not intend to vote any Wind
Cubes. All players reveal the contents of their hands at the
same time.
Resolve ownership of Blackbeard’s tile first. If one player
votes with more cubes than any other, that player receives
Blackbeard’s tile. If there is a tie, the person currently
holding Blackbeard's tile decides which of the tied players
gets it. Of course, if the current holder of the Blackbeard tile
is one of the tied players, he may keep the tile himself.
Next, treat each cube as a vote for the same wind direction as
shown on the player’s compass. Place the wind Arrow on the
game board compass pointing to the direction that receives
the most votes. If there is a tie between two or more
directions, the new owner of Blackbeard's tile chooses
between the tied directions.
All cubes that were used for voting are discarded back to the
player's reserve supply. The players also return their
remaining unused cubes to plain sight in front of them.
After establishing the wind direction for this turn, the player
holding Blackbeard's tile may either go first or choose
another player to go first.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder

5

PLUNDERING PHASE

SUMMARY OF PORT ARRIVAL SEQUENCE

Starting with the player selected by the Blackbeard tile's
holder, each player in clockwise order takes a turn at
plundering. A player's plundering phase consists of sailing
once and spending 3 Action Points.

1) Set aside any Action cards you have in your hand, face
down, and move your ship to the new port.

Players may spend Action Points or sail in any order. You
need not spend all of your Action Points before sailing.
EXAMPLES: On his turn, Bonnet spends one Action Point,
sails, and spends his two remaining Action Points. Next,
“Calico Jack” spends all of his Action Points, then sails.
Finally, “Black Sam” sails, then spends all his Action Points.

Flip your compass tile over when you are done plundering.
This serves as a reminder that you have taken your turn.

2) Take the VP tile, adjust ship contents in the appropriate
tally areas and/or take a Buried Treasure Card (if
applicable), score VPs for the port, and replace the VP
tile through the Tile Rotation Bar.
3) In any order:
• Board and plunder an opponent, if possible.
• Locate buried treasure and score a map, if applicable.
4) Gain Reputation, if eligible.
5) Score a Port Reputation bonus, if applicable.
6) Pick up your Action cards, if any.

ACTION POINTS

DETAILS OF PORT ARRIVAL SEQUENCE

Action Points may be spent as follows:

Details for the above Port Arrival Sequence are as follows:

• Take an Action card (costs 1 Action Point).

1) You may NOT play any Action cards during the Port
Arrival Sequence. Set aside your Action cards.

• Play an Action card (costs 1 Action Point).
• Add 2 cubes from your reserve to your Wind Cube
supply (costs 1 Action Point).
• Add 5 cubes as above (costs 2 Action Points).
• Add 9 cubes as above (costs 3 Action Points).
• Gust of Wind in any direction (costs 3 Action Points):
A Gust of Wind allows the player to either treat the Wind
as if it was blowing in a different direction, or to add to the
strength of an East (West) wind to move one extra area
East (West) across the board, before sailing to a new port.
Gust of Wind only applies to a single ship movement.
NOTE: a Gust of Wind does not change the wind arrow.
It only affects movement for the player who employs it.

SAILING AND THE PORT ARRIVAL SEQUENCE
Sailing in and of itself does not cost any Action Points.
However, unless a player plays an Action card permitting
him to do otherwise, he may only sail once during his turn.

Move your ship in accordance with the current direction
of the Wind – either as-is or as altered by your use of a
Gust of Wind – to the desired port.
2) On arrival, take the VP tile. Add any Crew, Provisions and/
or Weapons indicated to the ship’s storage hold by moving
the appropriate tally marker up one space. If the VP tile
indicates you should take a Buried Treasure card, draw one.
However, if there are
no Treasure cards
Item(s) available
in port
available, you do not
get one. Also, if
there is no room in a
Victory Points for
scoring port
tally area for the
corresponding new
item (i.e., you already have a total of nine of the items in
question), that item is lost.
NOTE: If you take the lead in Crew, Weapons, or Provisions,
you immediately become entitled to the corresponding
Advantage marker; i.e., Largest Crew, Most Weapons, or
Most Provisions. For more details on these items see the
next section, ITEMS AND THEIR ADVANTAGES.

Ships move with the wind, as described in the section,
WIND DIRECTION: THE KEY TO MOVEMENT.
A player MUST sail his ship during his turn unless it is wind
locked; i.e., unable to legally sail to another port with the
wind. If a player's ship is wind locked, he may either spend
three Action Points on a Gust of Wind or he may remain in
his current port.
EXAMPLE: You are in Guadeloupe and the wind is East.
Due to the requirement that your ship must move one or two
areas to the east with an East wind, there is no port to which
you may legally sail. Your ship is wind locked.

When you elect to sail to a new port, you will follow a
special list of activities. These activities are referred to as the
Port Arrival Sequence.

AFTER adjusting the ship's storage tally areas, award
Victory Points for the port. Advance your VP marker as
many spaces as indicated by the number on the VP tile. If
you have the Advantage marker for the Most Provisions,
you also score a bonus of 1 VP (as indicated on that
Advantage marker) at this time.
Once you have scored the Victory Points, pick up the VP
tile. Place it at the left end of the VP tile Rotation Bar
(i.e., the row near the bottom of the board). Slide the tiles
on the Bar to the right, and place the right-most tile in the
vacant space beside the port.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder

6

3) Aside from scoring the VP tile, pirates have other
potential opportunities for Plunder in a new port; namely,
boarding opponents and locating buried treasure.
Boarding and locating buried treasure may be done in
any order.
a)

To show this – if you have not already done so for this
port, and if you have at least one cube in your reserve
supply – you MUST take a cube from your reserve (not
one of your Wind Cubes!) and place it on the port circle.
EXAMPLE: Bonnet and “Calico Jack” both have their
ships in Trinidad. Bonnet has two Weapons, and “Calico
Jack” has one. “Black Bart” has his ship in Barbados,
and has two Weapons plus the MOST WEAPONS marker.
“Black Sam” has his ship in Guadeloupe, and has no
Weapons. Hornigold has his ship in Puerto Rico with one
Weapon. If Bonnet sails anywhere at this time, including
Barbados, he gains reputation in the new port. If
Hornigold sails anywhere other than Barbados, he is also
entitled to gain reputation; however, if he sails to
Barbados, he is not.

Boarding. (Optional)
You may board one opponent if
• that player's ship is in the same port that you have
moved to, and
• you have the stronger ship; i.e., you either have
more weapons than that opponent, or you hold the
Most Weapons marker.
You may take either two (2) VPs or any one (1) ship
item (i.e., Weapons, Crew or Provisions) from the
player you boarded. Adjust the storage areas on
both ships. If your opponent falls below any other
player in that item, he must discard that item's
Advantage marker. Again, if you take the lead in a
ship item you may immediately claim the
corresponding Advantage marker.
If there is more than one ship in the port with fewer
weapons, you may only board one opponent, but
you may choose which ship to board.

b)

Locate Buried Treasure.
If you have a Treasure Card for this port, turn it face
up. Advance your Booty marker up one space, if
there is room remaining to do so, then score the
number of VP indicated by the rung your marker
occupies.

Reputation can never be lost or stolen. Once a cube has
been placed in this manner, it remains at the port for the
remainder of the game.
5) If you have just established a reputation for the third port
in an area, score the appropriate Port Bonus for that area.
See the section on PORT BONUSES for the scores
awarded and for an example.
6) Finally, take your Action cards back into your hand. You
have completed the Port Arrival Sequence.

ITEMS AND THEIR ADVANTAGES
As noted in SAILING AND THE PORT ARRIVAL
SEQUENCE, several other items may be found in each
port: Weapons, Crew, Provisions, and Buried Treasure
Cards. At the start of the game, players start with their
markers at zero (0) in each item.
Each item confers its own distinct advantages, as described
below:

EXAMPLE: Hornigold sails to Jamaica and scores
his first Treasure Card. He moves his Booty marker
up one slot from “0” to the “2 VP” rung, and scores
two VP.

Once the Treasure has been scored, return the used card
face down to the bottom of the Treasure Card deck.
For more details on Treasure Cards, see the separate
section on BURIED TREASURE CARDS.
4) Next, a pirate gains Reputation amongst the port's
inhabitants, becoming both respected and feared. If you
sail into an unoccupied port, you automatically establish
your reputation in that port. Similarly, if you sail into a
port occupied by one or more other players, and have at
least as many Weapons as ANY other ship in that port,
you also gain reputation.
NOTE: the Most Weapons marker can not be used to
block a player from gaining Reputation. It does NOT act
as a tiebreaker for Reputation purposes.

WEAPONS: These are useful in
boarding other players' ships, and in
establishing one's Reputation as a
fierce Buccaneer.
For boarding, if a player has MORE Weapons than an
opponent – even if he does not have the most Weapons – and
sails to the port that opponent currently occupies, he may
board his ship. He may do so even if a different ship in that
port has more Weapons.
As for gaining reputation, if a player sails into an occupied
port and has at least as many Weapons as ANY other
opponent in that port (or into an unoccupied port regardless
of how many Weapons he has), he gains reputation there.
Finally, the player with the most Weapons takes the Most
Weapons Advantage marker. This marker acts as a special
tiebreaker for boarding when sailing to a different port,
allowing the person with the Most Weapons marker to
board any opponent.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder

CREW: The player with the most Crew takes
the Largest Crew Advantage marker. Having
this marker allows him to use a bonus Action
Point at the end of his turn. That player must
use all of his other Action Points and sail
before using this bonus. As a result, one
implication players need to be aware of is that
the bonus Action Point may not be combined
with other actions in a player's turn to collect
extra Wind Cubes or to use a Gust of Wind.
EXAMPLE 1: “Calico Jack” plays an Action card with his
second Action Point that allows him to take the lead in Crew.
He decides to collect Wind Cubes at the end of his turn.
However, he is not allowed to take the bonus action until he
has completed his regular turn. He may collect two cubes
with his third Action Point and another two on his bonus
Action Point for a total of four, but he cannot combine the
two points to take five cubes.
EXAMPLE 2: ”Black Bart” has the lead in Crew coming
into his turn. He wishes to sail against the wind. He may
spend his original three Action Points on a Gust of Wind,
sail, and take his bonus action. However, he cannot use an
Action Point and then combine his last two Action Points with
the bonus one to create a Gust of Wind.

PROVISIONS: The player with the
most Provisions takes the Most
Provisions Advantage marker. Having
this marker allows him to score an extra
VP each time he scores VP for landing
in a port.
BURIED TREASURE: The presence of
this item in a port allows a player to take a
Buried Treasure card (left). Both the Port
Arrival Sequence and a separate section,
BURIED TREASURE CARDS, explain
how Buried Treasure
cards are turned into
Booty (right) and scored. No special
advantages are conferred for having
either the most unscored Treasure cards
or the most Booty.
A player may only use an advantage if he has it at the time
required for its use.
EXAMPLE 1: Hornigold sails to a new port and completes
the Port Arrival Sequence. Next, he plays a “Buy Provisions”
Action card. Using this card places him in the lead for
Provisions. He takes the Most Provisions Advantage marker.
But since he did not have the advantage at the time required
in SAILING TO A PORT, he does NOT go back and add a VP
for the port scored earlier in his turn.

7

EXAMPLE 2: “Calico Jack” sails to the port that Hornigold
currently occupies, and starts his own Port Arrival Sequence.
At the time of his arrival, “Calico Jack” only has as many
Weapons as Hornigold. After taking the VP tile and adjusting
his ship, however, he finds that he has more Weapons than
Hornigold. Since boarding follows taking the VP tile,
“Calico Jack” may now board Hornigold's ship.

Strictly speaking, advantages should be used and Buried
Treasure cards should be played at the proper points in a
player's turn. Players may choose to offer each other some
flexibility in this matter. However, if a player forgets to use
an advantage (in Weapons, Crew or Provisions), or neglects
to play a Buried Treasure card, he cannot go back and use it
once the next player begins his turn.
As soon as a player gains the clear lead in Weapons, Crew,
or Provisions (i.e., is not tied for the lead), he immediately
takes the corresponding Advantage marker card for that
item. He places this Advantage marker face up in front of
him. This Advantage remains with the player so long as he
remains at least tied for the lead. Once he falls behind any
opponent in that item, he must immediately discard the
corresponding marker.
EXAMPLE 1: Bonnet has 5 Provisions and the Most
Provisions marker, “Black Bart” has 4 Provisions, and
“Calico Jack” has 3 Provisions. “Calico Jack” plays a
Swindle card on Bonnet, trading one of his Weapons for a
Provision. This simultaneously brings Bonnet's count in
Provisions down to 4 and “Calico Jack's” up to 4. Since no
one exceeds Bonnet's tally in Provisions, he is entitled to keep
the Most Provisions marker.
EXAMPLE 2: This time, Bonnet only has 4 Provisions and
the Most Provisions marker, “Black Bart” has 4 Provisions,
and “Calico Jack” has 3 Provisions. Again, “Calico Jack”
plays a Swindle card on Bonnet, trading one of his Weapons
for a Provision. This simultaneously brings Bonnet's count in
Provisions down to 3 and “Calico Jack's” up to 4. Since
another player now exceeds Bonnet's tally in Provisions, he
must discard the Most Provisions marker. However, neither
“Calico Jack” nor “Black Bart” is in the undisputed lead for
Provisions, so neither may claim that marker at this time.

It is possible for more than one player to obtain and use the
same advantage on the same game round.
Possession of each Advantage marker at the end of the game
is worth 2 VP. This is indicated both on the bottom of each
Advantage marker and in the “End Game VPs” block on the
game board.
NOTE: Weapons, Crew and Provisions share a common
trait. These items may be stolen from another player or
otherwise removed from his tally areas. In contrast, the Booty
tally area serves to indicate the value of the last Buried
Treasure Card a player had scored. As such, Booty can not
be stolen. In token of this, the tally areas for shipboard items
are presented in a different color than for Booty.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder

8

ACTION CARDS
Each Action card requires one Action Point to draw and a
separate Action Point to play.
You may play an Action Card at any point in your turn, except
during the Port Arrival Sequence when sailing to a port.
Discard an Action card immediately after playing it unless
the card instructs you to do otherwise. When the Action card
deck is empty, shuffle the discards to refresh the deck.
The rules do not impose a limit on the number of Action
cards you may keep in your hand. However, there may be
cards that force you to discard to a given limit.
The name, count, and description of each card in the Action
deck is given below.
BUY PROVISIONS (3) – You may buy one (and only
one) Provision for two VPs by playing this card, or gain
one Provision for FREE if your ship is currently in one of
the specified ports. Your Provisions tally marker must be
below nine to play this card. Adjust the appropriate ship
board tally area accordingly.
BUY WEAPONS (3) – You may buy one (and only one)
Weapon for two VPs by playing this card, or gain one
Weapon for FREE if your ship is currently in one of the
specified ports. Your Weapons tally marker must be below
nine to play this card. Adjust the appropriate ship board
tally area accordingly.
HEAVE, YE SCURVY DOGS! (2) – If you have already
sailed this turn and each of your opponents still has more
VP than you do, you may pay 1 Crew to sail a second
time. You must sail as indicated by the wind compass,
unless you have already spent the Action Points to employ
a Gust of Wind prior to playing this card. Also, you must
have at least one Crew in order to play this card. You may
play only one HEAVE card in your turn.
EXAMPLE 1: The wind is blowing East. You are in Nassau,
and are 1 Crew behind the player with the Largest Crew
marker. You decide to sail to Puerto Rico, which has a tile for
3VP plus a Crew. At this point you find that your VP score is
still lower than each of your opponents, so you may spend a
Crew and play the HEAVE card this round to sail a second
time. However, unless you have the PUT THE CREW TO
THE TEST card to gain extra actions, you must either use
HEAVE to sail with the wind or forgo using HEAVE this
round. Otherwise, you will not have enough Action Points to
employ a Gust of Wind and play the HEAVE card.
EXAMPLE 2: Same situation as above, except that you
either have the Largest Crew marker or would acquire it by
sailing to Puerto Rico. You may spend three Action Points on
a Gust of Wind, then use the Largest Crew bonus Action
Point to play HEAVE and sail whichever direction you desire.

EXAMPLE 3: Same situation as EXAMPLE 2, except that
you spend three Action Points to sail South to Jamaica which
has a tile for 4 VP plus 1 Crew. You can use the Largest Crew
bonus Action Point to play HEAVE, but this time you must
sail with the wind (East).

HIRE CREW (3) – You may hire one (and only one) Crew
for two VPs by playing this card, or gain one Crew for
FREE if your ship is currently in one of the specified
ports. Your Crew tally marker must be below nine to play
this card. Adjust the appropriate ship board tally area
accordingly.
INTRIGUE! (3) – Play this card to switch any two VP
tiles (not scoring disks!) on the board. These tiles may
either be next to a port or on the Rotation Bar.
MISFIRE! (2) – Choose any opponent, regardless of
whether or not your ships share the same port. That
opponent loses one Weapon from the appropriate ship
board tally area.
MUTINY! (2) – Choose any opponent, regardless of
whether or not your ships share the same port. That
opponent loses one Crew from the appropriate ship board
tally area.
PUT THE CREW TO THE TEST! (3) – Spend one
Action Point as normal to play this card, pay one Crew,
and receive an additional three Action Points on your turn.
You must have at least one Crew in order to play this card.
You may play only one PUT THE CREW TO THE TEST
card in your turn.
EXAMPLE: You have three Action Points and 1 Crew. You
play PUT THE CREW TO THE TEST as your first Action.
You reduce your Crew from 1 to 0, and now have five Action
Points ((3-1)+3) remaining.

RATS! (2) – Choose any opponent, regardless of whether
or not your ships share the same port. That opponent loses
one Provision from the appropriate ship board tally area.
SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS! (3) – Play the card
face up to the table in front of you. Do not advance your
Weapons count in your tally area. However, for the
remainder of this Game Round, add two to the number of
your Weapons shown in that tally area to determine your
true Weapons count. This card is cumulative; i.e., if you
have two such cards in play, add four to that number
determine your Weapons count.
If this card causes you to gain the lead in Weapons, take
the Most Weapons marker. At the end of the round, place
the SECRET CACHE card in the discard pile and, if
necessary, discard the Most Weapons marker.
EXAMPLE: You have 4 Weapons, “Black Sam” has
7 Weapons plus the Most Weapons marker, and “Calico

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder
Jack” has 7 Weapons. You play two SECRET CACHE OF
WEAPONS cards in front of you. This temporarily gives you
8 Weapons, allowing you to take the Most Weapons marker.
In this particular round, no one acquires any Weapons
during their turn. At the end of the round, you discard the
SECRET CACHE cards and drop back down to 4 Weapons.
Since you are no longer in the lead for Weapons, you must
discard the Most Weapons marker. Further, since “Black
Sam” and “Calico Jack” are still tied at 7, neither of them
may take it.

STORM! (3) – This card forces each of your opponents
with more than two Action cards in his hand to discard
down to two Action cards, regardless of whether or not
your ships share the same port. Neither Treasure cards nor
any cards in play in front of a player (e.g., SECRET
CACHE OF WEAPONS) count against this Action card
limit.
EXAMPLE: You have five Action cards in your hand. One of
your opponents has three Action cards in hand plus a
Treasure card face down on the table. Another has two
Action cards in hand plus a SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS
cards in play on the table. You play a STORM card. You need
not discard. Your opponent with two cards in hand need not
discard. Your opponent with three Action cards in hand will
need to get rid of one. The cards on the table remain in place.

SWINDLE! (4) – This card allows you to trade any one
item in your storage area for any one item on any
opponent’s ship, regardless of whether or not your ships
share the same port. Tradable items only include Weapons,
Crew and Provisions. Adjust both players' tallies on the
appropriate ship board tally areas.
TAVERN BRAWL! (3) – Place this card in front of any
opponent that does not already have a TAVERN BRAWL
card in front of them, regardless of whether or not your
ships share the same port. At the start of his turn, that
player must choose to lose either 2 Action Points or 2 VP.
If the player does not have 2 VP, then he must lose 2
Action Points. Discard this card after the player makes his
decision and suffers the chosen effect.
NOTE: this card only takes effect at the start of that
player's next turn. If you play it on Round 9 on an
opponent that has already taken his turn, the game will
end before this card affects its target.

TREACHERY! (4) – Steal half the Wind Cubes (up to
five) held by any opponent, rounded down, regardless of
whether or not your ships share the same port. You may
only steal the Wind Cubes in play by your opponent; i.e.,
you may not steal reserve cubes, reputation markers, or
item markers. Exchange these cubes for cubes of your own
color. If you do not have enough cubes of your color, you
may only steal as many as you have remaining in your
reserve supply.

9

EXAMPLE: You play TREACHERY on an opponent with 9
Wind Cubes. You would normally be entitled to steal 4 cubes.
However, you only have three cubes in your reserve at this
time. You take three from your reserve and your opponent
puts three back into his reserve.

BURIED TREASURE CARDS
BURIED TREASURE (12, one for each port) – When you
land on a port with a Buried Treasure icon on the VP tile,
draw a Buried Treasure card and place it face down in front
of you. Players may have more than one Buried Treasure
card in front of them at any one time, and may look at their
Buried Treasure card(s) at any time.
When you are in a port matching that on one of your Buried
Treasure cards (see SAILING TO A PORT) – even if it is a
card you just drew – turn that card face up. Advance your
Booty tally marker one space (if possible), and score the
number of VP indicated by his marker. Turning a Treasure
card face up does NOT cost an Action Point.
NOTE: Be sure to advance your Booty marker in the
appropriate tally area BEFORE scoring the Treasure card.
Return the card, face down, to the bottom of the Buried
Treasure card deck.

PORT REPUTATION BONUSES
The chart on the right hand side of the game board illustrates
the Port Reputation Bonus chart. Players earn bonuses by
establishing their reputation in each of the three ports within
an area of the map. Marker cubes placed during the Port
Arrival Sequence allow the players to tell when a bonus has
been earned.
Port Reputation Bonuses are scored independently for each
of the four areas of the map.
• The first player to establish his reputation in all three
ports in any area scores 7 VPs.
• Second player to establish his reputation in all three ports
for that same area scores 5 VPs.
• Third player to establish his reputation in all three ports
for that area scores 3 VPs.
• Fourth player to establish his reputation in tall three ports
for that area scores 2 VPs.
• Fifth player to establish his reputation in all three ports
for that area scores 1 VP.
EXAMPLE: You have already established your reputation in
Barbados and Guadeloupe. You sail to Trinidad, establish
your reputation there, and complete the area. Two other
players already have reputation markers in all three of these
ports, making you the third player to complete this area. You
thus score 3 VPs as a Port Reputation Bonus.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

Winds of Plunder

10

GAME ROUND COMPLETION

SCORING RECAP

Advance the Game Round marker to the next higher number,
after completing both phases of a round: voting to settle the
Winds AND having each player take his opportunity to
Plunder.

There are five different ways to score Victory Points in
Winds of Plunder:

The game ends after nine (9) full rounds have been completed.

• VP tiles.
• Port Reputation bonuses.
• Finding Buried Treasure.

END-OF-GAME BONUSES

• Boarding opponents.

The end-of-game bonuses are indicated in graphic form in
the upper right hand corner of the map area.

• End of game bonuses for Weapons, Crew, Provisions,
Wind Cubes, and Advantage markers.

• WIND CUBES: Score one bonus VP for every three (3)
Wind Cubes in your main supply (i.e., not including your
reserve cubes).
• WEAPONS: Score one VP for every three (3) Weapons
you have in the Weapons tally area.
• CREW: Score one VP for every two (2) Crew.
• PROVISIONS: Score one VP for each Provision.
• ADVANTAGE MARKERS: Score two VP for each
Advantage marker that you hold at the end of the game This
is indicated both on the game board and on each marker.
NOTE: This applies even if the Advantage marker is
acquired at the end of the game, such as by an opponent's
discard of a played SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS
card at the end of Round 9.

• Buried Treasure cards that have not been scored are
worthless!!!
Leftover cubes, Weapons, and Crew do not accrue bonus
points. For example, a player with eight Wind Cubes at the
end of the game will only score two (2) VP.
The player with the highest Victory Point total wins!

TIE BREAKERS
In the event of a tie, the players who are tied for the lead
determine the winner using a set of tie breakers. These may
also be used in tournament play to settle other tied finish
positions. In order of precedence, the tie breakers are:
• Possession of Blackbeard's Tile.

VARIATIONS
Players who have gained experience with the standard game
may wish to incorporate one or more of the variations given
below. These options change the strategies players will need
to employ and/or the game's mechanics.
The variations below may also place inexperienced players
at a greater disadvantage against experienced opponents.
Consequently, these variants are not recommended for use
when there are players unfamiliar with the standard rules.
a) Play SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS in reaction to
Boarding: Players who desire to add a greater defensive
element may allow the SECRET CACHE OF
WEAPONS card to be played in its normal manner, and
to be played reactively. In the latter case, this card may
be played at no cost, either in terms of Action Points or
other items, if
• an opponent declares the intent to board your ship,
AND
• you can surpass that player's Weapons count with one
or more SECRET CACHE card(s) if that opponent
holds the Most Weapons marker, or tie or surpass that
player's count if he does not hold it.
When a player who was originally targeted for boarding
reacts in this manner, that player will have at least as
many Weapons as the boarder. In such an event, the
boarding attempt fails and the plundering player may not
choose a new target.
A player who uses one or more SECRET CACHE OF
WEAPONS card(s) to block a boarding attempt places
the card(s) face up in front of him. SECRET CACHE
cards played in this manner stay in play until the end of
the round OR that player's next turn, whichever comes
first.

• Most Advantage markers.
• The Most Weapons Advantage marker.
• The Largest Crew Advantage marker.
• Most unused Action cards.
• For friendly play, if there is still a tie, the game is tied. For
tournament play where a final tie breaker is absolutely
required, the player closest in clockwise order from the
player with Blackbeard's Tile wins the tie breaker.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

EXAMPLE 1: “Calico Jack” and Hornigold have ships
in Puerto Rico. Each of them has 2 Weapons. Bonnet is in
Belize, and has 5 Weapons. Bonnet sails to Puerto Rico,
sets his Action cards aside, and names “Calico Jack” as

Winds of Plunder
the target of his boarding attempt. “Calico Jack” plays
two SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS cards for free in
reaction to the boarding, bringing him to 4 Weapons.
Now “Calico Jack” has 6 Weapons to Bonnet's 5. The
boarding attempt fails. Bonnet may not board Hornigold.
“Calico Jack's” two SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS
cards remain in play until the end of the round or the start
of his next turn, whichever comes first.
EXAMPLE 2: Again, “Calico Jack” and Hornigold have
ships in Puerto Rico. Each of them has 2 Weapons.
Bonnet is in Belize, and has 4 Weapons plus the Most
Weapons marker. Prior to sailing, Bonnet uses an Action
Point and plays SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS. This
brings his effective Weapons count to 6. Now Bonnet sails
to Puerto Rico, sets his Action cards aside, and names
“Calico Jack” as the target of his boarding attempt.
“Calico Jack” has two SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS
cards. However, since their use would only bring his
weapons count to 6, AND since Bonnet has the Most
Weapons marker, the tie is insufficient to stop the
boarding attempt. “Calico Jack” may not play his cards
reactively. Bonnet successfully boards “Calico Jack's” ship.

Using SECRET CACHE OF WEAPONS in this manner
changes the mechanics of play for this particular Action
card, and may disrupt a player's expectations for plunder.

11

CREDITS
Game Design: Alan Newman
Game Developer: Tony Nardo
Playtesting: Ward Ahders, Chris Bernardo, John
Bernardo, Stephen Bernardo, Charley Burkhart,
Stephane Brochu, Joe Casadonte, Ron Cholewa,
Samantha Cholewa, Mark Delano, John Dukehart,
Emily Durbin, Michael Emmons, Mike Frailer,
Martin Gallo, Renee Gearinger, Norbert Gershkovich,
Marty Goldberger, Eric Heilman, Timo Heiber,
Scott Henshaw, Jonathan Hobill, Tim Isakson,
James James, Steve Kurzban, Carl Lamy, Eugene
Lee, Jason Levine, Herb Levy, Kevin Maroney,
John McMillan, Teresa Nardo, Andrea Nawratil,
Brian Newman, Patrick O'Brien, John Palagyi,
Dave Rapp, Nick Sauer, Stan Spector, Sean Tate,
Dale Yu
Art Director: Rodger B. MacGowan

b) Make Advantage markers easier to lose: Instead of
allowing a player to retain an Advantage marker even
when tied for the lead in that item, force the player to
discard the marker when his tally is tied or surpassed by
any opponent. This change increases the chances that a
single player can force an opponent to lose an Advantage
marker.

Production Coordinator: Tony Curtis

c) Forbid GUST OF WIND: Players who desire an
additional degree of competition over control of the wind
may forbid the spending of Action Points to employ a
Gust of Wind. This change will lead to a greater
possibility of wind lock, and thus increases the emphasis
on controlling the wind. It may also force occasions
where a player is unable to sail – and therefore score – in
his turn.

Tiles and Other Component Illustrations:
Mike Lemick, Mark Simonitch, Rodger B.
MacGowan

d) Restrict North-South movement to one area; restrict
Round 1 Wind votes to East-West: Another means to
increase the importance of controlling the wind is to
specify that ships moving North (or South) with the wind
must stay inside the area they started in. For example, a
ship in Havana can only use a South wind to sail to
Cozumel or Belize, and can not use a North wind to sail
anywhere. As with the prior option of removing the Gust
of Wind, this change will lead to a greater possibility of
wind lock. Wind votes are restricted to East and West on
Round 1 to avoid wind lock on that round, thus reducing
the impact of one's starting position on the game.

Package Art and Design: Rodger B. MacGowan
Map Illustrations: Knut Grünitz, Mark Simonitch
Card Illustrations: Mike Lemick, Mark Simonitch,
Rodger B. MacGowan

Rules Layout: Tony Nardo, Mark Simonitch
Proofreaders: John Bernardo, Michael Gouker,
Chad Jensen, Dale Yu (English); Timo Heiber
(German); Michel Boucher (French); Fabio
Patricolo (Italian)
Translations: Dario Bagatto, Michael Blumöhr
(German); Jean-Philippe Madelaine, Philippe
Poirier (French); Gianni Sorio, Maurizio Bragaglia
(Italian)
Special Thanks: to Paul Abrahamse, Kim Beattie,
Michael Blumöhr, Chad Jensen, and many others
who have coordinated convention demonstrations
and offered suggestions for the game.

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

12

Winds of Plunder

DEVELOPER'S NOTES
The historical notes given in this section are presented
solely as background to the game's development. They are
not required for play.
While Winds of Plunder is not a historical simulation, the
tales of Caribbean piracy – particularly those from the early
18th century – helped bring the game to its current form.
The introduction sets a stage for the game, where “news
travels faster than navies,” and “the clock is ticking on the
days of easy piracy.” To a small extent the game mirrors that
of the real world at the close of the Golden Age of Piracy.
The Treaty of Utrecht, signed in 1713 to end the War of the
Spanish Succession, opened a new chapter for piracy in the
Americas. Despite the cessation of the war, privateers
continued to harass shipping of all nations in the West
Indies.
King George I's Proclamation for Suppressing of Pyrates
suggests that it was not until June of 1715 that hostilities
formally closed, not until late 1717 that the crown took
action in offering an amnesty, and not even until late 1718
that the amnesty period formally closed. In real life, pirates
most likely witnessed a gradual buildup of forces to curtail
their activity; in the game, we chose to offer a period of no
effective resistance to piracy from the European navies.
Blackbeard is the one pirate from the Golden Age of Piracy
referenced by name in the game components. While there is
disagreement over his actual name (Teach and Thatch are the
two most common forms one will find for his surname) and
his birthplace, there is little doubt over his place in the
history of Caribbean piracy. Teach served in the British navy
during the War of the Spanish Succession, but did not come
into a ship command until joining with Benjamin Hornigold
in acts of piracy after the war.
According to some accounts, at one point in his career
Blackbeard took on the title of magistrate for a “privateer's
republic” based in Nassau. As such, it is appropriate that the
tile for the player who breaks ties and decides on the order of
plunder be named “Blackbeard's tile.”
Examples of game play within these rules feature five pirates
who, while not precisely contemporaries in their careers,
operated in the Caribbean at the close of the Golden Age of
Piracy. Along with the aforementioned Benjamin Hornigold,
these include Stede Bonnet, Bartholomew Roberts (“Black
Bart”), Samuel Bellamy (“Black Sam”), and John Rackham
(“Calico Jack”).
Accounts by Daniel Defoe (A General History of The Pyrates)
of Bonnet's attempts to evade the name of “pirate” could

almost serve as a model for the Swindle card provided in the
game. In one account, Defoe relates that Bonnet's crew took,
“ten or twelve Barrels of Pork, and about 400 Weight of
Bread; but because they would not have this set down to the
Account of Pyracy, they gave them [their victims] eight or
ten casks of Rice, and an old Cable, in lieu thereof.”
Each of the twelve ports presented in the game also played a
role in the history of Caribbean piracy, though not
necessarily during the eighteenth century. The twelve ports
selected offered the best compromise between drawing upon
regional history and preserving the desired flow of the ship
movement mechanism.
One particular island shown on the map, San Salvadore,
bears special note. The name “San Salvador” has been
applied to two neighboring islands in the Caribbean.
Columbus's original logs from the first voyage were lost,
leaving some doubt as to precisely which island he first
made landfall on.
For game purposes, the island now known as Cat Island
serves as San Salvadore. (According to one account, Cat
Island derives its name from a 17th century pirate, Arthur
Catt, who used the island as a hideaway and may have buried
his treasure there.) We have used an older spelling for the
isle to help differentiate it from Watling Island – named after
George Watling, another 17th century pirate – which is
currently called San Salvador.
To those familiar with the history of Caribbean piracy, the
isle of Tortuga is conspicuous in its absence from the map.
At first glance, its connection to the history of Caribbean
piracy seems to make it a better selection for a port than
Santo Domingo or Turks &amp; Caicos. Geographically, it could
even be substituted for Turks &amp; Caicos with no effect on
relative North/South movement in the game.
However, Tortuga was the origin for the “Brethren of the
Coast” – buccaneers who, among other things, followed a
code by which they swore not to steal from one another. This
code ran contrary to a critical game mechanism; namely, the
ability to use Weapons in order to board another player and
steal either Victory Points or a ship item. While diligent
adherence to the code of the Brethren eventually dropped out
of common practice, the historical association between
Tortuga and the “Buccaneer's Code” nonetheless made it
inappropriate to offer Tortuga as a port.
Again, though historical persons, places and events played a
minor role in shaping the background for elements of this
game, Winds of Plunder was designed first and foremost as
a means to entertain. We hope you will find as much
enjoyment in playing this game as we found in its creation!

© 2006 GMT Games, LLC

</rulebook>
			
						                           
						               													<description>Set in the Caribbean at a time when pirates have naught to fear but each other, Winds of Plunder allows 3-5 players to compete for Victory Points (VP) by a variety of means: plundering ports, spreading their fierce reputations in the Caribbean isles, finding buried Treasure, and boarding their opponents. Randomly placed VP tiles dictate the value of each port and the location of Treasure Maps, while a unique tile rotation system helps keep game play fresh. Weapons, Crew, and Provisions may also be found in the various ports, each of which confers its own Advantages during the game and translates to VP's in the end. Action cards enhance a player's ability to gain plunder or to forestall his opponents. Wind Cubes permit players to vie over control over the winds that guide movement and the order of play for each game round. But the clock is ticking on the days of easy piracy! The game lasts 9 rounds, or approximately 60-120 minutes.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;All materials are marked &amp;quot;Copyright 2006.&amp;quot; However, the game was not released until May 2007.&amp;#10;&amp;#10;</description>
										      	               				<yearpublished value="2007" />
						               				<minplayers value="3" />
						               				<maxplayers value="5" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_numplayers" title="User Suggested Number of Players" totalvotes="16">
			
		<results numplayers="1">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="8" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="2">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="8" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="3">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="8" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="1" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="4">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="10" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="5">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="11" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="4" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
			
		<results numplayers="5+">		
					<result value="Best" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Recommended" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="Not Recommended" numvotes="6" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			               				<playingtime value="120" />
						               				<minplaytime value="120" />
						               				<maxplaytime value="120" />
						               				<minage value="10" />
						      			<poll name="suggested_playerage" title="User Suggested Player Age" totalvotes="3">
			<results>		
					<result value="2" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="3" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="4" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="5" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="6" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="8" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="10" numvotes="2" />
					<result value="12" numvotes="1" />
					<result value="14" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="16" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="18" numvotes="0" />
					<result value="21 and up" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			<poll name="language_dependence" title="Language Dependence" totalvotes="5">
			
		<results>		
					<result level="1" value="No necessary in-game text" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="2" value="Some necessary text - easily memorized or small crib sheet" numvotes="4" />
					<result level="3" value="Moderate in-game text - needs crib sheet or paste ups" numvotes="1" />
					<result level="4" value="Extensive use of text - massive conversion needed to be playable" numvotes="0" />
					<result level="5" value="Unplayable in another language" numvotes="0" />
				</results>					
	</poll> 			      			 			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamecategory" id="1090" value="Pirates" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2001" value="Action Points" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2012" value="Auction/Bidding" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2686" value="Take That" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamemechanic" id="2017" value="Voting" />
		
									
			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      			

			      	      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamedesigner" id="205" value="Al Newman" />
		
									
			

			      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="11322" value="Knut Grünitz" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="6548" value="Mike Lemick" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="71" value="Rodger B. MacGowan" />
		
									
				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgameartist" id="140" value="Mark Simonitch" />
		
									
			

			      	      				
		 			

			
		
					<link type="boardgamepublisher" id="52" value="GMT Games" />
		
									
			

			
	

	

	
	
	
   		<statistics page="1">
								<ratings >
			<usersrated value="719" />
			<average value="6.42733" />
			<bayesaverage value="5.76019" />

			<ranks>
															<rank type="subtype" id="1" name="boardgame" friendlyname="Board Game Rank" value="4337" bayesaverage="5.76019" />
																				<rank type="family" id="5496" name="thematic" friendlyname="Thematic Rank" value="691" bayesaverage="5.90638" />
											<rank type="family" id="5497" name="strategygames" friendlyname="Strategy Game Rank" value="1598" bayesaverage="5.83754" />
												</ranks>

			<stddev value="1.41551" />
			<median value="0" />
			<owned value="972" />
			<trading value="102" />
			<wanting value="38" />
			<wishing value="150" />
			<numcomments value="331" />
			<numweights value="115" />
			<averageweight value="2.3652" />
			</ratings>
								</statistics>
     
	
          
</item>
</items>